<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails | Words and Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-03T17:46:08-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vaidehi Joshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hunting Down the Scoop on ActiveRecord Scopes]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/11/03/hunting-down-the-scoop-on-activerecord-scopes/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-03T08:43:46-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/11/03/hunting-down-the-scoop-on-activerecord-scopes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/PzrPi0UVzgYHm" width="480" height="254" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Over the past forty or so Tuesdays &mdash; has it really been that many?! &mdash; I&rsquo;ve written on a spread of topics. There&rsquo;s a slight problem with this: sometimes I forget what I have and haven&rsquo;t written about. Here&rsquo;s a case in point for you: last week, I wrote about <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/10/27/digging-into-the-finder-object-pattern/">finder objects</a>, and casually tossed in some scopes into my models. It turns out, I&rsquo;ve never actually written about how scopes work, or what they really do!</p>

<p>I know, I know, that&rsquo;s pretty terrible of me. I actually learned about scopes awhile ago, and now I use them fairly often in my applications. However, I got so used to writing them, that I never really thought that much about how they work behind the scenes. In fact, when I sat down to write <em>this</em> post, I had to go on a hunt into the Rails source code and Ruby blogosphere to figure out what was going on under the hood every single time I implemented a scope in my code.</p>

<p>The main reason that I like to use <strong>ActiveRecord scopes</strong> is because they allow us to specify commonly-used queries, but encapsulate these queries into methods, which we can then call on our models or association objects. However, my hunt lead me to find out that scopes have been around for awhile in Railsland, so they&rsquo;re not exactly that new. But, what&rsquo;s interesting about them is how their implementation has changed and grown with different releases of Rails. There&rsquo;s also a lot of debate over how and when scopes are different from their counterparts, or simpler class methods. But what makes a scope exactly? Well, it&rsquo;s finally time for us to hunt down the answer to that question.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The simplest of scopes</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/uH37VANhgHDaM" width="480" height="360" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>While developing applications, we often run into a situation where we want to select a particular group of objects (read: rows from our database) based on the characteristics that they share. The basic implementation of scopes can be summed up as this simple idea: being able to narrow down the objects that we want into a specific subset, based on some given parameters. We can tell <code>ActiveRecord</code> (an Object Relational Mapper, or ORM) to select a certain group of objects by implementing a scope that is specific to a model. Luckily, scopes aren&rsquo;t too difficult to define, and mostly adhere to a simple structure.</p>

<p>In our bookstore app for example, we have a <code>Review</code> object, that we allow our users to write about the <code>Book</code>s that they purchase through our store. For now, our <code>Review</code>s belong to a <code>User</code>, and they have some basic attributes which map to columns in our database, including a <code>published_at</code> datetime attribute, that we set when our User clicks the submit button, which saves their &ldquo;drafted&rdquo; review and turns it into a &ldquo;published&rdquo; review.</p>

<p>However, one side effect of having this attribute (and effectively, two different states or &ldquo;types&rdquo; of reviews) is that we now have no obvious form of selecting only our &ldquo;published&rdquo; reviews &mdash; that is to say, reviews that have a <code>published_at</code> date attribute set on them. How can we fix this? Well, we can write a class method that, when invoked, will run a query on our <code>ActiveRecord</code> object and only return the reviews that have this attribute. If we did that, our model might look something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Review &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    belongs_to :user

    def self.published
        where('published_at IS NOT NULL')
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Okay, that&rsquo;s a good start. Remember that the implicit <code>self</code> in the body of this class method is our <code>Review</code> class, so we&rsquo;re basically running <code>Review.where('published_at IS NOT NULL')</code>. But now we run into another problem: this query isn&rsquo;t all that specific, is it? What makes a <code>published</code> review, exactly? Well, it&rsquo;s not just the fact that the <code>published_at</code> date should be set; we also need to account for the fact that some reviews could be set to be published in the <em>future</em>, at a later date. What we <em>really</em> want to select are our reviews that have a <code>published_at</code> date that has already happened; in other words, a date which occurred in the past. We can modify our class method to account for this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Review &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    belongs_to :user

    def self.published
        where('published_at IS NOT NULL AND 
        published_at &lt;= ?', Time.zone.now)
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>If we try out this class method, we can see the exact SQL that gets executed:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">♥ rails c
Loading development environment (Rails 4.1.4)
irb(main):001:0&gt; Review.published
# SELECT "reviews".* FROM "reviews" WHERE "reviews".
"published_at" IS NOT NULL AND "reviews"."published_
at" &lt;= 2015-10-27 08:07:36 -0400
</code></pre>

<p>However, instead of writing this functionality into the body of a class method, we could accomplish the exact same thing by using a scope:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Review &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    belongs_to :user

    scope :published, -&gt; {
        where('published_at IS NOT NULL AND 
        published_at &lt;= ?', Time.zone.now)
    }
end
</code></pre>

<p>which allows us to invoke a method in the console that pretty much looks like the method we had before:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):002:0&gt; Review.published
  Review Load (2.6ms)  SELECT "reviews".* FROM 
  "reviews" WHERE "reviews".
"published_at" IS NOT NULL AND "reviews"."published_
at" &lt;= 2015-10-27 08:07:36 -0400
=&gt; #&lt;ActiveRecord::Relation []&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Okay, wait &mdash; what&rsquo;s going on here?! How did that even happen? Well, let&rsquo;s break it down:</p>

<ol>
<li>First, we&rsquo;re using something called the <code>scope</code> method. This class method is defined within the <code>ActiveRecord::Scoping::Named</code> module.</li>
<li>Second, the <code>scope</code> class method requires two important arguments: a <strong>name</strong> for the scope, and a <strong>callable object</strong> that includes a query criteria. That last part about passing a callable object is pretty important, because only procs and lambdas are callable objects. In fact, that <code>-&gt; {}</code> syntax that we&rsquo;re using is just another way of writing a lambda in Ruby.</li>
<li>Third, and most interestingly, the return value of our scope was an <code>ActiveRecord::Relation</code> object. This is significant because <code>ActiveRecord::Relation</code> objects are <em>not</em> eagerly-loaded &mdash; they&rsquo;re <em>lazily-loaded</em>. Lazy-loading basically means that we&rsquo;re never going to query to the database until we actually <em>need</em> to. What makes this really awesome is that lazy-loading allows us to call more methods (read: scopes galore!) on our returned <code>ActiveRecord::Relation</code> object.</li>
</ol>


<p>It looks like perhaps there&rsquo;s some funky stuff going on here. But, all of these things still don&rsquo;t really answer our burning question: why use a scope when we could just write a class method?!</p>

<h2>Class methods by any other name</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/fwok0XCSAIivm" width="480" height="729" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>What&rsquo;s in a scope? A class method by any other name would smell just as sweet! Oops, I got carried away there. Enough poetry, let&rsquo;s talk prose. Or scopes, rather, and why we might want to use them.</p>

<p>We want to change the implementation of our <code>published</code> class method such that it accepts an argument that makes our query more flexible. Let&rsquo;s say that we want to be able to filter our <code>Review</code>s by a specific publication date. We might now have a class method that looks like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Review &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    belongs_to :user

    def self.published(on)
        where('published_at IS NOT NULL AND 
        published_at &lt;= ?', on)
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>on</code> parameter would ideally be a <code>Date</code> or a <code>Datetime</code> object that would dynamically change the rows that we&rsquo;ll query for in our database. This will behave exactly like we want it to, until&hellip;it breaks. How can we break this? Well, let&rsquo;s say that we now want to order our published reviews by their <code>position</code> attribute, which for the time being, is just an integer. No problem, we can do that, right?</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):003:0&gt; Review.published(Time.zone.now)
    .order(position: asc)
    Review Load (0.2ms)  SELECT "review".* FROM 
    "review"  WHERE (published_at IS NOT NULL AND 
    published_at &lt;= 2015-11-02 08:07:36 -0400) 
    ORDER BY "review"."position" ASC
=&gt; #&lt;ActiveRecord::Relation [#&lt;Review id: 1, published_at: 
"2015-08-02 00:04:22", position: 5&gt;, #&lt;Review id: 2, 
published_at: nil, position: 10, published_at: 
"2015-10-02 00:02:00"&gt;]&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Sure, no problem! This returns exactly what we&rsquo;d expect. But what if we&rsquo;re relying on this method elsewhere and somehow don&rsquo;t pass in a parameter to our <code>published</code> method. What happens then?</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):004:0&gt; Review.published(nil).order(position: asc)
=&gt; NoMethodError: undefined method `order' for nil:NilClass
</code></pre>

<p>BOOM! Everything broke. Oops. What happened here? We tried to call the <code>order</code> method on a falsy object (aka <code>nil</code>). Obviously Ruby is unhappy, because it looks like <code>Review.published(nil)</code> returns <code>nil</code>, which doesn&rsquo;t respond to a method called <code>order</code>!</p>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s go fast forward to our new scope implementation in the Review class:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Review &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    belongs_to :user

    scope :published, -&gt; (on) {
        where('published_at IS NOT NULL AND 
        published_at &lt;= ?', on)
    }
end
</code></pre>

<p>We&rsquo;ve changed our callable object to accept a parameter, which is how we&rsquo;re going to determine our <code>published_at</code> date. We can be pretty certain that this will execute the same query if we pass an actual <em>date</em> to this scope. But what if we pass <code>nil</code> again?</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):005:0&gt; Review.published(nil)
    .order(position: asc)
   Review Load (0.2ms)  SELECT "review".* 
   FROM "review"  WHERE (published_at IS NOT 
   NULL AND published_at &lt;= 2015-11-02 08:07:36 -0400) 
   ORDER BY "review"."position" ASC
=&gt; #&lt;ActiveRecord::Relation [#&lt;Review id: 1, published_at: 
nil, position: 1, created_at: "2015-11-02 00:45:22", 
updated_at: "2015-11-02 00:45:22"&gt;, #&lt;Review id: 2, 
published_at: nil, position: 2, created_at: 
"2015-11-02 00:46:22", updated_at: "2015-11-02 00:46:22"&gt;]&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Well, would you look at that! It didn&rsquo;t break! It ran our expected query, but because scopes return <code>ActiveRecord::Relation</code> objects, it didn&rsquo;t call <code>order</code> on <code>nil</code>, it just kept chaining on to our query. The first part of our query (responsible for finding any reviews that were published on a date) didn&rsquo;t return anything, but the second part of our query (responsible for just ordering whatever got returned by our first query) did work! How, exactly? Well, <a href="http://aspiringwebdev.com/use-activerecord-scopes-not-class-methods-in-rails-to-avoid-errors/">it just so happens</a> that calling a method on a blank <code>ActiveRecord::Relation</code> object returns that same relation. An important thing to note: if we had a query that was scoping down our reviews to ones that were published on a date and ordering <em>those</em> objects by their position, we would have gotten an empty relation:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT "review".* FROM "review"  WHERE 
(published_at IS NOT NULL AND published_at 
&lt;= 2015-11-02 08:07:36 -0400 AND 
(ORDER BY "review"."position" ASC))
</code></pre>

<p>The above query narrows down our scope quite a bit, which we could do if we wanted to specify that to SQL. But in our case, our <code>ORDER BY</code> clause isn&rsquo;t grouped inside of the <code>AND</code>, but instead exists outside of it, which is why we&rsquo;re not getting an empty relation returned to us.</p>

<p>While we&rsquo;re on the topic of relations, it&rsquo;s also important to note that the method we have right now <em>does not</em> return an object to us! Relations are not objects! We&rsquo;d need to explicitly query for a record if we wanted to return it:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):006:0&gt; Review.published(nil)
    .order(position: asc).first
=&gt; #&lt;Review id: 1, published_at: nil, position: 1, 
created_at: "2015-11-02 00:45:22", 
updated_at: "2015-11-02 00:45:22"&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Hopefully we should now be able to easily see that the <code>order</code> method that we&rsquo;re chaining on right there at the end could really be abstracted into its own scope! Let&rsquo;s fix that, shall we?</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Review &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    belongs_to :user

    scope :published, -&gt; (on) {
        where('published_at IS NOT NULL AND 
        published_at &lt;= ?', on)
    }

    scope :ordered, -&gt; { order(position: :asc) } 
end
</code></pre>

<p>Much better. Now we can just chain on our <code>order</code> scope to our <code>published</code> scope without ever having to worry that our scopes will break. But wait, there&rsquo;s even more we can do with scopes!</p>

<h2>Special scope tricks</h2>

<p>Because scopes accept lambdas and procs, we can pass in different arguments. We did that before when we passed in a datetime parameter. But this kind of flexibility can be especially powerful, because we can do things like pass in limits:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Review &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    scope :published, -&gt; (limit: 20) {
        where('published_at IS NOT NULL AND 
        published_at &lt;= ?', Time.zone.now)
    }
end
</code></pre>

<p>This will run our same SQL query, but will add <code>LIMIT 10</code> to the end of it. We can customize this scope further, or we can add more if we need to. We also might want to just perpetually apply a scope to all queries on a specific model. When we run into this situation, we can use the <code>default_scope</code> method.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Review &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    default_scope -&gt; { order(published_at: :desc) }
end
</code></pre>

<p>This will automatically append all of our SQL queries on this model with <code>ORDER BY "review"."position" DESC</code>. What&rsquo;s really nice about having a default scope is that we don&rsquo;t need to write and perpetually call a method named something like <code>by_published_date</code> on this model; it will be applied and invoked by default on all instances of this class.</p>

<p>According to <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/active_record_querying.html#scopes">the documentation</a>, if we want to get <em>super</em> fancy with our default scope and have so much logic that it&rsquo;s bursting from our callable object&rsquo;s so-called seams, we can also define it in an alternate way as a class method:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Review &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  def self.default_scope
    # Get fancy in here, but just make sure 
    # to return an ActiveRecord::Relation.
    # Otherwise, any scopes we chain onto 
    # this will automatically break!
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>We&rsquo;re also not limited to just using the <code>where</code> method! We can use plenty of other <code>ActiveRecord::Relation</code> methods, such as <code>joins</code> or <code>includes</code>, which will eager load other relations when we want to. Here&rsquo;s a handy scope we could add to our <code>Shipment</code> model that <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/10/27/digging-into-the-finder-object-pattern/">we built out</a> last week:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Shipment &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    default_scope -&gt; { includes(:order, :line_items) }
end
</code></pre>

<p>This is pretty cool because we&rsquo;re using our <code>default_scope</code> method to automatically eager-load our associated <code>order</code> and <code>line_items</code> on our <code>shipment</code> without having to make two additional queries just to load them! As is the case with <code>includes</code>, it might not always be a good idea to do this, since we could be loading more records than we want, or could get stuck with a n+1 situation on our hands. But if we know what we&rsquo;re doing and are sure that this scope is necessary, it can be pretty powerful.</p>

<p>We can also merge two scopes together, which effectively allows us to mix and match different <code>WHERE</code> conditions and group them together in SQL with an <code>AND</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Shipment &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    scope :shipped -&gt; { where(state: 'shipped') }
    scope :damaged -&gt; { where(condition: 'damaged') }
end
</code></pre>

<p>which we can then merge into a single SQL query by chaining our scopes together:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):007:0&gt; Shipment.shipped.received
=&gt; SELECT "shipments".* FROM "shipments" WHERE 
"shipments"."state" = 'shipped' AND "shipments".
"condition" = 'damaged'
</code></pre>

<p>We&rsquo;ll notice that in this situation, our <code>WHERE</code> clauses are grouped together with an <code>AND</code>, which can help us when it comes to writing super specific queries.</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/OIIB1hkbwFs76" width="480" height="339" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>ActiveRecord scopes give us a lot of flexibility, even though they are effectively defining a class method on a model. The fundamental difference between them however, is that scopes should always return an <code>ActiveRecord::Relation</code> object, which makes them forever chainable!</li>
<li>How does the <code>scope</code> method actually work? I&rsquo;m not sure that I understand all of it, but perhaps you will! Check it out in the <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/428d47adfed8d6aa7b21aec2bf5ad890961c9de3/activerecord/lib/active_record/scoping/named.rb#L143">Rails source code</a>!</li>
<li>There are a few great primers on writing effective scopes, like <a href="http://www.informit.com/articles/article.aspx?p=2220311">this one</a>, and this <a href="http://blog.plataformatec.com.br/2013/02/active-record-scopes-vs-class-methods/">other one</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Digging Into the Finder Object Pattern]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/10/27/digging-into-the-finder-object-pattern/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-27T08:58:31-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/10/27/digging-into-the-finder-object-pattern</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/y5A0PlFbGIk4o" width="480" height="280" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Most developers aren&rsquo;t ever <em>completely</em> happy with their code. I&rsquo;m no exception to this stereotype &mdash; I almost always know that I could probably write a cleaner, more concise method, controller, or class. Usually, it&rsquo;s a matter of not know the best tool to reach for to refactor my code; eventually, I learn a new pattern or form of encapuslating logic that I later use to make my old code a lot better.</p>

<p>But a few weeks ago, I wrote 100 lines of beautiful code. I&rsquo;m talking about a goregous, straightforward, no-nonsense class that did a lot in a relatively few lines of Ruby. I still feel pretty proud of it (can you tell?), and part of the reason for this is because I also learned a new pattern while writing this class. I was actually pairing with another developer, and we wanted to try using a rather common Rails pattern to solve a problem we were running into again and again: messy queries in our controllers and models.</p>

<p>We both were familiar with the concept of &ldquo;skinny controllers&rdquo; and &ldquo;fat models&rdquo;, or the idea that your controllers shouldn&rsquo;t be responsible for containing the logic specific to a model. However, we also didn&rsquo;t want our models to get out of control in size, which is exactly what was starting to happen. So, we searched for a workaround, and found our answer in one of the most elegant patterns I&rsquo;ve seen in awhile: <strong>finder objects</strong>. Finder objects are simple Ruby classes that encapuslate the logic behind querying the database, and they are hands down, my new favorite kind of Ruby object.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Scopin&#8217; Down The Problem of Scopes</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/Y6eQqv3jdV4RO" width="480" height="360" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>In our bookstore application, we have <code>Order</code> objects, which represent the orders that a user places in our system. However, these are books that we&rsquo;re dealing with, and eventually we need to address the whole fulfillment process, which will need to be represented by a whole other set of models. For now, we&rsquo;ll try to keep it as simple as possible. Let&rsquo;s say that an <code>Order</code> has many <code>Shipments</code>, and each shipment represents a batch of <code>Book</code> objects (read: products) that need to be shipped out together.</p>

<p>Right off the bat, we know that our <code>Shipment</code> model will have some kind of state machine that will need to track the different stages of the shipment phase. Again, to keep it simple, let&rsquo;s say that there are five different stages or <code>state</code>s of a shipment:</p>

<ol>
<li>A shipment starts off as <code>processing</code> once an order has been placed.</li>
<li>Once it has been processed, it needs a label with the shipping address information, so it transitions to the <code>needs_label</code> state.</li>
<li>After it has a label generated, it&rsquo;ll need a tracking number, so transitions to the <code>needs_tracking</code> state.</li>
<li>Once it has a tracking number, it transitions to being <code>ready</code> for shipment.</li>
<li>Finally, when the shipment is actually sent out of the warehouse and to our shipping service, it should be marked as <code>shipped</code>.</li>
</ol>


<p>To be clear, this is a <em>super</em> simplified version of what would happen in a real-life application! Now, in our admin panel, let&rsquo;s say that we have a page that will render all of our shipments, which should always ordered by when they were created, so that our admins know which shipments to process, and in which order.</p>

<p>We can take it a step further and say that our main admin panel page &mdash; which will correspond to the <code>index</code> action in our controller, should show our admins the most urgent shipments that need their attention as soon as they log in; in other words, these would be the shipments that were created more than a week ago, but still haven&rsquo;t been processed.</p>

<p>I think we can all agree that basic Rails best practices should steer us away from doing something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ShipmentsController &lt; ApplicationController
  def index
    @shipments = Shipment.where(state: :ready)
            .where('created_at &lt;= ?', Time.zone.now + 7.days)
               .order(created_at: :desc)
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>We <em>definitely</em> know that the controller really shouldn&rsquo;t be responsible for querying for the correct <code>Shipment</code> objects. All our controller should have to do is just render the correct ones, and not go digging for them in the database!</p>

<p>Okay, so we&rsquo;ll create some scopes for these queries instead. These scopes should live in our model, not in the controller, right? Let&rsquo;s see what our model might look like if we take that approach:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Shipment &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    belongs_to :order

    default_scope -&gt; { order(created_at: :desc) }
    scope :shipped, -&gt; { where(state: 'shipped') }
    scope :urgent, -&gt; {
        where('created_at &lt;= ?', Time.zone.now + 7.days)
    }
end
</code></pre>

<p>This cleans things up a decent bit! Scopes are actually part of the Active Record Query Interface, and they allow us to specify commonly-used queries which we can then actually reference and use in the form of method calls on our models themselves. They are really nothing more than defining class methods on a model:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Shipment &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    def self.shipped
        where(state: 'shipped')
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>However, they&rsquo;re pretty wonderful because you can just chain them as method calls (<code>Shipment.urgent.shipped</code>), but all they do is execute the correct query for you:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">Shipment.shipped
=&gt; SELECT "shipments".* FROM "shipments" WHERE "shipments"."state" = "shipped"
</code></pre>

<p>But the good news about scopes is also the bad <a href="news:">news:</a> you can just keep adding them and adding them, and chaining them onto everything. Our <code>Shipment</code> class has only three scopes at the moment, one of them being the <code>default</code> scope. But, we&rsquo;ll probably have a page that should only render only the shipments that are in the <code>needs_label</code> state, or a page that maps to a controller action which should only return shipments that are in the <code>needs_tracking</code> state. We <em>could</em> keep adding scopes and then have our controller actions call the scopes on the class to return the appropriate shipments from our database.</p>

<p>Or, we could try something a little different.</p>

<h2>Finder Objects</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/12bpEjD05ac2IM" width="480" height="269" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Our scopes don&rsquo;t actually add any new behavior to our model. As we saw earlier, they are nothing more than macros for querying for the correct rows from our <code>shipments</code> table in our database. So, it really doesn&rsquo;t make sense for our model to contain all this logic that doesn&rsquo;t <em>add</em> any new behavior to it.</p>

<p>It would be nice, however, if we could apply the rule of &ldquo;separation of concerns&rdquo; here, and have an entire class whose sole responsibility would be to dig up the correct objects based on the parameters we were querying by. Really, this class should do nothing more than <em>find the right objects</em>. You might even say that instances of this class are just&hellip;<em>finder objects</em>! (Get it? Man, I really hope you got it.)</p>

<p>Anyways, how might this class look? Well, we don&rsquo;t need any of the functionality from ActiveRecord, so we can create it as just a Plain Old Ruby Class:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ShipmentFinder
end
</code></pre>

<p>Next, we&rsquo;ll want to tell our finder object which models to query for, so it will know how to construct our queries, and which table to query. Since we never really want to have this method accessible elsewhere, we can make it a private class method that will only be called from the context of another <code>ShipmentFinder</code> class method:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ShipmentFinder
    class &lt;&lt; self
        private
        def resource_class
            ::Shipment
        end
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now, we can use Rails&#8217; <a href="https://github.com/rails/arel">arel DSL</a> to construct a basic query. To do this, we&rsquo;ll need a method that returns the table, which can also be a private method since we&rsquo;ll never want to call it explicitly:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ShipmentFinder
    class &lt;&lt; self
      private

      def table
        resource_class.arel_table
      end

      def resource_class
        ::Shipment
      end
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now, we can write as many specific queries as we want. For example, we could write a <code>urgent_needs_tracking</code> class method that could constructs a query using two private methods, <code>needs_tracking</code> and <code>is_ready</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ShipmentFinder
    class &lt;&lt; self
      def urgent_needs_tracking
        query = needs_tracking.and(is_ready)

        resource_class.where(query)
      end

      def shipped
        resource_class.where(state: 'shipped')
      end

      private

      def urgent
        resource_class.where('created_at &lt;= ?', Time.zone.now + 7.days))
      end

      def is_ready
        table[:state].eq('ready')
      end

      def needs_tracking
        table[:state].eq('needs_tracking')
      end

      def needs_label
        table[:state].eq('needs_label')
      end

      def table
        resource_class.arel_table
      end

      def resource_class
        ::Shipment
      end
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now we can rely on our <code>ShipmentFinder</code> class to find our shipments that have been created more than 7 days ago, and still don&rsquo;t have a tracking number. We also can add more functionality that can be used in specific instances, which is exactly what we&rsquo;ve done with our <code>needs_label</code> and <code>is_ready</code> private methods. We can use arel to construct queries using those methods to scope down what objects are actually returned. We don&rsquo;t have to do anything fancy, if we don&rsquo;t want to. Take a look at that <code>shipped</code> method &mdash; this is just using a simple <code>where</code> arel method to construct a query that reads like this: <code>SELECT "shipments".* FROM "shipments" WHERE "shipments"."state" = "shipped"</code>.</p>

<p>Finally, the last step: it&rsquo;s time for us to actually call on our finder object to do its job!</p>

<h2>Cleaner Querying, Cleaner Controllers</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s bring it all together by going back to our <code>ShipmentsController</code> and add our new finder object into it. Our <code>index</code> action should now be able to account for different types of shipments that our admins might want to query for. For now, we&rsquo;ll construct our controller to accept a query parameter in our params hash that will be that <code>status</code> of the types of shipments we want to return. Depending on the frontend framework we&rsquo;re using, this might be a dropdown or checkbox option that will set a value on the <code>status</code> key in our params hash.</p>

<p>Our controller action could now be rewritten to look something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ShipmentsController &lt; ApplicationController
  def index
    status = params[:status]
    status_method = status.to_sym

    if ShipmentFinder.respond_to?(status_method)
            @shipments = ShipmentFinder.send(status_method)
        else
            @shipments = Shipment.all
        end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Here, we&rsquo;re accessing the query param from <code>params[:status]</code>, and turning it into a symbol (<code>status_method</code>). Next, we&rsquo;re using Ruby&rsquo;s super handy <code>respond_to?</code> method, and sending our <code>status_method</code> symbol to our <code>ShipmentFinder</code>. So, if our admin selects an option that sends the query param <code>urgent_needs_tracking</code>, we are telling our finder object to call that method, and execute that query. The return value of the query executed by our <code>ShipmentFinder</code>&rsquo;s <code>urgent_needs_tracking</code> method is what will be set as the instance variable <code>@shipments</code> for the duration of this action on the controller.</p>

<p>If no query param is set, or if our <code>ShipmentFinder</code> doesn&rsquo;t have a method that maps to a query param, we&rsquo;re just returning all of our <code>Shipment</code> objects by default.</p>

<p>This is quite an improvement from our earlier code, which had our controller digging for rows in a database that it really didn&rsquo;t have anything to do with. Now, we&rsquo;ve separated our concerns into a new finder object, which exists as its own query interface on its own. It&rsquo;s also worth noting that sometimes, creating a finder object can be overkill, and sometimes, if we have a lot of finder objects, we&rsquo;d probably want to abstract a lot of this functionality out into a <code>BaseFinder</code> class, which our finder objects could inherit from. But this is definitely a great start. No more digging for us!</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/FqEDV3gjMhqRG" width="480" height="267" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>The finder object pattern helps keep your model logic strictly related to a class&#8217; behavior, while also keeping your controller&rsquo;s skinny. Since they are nothing more than plain old Ruby classes, finder objects don&rsquo;t need to inherit from <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>, and should be responsible for nothing more than executing queries. Read more about them on this <a href="http://twin.github.io/finder-objects/">fantastic blog post</a>.</li>
<li>Scopes are a great tool to use if a finder object seems like more work than it&rsquo;s really worth, given the size and context of your application. Read more about scopes in the Rails <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/active_record_querying.html#scopes">documentation</a>.</li>
<li>Want to see more examples of implementing finder objects? Check out this <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/weppos/maintaining-a-5yo-ruby-project-shark-edition?slide=103">slidedeck</a> series.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solutions for Slugs of All Sizes: Acts_as_url + To_param]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/10/20/solutions-for-slugs-of-all-sizes-acts-as-url-plus-to-param/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-20T08:17:21-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/10/20/solutions-for-slugs-of-all-sizes-acts-as-url-plus-to-param</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/g5FB33d3GVUkg" width="480" height="288" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Last week was my first week of working from home, which meant two things: spending a lot of time with my computer and limited time with other human beings and, more importantly, debugging things on my own without having anyone nearby to ask for help. The latter of the two actually ended up reaffirming the fact that I actually <em>can</em> debug a decent amount of things on my own if I just power through and am stubborn enough to not give up.</p>

<p>I also learned something interesting about the debugging process: while we&rsquo;re learning, we often solve the same problem again and again. At least, this was the case for one of the features I was working on which involved using an object&rsquo;s slug to generate a url. As I started thinking through how to approach solving this, I immediately had the feeling that I had done something similar in another project. Digging through another repository&rsquo;s source code confirmed my suspicions, and I rediscovered the <code>stringex</code> gem and its multiple libraries, including <code>acts_as_url</code>!</p>

<p>All of this begs the question: why didn&rsquo;t I remember that this gem existed &mdash; or that I had already used it? My guess is that it&rsquo;s because I neither wrote about it nor understood how it worked until a few days ago. This week, it&rsquo;s time to rectify that situation and dive into the <code>acts_as_url</code> library and find a solution for all slug problems, once and for all!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Other Kind of Slug</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/C1aCu8kUyF6p2" width="480" height="350" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>We all are familiar with the Rails mantra of <em>convention over configuration</em>, aka making the lives of developers easier by eliminating the need for them to make decisions about how to structure their code. Now, this design paradigm is pretty fantastic, particularly when we&rsquo;re first learning a new framework. But eventually, there comes a time when we need to tweak our code&rsquo;s conventions just a tiny little bit.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s an example of this? Well, take Rails convention of finding an object by it&rsquo;s <code>id</code>. This standardization pops up all over the place, but the one that we&rsquo;re particularly concerned with is the generation of a url. By default, Rails applications will build a URL path for the <code>show</code> action of any given controller based on the primary key (aka the <code>id</code> column in our database) of the object that we&rsquo;re trying to &ldquo;show&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s put this in context of our bookstore application. We have a bunch of <code>Book</code> objects, and we want to iterate through their titles and then link to their individual &ldquo;show&rdquo; pages. A very basic, not-at-all-fancy template might look something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="slim">h2 Books!
- @books.each do |book|
    p = link_to book.title, book_path(book)
</code></pre>

<p>It&rsquo;s important to note that we&rsquo;re actually passing in the <code>book</code> instance here &mdash; an <code>ActiveRecord</code> object, and <em>not</em> the <code>book</code>&rsquo;s <code>id</code>. Why is this important? Because there&rsquo;s a method that Rails is using to convert the <code>Book</code> object into a URL in order to generate the correct address for our <code>book_path</code>. That&rsquo;s why we need to pass it an <code>ActiveRecord</code> object, because the method that&rsquo;s being called expects an object and returns the <code>id</code> as parameters in the url. What does this look like, exactly? Well, right now our <code>book_path</code> takes a <code>Book</code> instance and creates a path that looks like this: <code>localhost:3000/books/25</code>.</p>

<p>Which is fine! Actually, it&rsquo;s more than fine: it&rsquo;s the expected behavior given our Rails mantra of convention over configuration. But, what if we actually <em>want</em> to configure this a little bit more. What if, instead of using the primary key of our <code>Book</code> instances, we wanted to use the title of the book? It would be lovely if we could link someone to a particular book&rsquo;s page with a more human-readable url (for example, something like <code>awesomebookstore.com/books/the-bell-jar</code> in production).</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a solution for this problem, and it&rsquo;s called slugs. Slugs are a solution for semantic URL generation, which is also sometimes referred to as &ldquo;RESTful&rdquo; or &ldquo;SEO-friendly&rdquo; URL generation. As our application grows, not only would we want our URLs to be user-friendly, but we probably also will want them to be optimized for search engine results. So, we need to change our application&rsquo;s configuration to use a slug.</p>

<p><em>Protip:</em> if anyone ever pop quizzes you about where the term &ldquo;slug&rdquo; comes from, you can totally school them with the following interesting fact: a &ldquo;slug&rdquo; used to be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slug_(publishing)">a shorter name</a> given to a newspaper article while it was in production; during the editing process, the article would be labeled by its slug, which would more specifically indicate the content of the story to the editors and reporters. The more you know, amirite?</p>

<p>There are obviously a lot of ways to approach this, but why reinvent the wheel by writing a bunch of methods that someone else has already written? Let&rsquo;s make use of someone&rsquo;s open source work and use the <code>acts_as_url</code> library to get the job done for us!</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t Let Slugs Slow You Down</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/11zeCgKZ1MaNuE" width="480" height="342" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>The <code>acts_as_url</code> library is actually part of the <code>stringex</code> gem, which adds some useful extensions to Ruby&rsquo;s <code>String</code> class. After we add this gem to our <code>Gemfile</code> (<code>gem "stringex"</code>) and run <code>bundle install</code>, we can get started doing a quick setup.</p>

<p>The documentation for this library is fairly straightforward, and a quick read-through gives us a good idea of what we need to do in order to make it work properly. The basic implementation of this library is four-fold:</p>

<ol>
<li>We need a column in our database that will map to the attribute used in generating our url.</li>
<li>We need to call the <code>acts_as_url</code> method in our model using the attribute name that we want to use for generating our url.</li>
<li>We need to override Rails&#8217; <code>to_param</code> method (Confused? Hang tight, we&rsquo;ll get there in a second!)</li>
<li>We need to <code>find_by</code> our new url attribute inside of our controllers.</li>
</ol>


<p>Let&rsquo;s take it step by step. First, we&rsquo;ll write a migration that will add a <code>slug</code> column to our <code>books</code> database. This is going to be the column that will map to a <code>slug</code> attribute on our <code>Book</code> objects:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddSlugColumnToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_column :books, :slug, :string
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Once we run <code>rake db:migrate</code> and add this attribute, we will want to add the <code>acts_as_url</code> class method to our <code>Book</code> model.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Book &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  acts_as_url :title, url_attribute: :slug
end
</code></pre>

<p>The default behavior of this method expects that we have a column and attribute called <code>url</code> on our object. Since we aren&rsquo;t using the default attribute name, we need to specify the name of the attribute that we&rsquo;re using to store the generated url string. Thankfully, <code>acts_as_url</code> takes a bunch of options, including <code>url_attribute</code>, which is what we&rsquo;re using here. There are some other useful options <a href="https://github.com/rsl/stringex">worth checking out</a> in the documentation, including <code>scope</code>, <code>limit</code>, <code>truncate_words</code>, and <code>blacklist</code>.</p>

<p>Next, we&rsquo;ll need to override Rail&rsquo;s <code>to_param</code> method in order to actually <em>use</em> our generated url attribute. Basically, we&rsquo;ll just want to write our own <code>to_param</code> method and return our <code>slug</code> attribute from inside of it.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Book &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  acts_as_url :title, url_attribute: :slug

  def to_param
    slug
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>And finally, we need to make sure that we&rsquo;re finding our object using the appropriate attribute from within the context of our controller. The documentation suggests we use
the <code>find_by_url</code> method, but we could also use the <code>find_by</code> method in our controller as well.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class BooksController &lt; ApplicationController
  def show
    @book = Book.find_by(slug: params[:id]).decorate
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Nothing changes about how our controller works and we can still do all the fancy things we were doing before, like use a decorator (<a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/01/13/tidying-up-those-views-using-decorators-in-rails/">Remember those?</a>). The only thing that happens now is that our original <code>book_path</code> helper will now use the <code>book</code> instance we passed it to generate a url with a slug instead of the primary key!</p>

<p>Success! We&rsquo;ve done it! Actually, we&rsquo;ve <em>almost</em> done it. One tiny little thing that I always forget is all of the books that already exist in our database. What about them? They all have a <code>slug</code> attribute, sure, and a <code>slug</code> column &ndash; but there&rsquo;s a slight problem: the column is empty! So we can&rsquo;t <code>find_by</code> the <code>slug</code> attribute for those books, can we? In fact, if we try to call <code>to_param</code> on any of our preexisting <code>Book</code> instances right now, all we&rsquo;ll get is <code>nil</code>!</p>

<p>No worries, we just need to call a method inside of our console:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">♥ rails c
Loading development environment (Rails 4.1.4)
irb(main):001:0&gt; Book.initialize_urls
</code></pre>

<p>Now all of the <code>Book</code> instances that had empty <code>slug</code> attributes have ben initialized, and we&rsquo;re good to go! Right? Wrong. Because I haven&rsquo;t explained the whole <code>to_param</code> situation yet, and I promised that I would get to it. Now&rsquo;s the time to figure out the magic behind that!</p>

<h2>Rails Non-Sluggish Solution: <code>to_param</code></h2>

<p>The Rails solution to generating params for an object&rsquo;s url path comes from its elegant <code>to_param</code> method. By default, this method just calls <code>to_s</code> on a Plain Old Ruby Object, and converts it to an instance of Ruby&rsquo;s <code>String</code> class. However, there are plenty of places where Rails itself <em>overrides</em> this method (which explains why we also have to do it in the context of our own controller)!</p>

<p>In fact, the Rails documentation even explains when and how to go about redefining the implementation of this method:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Notably, the Rails routing system calls <code>to_param</code> on models to get a value for the <code>:id</code> placeholder. <code>ActiveRecord::Base#to_param</code> returns the <code>id</code> of a model, but you can redefine that method in your models.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<pre><code class="ruby">class User
  def to_param
    "#{id}-#{name.parameterize}"
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Of course, we could have easily redefined this in the context of each of our models, but using the <code>acts_as_url</code> library reduces the amount of duplicated code that we need in each of our models, and is pretty sophisticated in that it allows us to use <em>different</em> attributes across different models to generate our url path.</p>

<p>Interestingly, <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/7f18ea14c893cb5c9f04d4fda9661126758332b5/activemodel/lib/active_model/conversion.rb#L71">the source code</a> for Rails&#8217; <code>to_param</code> method reveals some elegant checks as well. This method first checks whether the object as been persisted to the database, and then returns a string representing the object&rsquo;s key. We can actually see how the <code>to_key</code> method is being called from <em>inside</em> of <code>to_param</code>, and how the default return value of an unpersisted object&rsquo;s param will be <code>nil</code>. This is the magic that goes on under the hood when we were trying to find the <code>slug</code> attributes for all of those <code>Book</code> instances before we called <code>initialize_urls</code> on them!</p>

<p>So, even though slugs have a <em>reputation</em> of being slow, now we know how to speed through this problem with an elegant and quick solution! I can&rsquo;t say the same for this poor guy, though:</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/1KJPg114jm68U" width="480" height="169" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>The <code>acts_as_url</code> library expects an <code>url</code> attribute on a model, and uses that to generate the path for an object. You need to override Rails&#8217; <code>to_param</code> method that, by default, will use the <code>id</code> of an object to generate its path.</li>
<li>This <a href="https://gist.github.com/jcasimir/1209730">awesome gist</a> by Jeff Casimir is the best write-up on slugs and Rails&#8217; url generation out there. Give it a read!</li>
<li>The original <code>to_param</code> method used to be defined inside of <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>, but has since moved to the <code>ActiveModel::Conversion</code> module, which handles default conversions, including <code>to_model</code>, <code>to_key</code>, and <code>to_partial_path</code>. Read more about how these methods work in the Conversion <a href="http://apidock.com/rails/ActiveModel/Conversion">module documentation</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stop Worrying and Start Being Concerned: ActiveSupport Concerns]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/10/13/stop-worrying-and-start-being-concerned-activesupport-concerns/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-13T09:22:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/10/13/stop-worrying-and-start-being-concerned-activesupport-concerns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/iQA2hMPX88icM" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>A few weeks ago, while learning everything I never knew about <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/09/29/using-pundit-the-cool-kid-of-authorization/">user authorization</a>, I also stumbled upon a cool refactoring pattern that I didn&rsquo;t even know existed. This pattern is based on the simple idea of Ruby modules and mixins, but is particularly handy when it comes to dealing with class methods and callbacks.</p>

<p>ActiveSupport is a pretty massive component within Rails, and it&rsquo;s responsible for a ton of different functionality, including language extensions and utilities. I last wrote about ActiveSupport back when we were exploring the <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/inflections-everywhere-using-activesupport-inflector/">Rails inflector</a> and the libraries it provides for handling the pluralization of different strings. This was way back in September, and at the time, my understanding of ActiveSupport was pretty limited. It turns out that yes, ActiveSupport does provide a bunch of different patterns to transform simple Ruby strings&hellip;but it also has a lot more going on inside of it. For example, the <strong>ActiveSupport Concern module</strong>, which only recently made its debut in Rails 4.</p>

<p>The ActiveSupport::Concern wrapper is an interesting way of encapsulating&hellip;well, certain functionality that you might be <em>concerned</em> with. These concerns take advantage of two directories that are automatically part of the load path within a Rails application: <code>app/models/concerns</code> and <code>app/controllers/concerns</code>. So, how do you write a concern, and what should go inside of it? Don&rsquo;t worry, that&rsquo;s exactly what we&rsquo;ll concern ourselves with next.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Should We Be Concerned?</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/374pcIBVEGb6g" width="480" height="269" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Concerns are meant to make our lives less complicated. Or at the very least, we should be less concerned about the quality of our code if we use concerns, right? But what are ActiveSupport&rsquo;s Concerns really meant to be used for? And how do we know if we should be using them? Well, to answer this question, we can turn to the creator of Rails himself. In a blog post pre-Rails 4 titled <em>Put chubby models on a diet with concerns</em>, DHH explains when and why to consider using ActiveSupport&rsquo;s Concern module:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Concerns encapsulate both data access and domain logic about a certain slice of responsibility. Concerns are also a helpful way of extracting a slice of model that doesn’t seem part of its essence (what is and isn’t in the essence of a model is a fuzzy line and a longer discussion) without going full-bore Single Responsibility Principle and running the risk of ballooning your object inventory.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>When we talk about concerns, what we really are honing in on is the most effective <em>separation of concerns</em>. I really like the way that David thinks of models having an &ldquo;essence&rdquo;, and I think that this is a great way of approaching when and when <em>not</em> to use a concern.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at our bookstore application. We have an <code>User</code> model for anyone that signs up to use our application. Whenever a <code>User</code> signs up, we want to send them an email telling them that they&rsquo;ve been registered, and probably highlighting some of the cool things that they can do to set up their profile on our application. Now, this seems like something that only the <code>User</code> model would be concerned with, right? Well, yes, until we realize that we have another model that needs to share this same functionality!</p>

<p>For example, we now have organizations that want to sign up for our application. They also need to receive the same email and be &ldquo;registered&rdquo;. As our application grows, we might even want to create a <code>Registration</code> model, which would belong to an <code>User</code> and <code>Organization</code>. Now, obviously we could accomplish what we wanted to by just adding the same lines of code to both models, but that makes for neither DRY code, nor a great separation of concerns. But wouldn&rsquo;t it be great if we could take this piece of &ldquo;registration&rdquo; functionality, wrap it up, and only pull it out when we need to use it? It turns out that is exactly what we can do with <code>ActiveSupport::Concern</code>.</p>

<h2>Extending Our Concerns</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/dnNuJUQvEnmjC" width="480" height="269" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Before we write our concern, let&rsquo;s look at what our <code>User</code> model looks like. Here&rsquo;s a truncated version that contains only the logic pertaining to registering a user:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    after_commit :register_user, on: :create

    def register_user
        # Where our logic for registering a user
        # would go. Would call on a background job
        # to perform and send our registration email.
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>We very well <em>could</em> stick this inside of our <code>organization.rb</code> model file, but there&rsquo;s a better way to do this. There are a few steps to creating a concern, the first of which is recognizing where to put it! Since we&rsquo;re creating a concern for a model, this will live inside of our <code>app/models/concerns</code> directory. We&rsquo;ll call this concern a  <code>Registerer</code> concern, since that&rsquo;s its single responsibility, and we can preemptively namespace our concern under <code>Users</code>, which would make its path <code>app/models/concerns/users/registerer.rb</code>.</p>

<p>Next, we&rsquo;ll want to <code>extend</code> the Rails <code>ActiveSupport::Concern</code> module itself from within our concern:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">module Users
    module Registerer
        extend ActiveSupport::Concern
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now, for the actual writing, there&rsquo;s one method that&rsquo;s going to be our new best friend: the <code>included</code> method, which takes a block. A little-known fact about this callback is that it&rsquo;s actually defined by Ruby&rsquo;s <code>Module</code> class, and it&rsquo;s called whenever a module is &ldquo;included&rdquo; into another class or module. This is where we&rsquo;ll put the important class methods and callbacks that we want to be shared amongst the models that will use our concern.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">module Users
    module Registerer
        extend ActiveSupport::Concern

        included do
            has_one :registration, dependent: :destroy

            after_commit :register_user, on: :create
        end

        def register_user
            send_registration_email(self)

            touch(:registered_at)
        end

        def send_registration_email(self)
            RegistrationEmailerJob.perform_later(self)
        end
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This is mostly straightforward. All the logic for a registration now lives in this single file, including the creating of a registration association on our target object (in this case, the <code>User</code> model), the registering of a user by passing our <code>User</code> instance (<code>self</code>) to our <code>RegistrationEmailerJob</code>, and the updating of the <code>registered_at</code> attribute on our <code>User</code> model using the <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/09/22/working-hard-or-hardly-working-part-2-custom-jobs/">touch method</a> &mdash; assuming, of course, that we&rsquo;ve defensively coded this attribute onto our <code>User</code> model. We&rsquo;re also able to use the <code>after_commit</code> callback hook, since the <code>included</code> method can accept callback names as parameters.</p>

<p>Now that we have all this code in one place, how do we add it to our model? Well, we can do it in a single line:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    include Users::Registerer
end
</code></pre>

<p>All we need to do is <code>include</code> our concern, just as we would a module. And down the road, when we find out that we need to create <code>Organization</code> model that shares this set of functionality, all we need to do is add the exact same line to our new model:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Organization &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    include Users::Registerer
end
</code></pre>

<p>And here&rsquo;s the really nice part about utilizing concerns in this way: when we realize that we need to change how this works &mdash; maybe we need to add another job or service object, or perhaps another, more specific callback &mdash; we can add it to one place and update our logic in a single file! This ties in quite nicely to DHH&rsquo;s point of a model&rsquo;s &ldquo;essence&rdquo;. In this case, being able to be &ldquo;registered&rdquo; isn&rsquo;t necessarily something that pertains to the <code>User</code> model specifically. But, it also doesn&rsquo;t need to be its own <em>object</em> per se. Instead, we really just need a set of methods that can be available to be invoked upon an object, which is exactly what <code>ActiveSupport::Concern</code> provides us with.</p>

<h2>Helpful Inclusion</h2>

<p>Because concerns are so simple to extend and include, there are lots of use cases for them. We learned earlier that Rails comes with two <code>concerns</code> directories preloaded: one for <code>models</code>, and another for <code>controllers</code>. Let&rsquo;s look at a practical example for using <code>ActiveSupport::Concern</code> in the context of a controller.</p>

<p>We <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/09/29/using-pundit-the-cool-kid-of-authorization/">recently added</a> the <code>pundit</code> gem to our bookstore app for user authorization. But we only had a few controller actions that actually <em>needed</em> to be authorized; the rest of our controllers didn&rsquo;t need any authorization, because they could be accessed by anyone. Our <code>Reviews</code> controller was being authorized, for example, but our <code>Comments</code> controller didn&rsquo;t need any authorization whatsoever.</p>

<p>So, for the controllers that <em>didn&rsquo;t</em> need authorization, what did we do? Well, we were adding some <code>skip_after_actions</code> lines, which were instructions that the <code>pundit</code> gem documentation had given us:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class CommentsController &lt; ApplicationController
  skip_after_action :verify_authorized
  skip_after_action :verify_policy_scoped

  # RESTful controller actions go here!
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now, imagine we also have a <code>BlogsController</code> with just an <code>index</code> action API endpoint, which doesn&rsquo;t need to be authorized. And maybe we also have <code>TagsController</code>, which also doesn&rsquo;t need to be authorized by <code>pundit</code>. We <em>could</em> copy and paste these two lines into every single controller&hellip;<em>or</em>, we could use our newfound knowledge of <code>ActiveSupport::Concern</code>!</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s share some of this code, shall we? We can create a <code>skip_authorized.rb</code> file inside of <code>app/controllers/concerns</code>. And inside of it, we&rsquo;ll include <code>Pundit</code> &mdash; otherwise, our <code>skip_after_actions</code> will have no idea what actions we&rsquo;re trying to skip! Our concern might look something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">module SkipAuthorized
  extend ActiveSupport::Concern

  included do
    skip_after_action :verify_authorized
    skip_after_action :verify_policy_scoped
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Pretty simple, right? And suddenly, our <code>CommentsController</code>, <code>BlogsController</code>, <code>TagsController</code>, and pretty much <em>every single</em> controller that we want to share these <code>skip_after_action</code> callbacks now can be refactored to have this single line:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class CommentsController &lt; ApplicationController
    include SkipAuthorized

    # RESTful controller actions go here!
end
</code></pre>

<p>And now, if we wanted to <code>rescue</code> from a <code>Pundit::UnauthorizedError</code>, we could add a single line, into a single file&hellip;but all of our controllers would mix that in! Similarly, we could create an <code>Authorized</code> concern for every controller that needed to actually implement <code>pundit</code> authorization. See, there&rsquo;s no need to worry for the rest of our days, because instead, we can just be concerned &mdash; ActiveSupport concerned!</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/jfw9xNEouCJO" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>ActiveSupport&rsquo;s <code>Concern</code> module allows us to mix in callbacks, class and instance methods, and create associations on target objects. This module has an <code>included</code> method, which takes a block, as well as an <code>append_features</code> method and <code>class_methods</code> block, which you can read about in <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveSupport/Concern.html#method-i-included">the source code</a>.</li>
<li>This <a href="http://engineering.appfolio.com/2013/06/17/ruby-mixins-activesupportconcern/">blog post</a> is pretty fantastic in its explanation of mixins, modules, and concerns.</li>
<li>Concerns are a little controversial in Railsland. This <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/justingordon/rails-conf-2014concernsdecoratorspresentersserviceobjectshelpershelpmedecideapril222014">slide deck</a> from RailsConf 2014 shares a bit about why that&rsquo;s the case.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Pundit, the Cool Kid of Authorization]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/09/29/using-pundit-the-cool-kid-of-authorization/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-29T08:57:21-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/09/29/using-pundit-the-cool-kid-of-authorization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/OdVug9ZRk8sqA" width="480" height="192" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Ah, authorization &ndash; or as I like to call it, authentication&rsquo;s cooler, slightly less complicated twin. It&rsquo;s easy to confuse the two, but there&rsquo;s a fundamental difference between them. I recently learned that while setting up an authorization system for an application that&rsquo;s nearing the end of development. Authentication focuses on who you are as a user &mdash; an admin, guest, or user with an account, for example &mdash; while authorization is about what actions you can take. Authorization centers around what you are actually <em>able to do</em> within the context of your role.</p>

<p>It often makes sense to leave authorization as one of the later (and sometimes, last) step of development, purely because it means that you don&rsquo;t need to worry about making sure that you are authenticated in your development environment while you are still building out your application. But eventually, somewhere between development and deployment, you&rsquo;ll have to think about the abilities of your users &mdash; or, what they can and can&rsquo;t do.</p>

<p>There are a few different ways to go about creating an authorization system, one of the most popular being <code>can_can</code>, a gem that has been around in the Rails community since 2010, as well as a newer gem called <code>rolify</code>. But the one that I&rsquo;ve found really easy and fun to work with is <code>pundit</code>, an <a href="https://github.com/elabs/pundit">authorization system</a> crafted by eLabs, and interestingly enough, based off of the logic and thought behind the CanCan&rsquo;s approach. The developers at eLabs actually started off using the CanCan library in their own applications, but quickly realized that it could become very complicated, very quickly. So, they built the simpler authorization system of <code>pundit</code>, which is exactly what we&rsquo;ll play around with today!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Policies of Pundit</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/zCn93ehzAzZNC" width="480" height="198" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Implementing the <code>pundit</code> gem is easy once we understand how it&rsquo;s structured, what it&rsquo;s expecting, and what conventions to follow. But before we do anything else, we&rsquo;ll need to add it to our <code>Gemfile</code>:</p>

<p><code>gem "pundit"</code></p>

<p>and run our favorite command, <code>bundle install</code>.</p>

<p>The documentation for this gem is fairly well-explained, and even allows you to generate all the basic files you need with a single command (<code>rails g pundit:install</code>). However, generators can be a little bit dangerous if you don&rsquo;t understand what&rsquo;s going on behind the scenes, since all logic has been abstracted away and things start happening automagically! So, let&rsquo;s set up our authorization system for our bookstore manually. Don&rsquo;t worry &mdash; it&rsquo;s not going to be <em>too</em> painful!</p>

<p>First things first: we need to make sure that we include <code>pundit</code> in our controllers. This is a particularly important step because we&rsquo;re going to use a method inside of all of our controllers, and if we don&rsquo;t <code>include Pundit</code>, none of our controllers will have any idea what method we&rsquo;re trying to call. Since we&rsquo;re going to be authorizing multiple classes, it makes sense to add <code>pundit</code> to the file where all our other controllers will inherit from: <code>ApplicationController</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ApplicationController &lt; ActionController::Base
  include Pundit
  protect_from_forgery
end
</code></pre>

<p>Next, we need to understand how <code>pundit</code> actually works. If we take a look at <a href="https://github.com/elabs/pundit">the documentation</a>, there are a few things that immediately become clear: <code>pundit</code> is focused around something called &ldquo;policy classes&rdquo;. Similar to how <code>cancan</code> relies &ldquo;ability classes&rdquo;, <code>pundit</code> expects a policy class to house our authorization logic.</p>

<p>Okay, so we need policy classes. But what kind of classes are they? Do they inherit from anything? How many do we need, exactly? And what should go inside of them? If these are the questions running through your head, fret not: there are answers to all of them!</p>

<p>Here are the basics of building a <code>pundit</code> policy class:</p>

<ol>
<li>Every policy class is just a plain old ruby class. It doesn&rsquo;t need to inherit from <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>, or anything else. The only thing that the class <em>must</em> have is the suffix <code>Policy</code>.</li>
<li>Each policy class should contain the authorization logic for the model class that it corresponds to. A <code>User</code> model would have a <code>UserPolicy</code>, while a <code>Book</code> model would have a <code>BookPolicy</code> class.</li>
<li>A policy class should initialize with two instance variables: a <code>user</code>, and the <code>model</code> that we want to authorize. The <code>initialize</code> method in a policy class will always expect these two parameters in a certain order: <code>user</code> as the first argument, and the <code>model</code> object that we want to authorize as the second arugment. The <code>model</code> doesn&rsquo;t have to be an <code>ActiveRecord</code> object &ndash; it can literally be anything that you want to authorize!</li>
<li>Inside of the policy class are query methods that actually contain the code for specific authorization checks. These should correspond and map to the actions in the controller for the model we want to authorize. If our <code>UsersController</code> has <code>create</code>, <code>update</code>, and <code>destroy</code> actions, our <code>UserPolicy</code> class should (theoretically) have <code>create?</code>, <code>update?</code>, and <code>destroy?</code> query methods inside of it.</li>
</ol>


<p>Okay, that&rsquo;s enough on policies to start. Let&rsquo;s actually start writing some of those policy classes! We&rsquo;ll need to create a folder for all of our policies since we&rsquo;re not using the generator (<code>app/policies</code>), which will house our policy classes. The most important policy class that we should write first is our <code>ApplicationPolicy</code>, which will reside at <code>app/policies/application_policy.rb</code>. This is where we can put our <code>initialize</code> method in, since we know that every policy needs to have this method inside of it.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ApplicationPolicy 
  attr_reader :user, :resource

  def initialize(user, resource)
    @user = user
    @resource = resource
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Since the <code>initialize</code> method of our <code>ApplicationPolicy</code> is going to be used by all of our other policy classes, we can refer to the second argument (the model that we want to authorize) as <code>resource</code>. Depending on what policy class we are in, the <code>resource</code> object will change. If we had used the generator, we&rsquo;d notice that the model object is actually referred to as <code>record</code>, which also would have been an acceptable name for our second argument. Either way, this is a nice and easy way of abstracting out this method into one file, and then reusing it in our other policy classes. Speaking of which&hellip;it&rsquo;s time for us to write those, next!</p>

<h2>Authorize Me</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/4SmyjSEh4wsPm" width="480" height="202" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>We&rsquo;ll start by authorizing (one of) the most important objects in our application: our users! Since we have a <code>User</code> model, we&rsquo;ll need to abide by <code>pundit</code>&rsquo;s policies, and create a <code>user_policy.rb</code> file inside of <code>app/policies</code>. We&rsquo;ll make sure that it inherit from <code>ApplicationPolicy</code>, so that we&rsquo;ll have access to the <code>initialize</code> method:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class UserPolicy &lt; ApplicationPolicy
end
</code></pre>

<p>Next, let&rsquo;s take a look at our <code>UsersController</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class UsersController &lt; ApplicationController

    # Some more RESTful actions would go here,
    # probably like #create and #destroy 

    def update
      user = User.find(params[:id])

      user.assign_attributes(user_params)

      if user.save
        render json: user
      else
        render json: {}, status: :unprocessable_entity
      end
    end

    private

    def user_params
      params.require(:user).permit(:name, :email)
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>There&rsquo;s nothing too fancy going on in here at the moment, and for now, we&rsquo;re only concerned with authorizing the <code>update</code> action in our <code>UsersController</code>. Ultimately, we don&rsquo;t want any user to be able to update their information unless they are logged in; in other words, a user shouldn&rsquo;t be able to update anyone else&rsquo;s name and email except for their own.</p>

<p>So, if we want to authorize the <code>update</code> action, we&rsquo;ll need a query method in our <code>UserPolicy</code> class called &mdash; you guessed it &mdash; <code>update?</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class UserPolicy &lt; ApplicationPolicy

    # Inherited from ApplicationPolicy:
    # def initialize(user, resource)
        # @user = user
        # @resource = resource
    # end

    def update?
        user == resource
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>All we&rsquo;re doing here is verifying that the <code>user</code> instance that we&rsquo;re passing in to the <code>initialize</code> method (which we&rsquo;re inheriting, remember?) is the same instance as the <code>resource</code> that we&rsquo;re passing in. The <code>resource</code> is the model that corresponds to the policy; in our case, we&rsquo;re in the context of the <code>UserPolicy</code>, so our <code>resource</code> is the <code>user</code> instance.</p>

<p>The last step is actually telling our <code>update</code> action in our <code>UsersController</code> to <em>use</em> the <code>UserPolicy</code> and authorize our <code>user</code> instance. To do this, we&rsquo;ll need to call the <code>authorize</code> method, and pass in our <code>resource</code> that we want to authorize:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class UsersController &lt; ApplicationController
    after_action :verify_authorized

    def update
      user = User.find(params[:id])

      authorize user
      user.assign_attributes(user_params)

      if user.save
        render json: user
      else
        render json: {}, status: :unprocessable_entity
      end
    end

    private

    def user_params
      params.require(:user).permit(:name, :email)
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>In addition to calling <code>authorize</code>, we also need to make sure that our policy is actually being used! In fact, that&rsquo;s what the <code>after_action :verify_authorized</code> line is doing. The documentation suggests adding this to our <code>ApplicationController</code>, but for the sake of clarify, we can put it here temporarily, just to see how everything is working together. Pundit adds a method called <code>verify_authorized</code> to our controllers. It&rsquo;s this method that is reponsible for raising an exception if <code>authorize</code> is not called. It&rsquo;s recommended to put this in an <code>after_action</code> so that we don&rsquo;t forget to authorize any controller actions when we invoke them. Eventually, we&rsquo;ll want to abstract this line to our <code>ApplicationController</code>:</p>

<p><code>after_action :verify_authorized, except: :index</code></p>

<p>Since this is an <code>after_action</code>, we can pass it <code>except</code> or <code>only</code>, if we want to skip authorization for certain controller actions.</p>

<p>So, how is all of this working? Well, when we pass <code>user</code> to the <code>authorize</code> method, we are actually telling <code>pundit</code> to look for a <code>UserPolicy</code>, find the corresponding action, and invoke it. If our <code>user</code> instance is <em>not</em> authorized, <code>pundit</code> will raise a <code>Pundit::NotAuthorizedError</code>. The source code for the <a href="https://github.com/elabs/pundit/blob/145d7592c0028c26e61e8a9569ed3440323eaa40/lib/pundit/policy_finder.rb">policy finder</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/elabs/pundit/blob/8d73705ca6886b757c9d41e13c1cb32a7b97334b/lib/pundit.rb">authorize method</a> reveal exactly how this happens, and are pretty cool to look at under the hood.</p>

<h2>Scopin&#8217; Out More Policies</h2>

<p>The <code>pundit</code> gem is pretty powerful, but the thing that makes it the cool kid of authorization is how it handles scopes. We can use scopes when we want to have a specific subset of records that a user has access to &mdash; basically, when we want to narrow the &ldquo;scope&rdquo; of the resources that are visible to our user, based on their &ldquo;level&rdquo; of authorization (admin, guest, etc.).</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s write a quick scope for the <code>Review</code> objects of the book reviews in our bookstore. Right now, our <code>ReviewPolicy</code> looks like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ReviewPolicy &lt; ApplicationPolicy
    def update?
        resource.user == user
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>We have a corresponding <code>update</code> action in our <code>ReviewsController</code>, and we&rsquo;re allowing a review to be updated only by the user who wrote it (in other words, the <code>user</code> object that the <code>review</code> belongs to). But we also need an <code>index</code> action, and we want to limit the <code>reviews</code> that can be viewed by a user in the index action. Ultimately, the only <code>user</code> that should be able to see <em>all</em> reviews (including drafts) should be admins; otherwise, the only reviews that should be visible are the ones that have been published.</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s where scopes come into play. There&rsquo;s a few rules to scopes:</p>

<ol>
<li>They are plain old ruby classes, nested within the policy class.</li>
<li>They have an initialize method that takes a <code>user</code> instance, and a <code>scope</code>. The <code>scope</code> is what we&rsquo;ll perform some kind of database query on &mdash; usually an ActiveRecord class or <code>ActiveRecord::Relation</code>.</li>
<li>The class should have a <code>resolve</code> method, which should return an array of instances that we can iterate over &mdash; again, probably an <code>ActiveRecord::Relation</code>.</li>
</ol>


<p>Let&rsquo;s go ahead and add a scope to our preexisting <code>ReviewPolicy</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ReviewPolicy &lt; ApplicationPolicy
  class Scope
    attr_reader :user, :scope

    def initialize(user, scope)
      @user = user
      @scope = scope
    end

    def resolve
        if user.admin?
            scope.all
        else
            scope.where(published: true)
        end
    end
  end

  def update?
    resource.user == user
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>The only thing that&rsquo;s actually happening here is that we&rsquo;re limiting the number and types of book <code>reviews</code> that will be rendered by the <code>resolve</code> method. If our <code>user</code> is an admin, we&rsquo;ll run the query <code>Review.all</code>; otherwise, we&rsquo;ll execute the query, <code>Review.where(published: true)</code>.</p>

<p>Again, we could abstract the initialize method of our <code>Scope</code> class into the <code>ApplicationPolicy</code> so that we could inherit <code>class Scope &lt; Scope</code>, rather that actually writing the method directly into this class. In fact, that&rsquo;s probably exactly what we would do once we realized that we needed to write more than a single scope.</p>

<p>The last step is adding our scope to our <code>ReviewsController</code>. We can use a method provided by <code>pundit</code> in our controller called <code>policy_scope</code>, which takes an class instance of a model (in our case, <code>Review</code>):</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ReviewsController &lt; BaseController
    after_action :verify_policy_scoped, only: :index
    skip_after_action :verify_authorized, only: :index

    def index
      if user_signed_in?
        reviews = policy_scope(Review)

        render json: reviews
      else
        render json: { reviews: [] }
      end
    end

    def update
        review = Review.find(params[:id])

        authorize review

        # Logic for updating our review
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now, our <code>index</code> action uses the <code>policy_scope</code> method to find the reviews that we&rsquo;ll render. The <code>policy_scope</code> method infers that we want to use the <code>ReviewPolicy::Scope</code> class, and it will instantiate the class and then call resolve on the instance. In fact, the code that&rsquo;s actually getting executed here is this:</p>

<p><code>reviews = ReviewPolicy::Scope.new(current_user, Review).resolve</code></p>

<p>The other important line in our controller is the method that&rsquo;s actually mkaing sure that the policy scope is being used:</p>

<p><code>after_action :verify_policy_scoped, only: :index</code></p>

<p>Similar to <code>verify_authorized</code>, the <code>verify_policy_scoped</code> method is what ensures that the policy scope is actually being used. And in our case, we only have a scope on our <code>index</code> action, so we can specify that we only want to use a scope on <code>:index</code>. Not too bad, right? Just tell <code>pundit</code> what you want to scope, and what you want to authorize, and it will do the rest for us!</p>

<p>But what if we had a class that never needed to be authorized or scoped? How could we tell <code>pundit</code> to just skip the authorization for that specific model? Well, it&rsquo;s pretty easy &mdash; we can just use <code>skip_after_action</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class CommentsController &lt; ApplicationController
    skip_after_action :verify_authorized
    skip_after_action :verify_policy_scoped

    # RESTful controller actions go here!
end
</code></pre>

<p>Simple! This gem is pretty fantastic to work with, and gives us great guidelines on the proper way of using it. I really liked this particular piece of advice from the library&rsquo;s developers:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Pundit strongly encourages you to model your application in such a way that the only context you need for authorization is a user object and a domain model that you want to check authorization for. If you find yourself needing more context than that, consider whether you are authorizing the right domain model, maybe another domain model (or a wrapper around multiple domain models) can provide the context you need.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>It turns out that authorizing with <code>pundit</code> can be a really good time. You might say that it&rsquo;s even kind of&hellip;fun!</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/btKQIhrebJ3Og" width="480" height="200" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>The <code>pundit</code> gem is a simple way to build a powerful authorization system. It expects plain old ruby policy classes for each model that you want to authorize, and each class should contain query methods that map to controller actions for the model. The controller that corresponds to the model should call the <code>authorize</code> method for the object, and should either contain or inherit an <code>after_action :verify_authorized</code> method.</li>
<li>The developers at eLabs put a lot of work into building <code>pundit</code>, and based it off of the <code>cancan</code> library. In fact, they even wrote a super blog post about their process, which you can read <a href="http://www.elabs.se/blog/52-simple-authorization-in-ruby-on-rails-apps">over here</a>.</li>
<li>Still confused about when to authorize and when to authenticate? Check out this <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/BruceWhite3/pundit-37048056">awesome slidedeck</a> that clarifies all your authorization confusion!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
