<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails | Words and Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-01T08:52:29-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vaidehi Joshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inflections Everywhere: Using ActiveSupport Inflector]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/inflections-everywhere-using-activesupport-inflector/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-01T08:45:22-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/inflections-everywhere-using-activesupport-inflector</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/JEIRAmTTfUgYE" width="480" height="264" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Words are pretty important. But do you know what&rsquo;s more important than words? <em>Grammar</em>. (Can you tell that I was an English major?) Despite how big of a book nerd I am, there&rsquo;s acually a crucial reason as to why we should keep things like grammar in consideration: convention.</p>

<p>At it&rsquo;s very core &mdash; pun totally intended &mdash; the Rails framework is based in conventions. We rely on the framework to create our models, controllers, and views in a specific file structure, and for them to be named in a certain way. But what we often forget is that we also rely on Rails to be smart enough to handle strange edge cases, like knowing that a <code>mice</code> table should store the <code>Mouse</code> model objects, and that the <code>MiceController</code> should be responsible for passing those objects back and forth!</p>

<p>It all seems pretty automagical. But we have to keep in mind that it was the Rails core team that created and established these conventions, which means that they&rsquo;re not magic &mdash; they&rsquo;re just code! And as much as we can rely on preexisting Rails conventions, there might be times that we need to tweak our code to abide by those conventions. And because computers are not people (and because English is a crazy language with so many strange exceptions), we&rsquo;re probably going to run into a roadblock when dealing with grammar naming conventions. Thankfully, there&rsquo;s a great tool to help with this problem: the Rails <strong>Inflector</strong>, also known as every grammar nerd&rsquo;s dream.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Meet The Inflector</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/yLV9y5wb0Qb1m" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>The Rails Inflector is actually a part of the ActiveSupport module, which is truly a beast of a module, and probably warrants a few blog posts of its own. The tl;dr version of ActiveSupport is this: it provides a bunch of different patterns to transform simple Ruby strings. The inflector library in particular is responsible for handling the pluralization of different strings.</p>

<p>An important thing to note about the inflections library is that it&rsquo;s pretty much set in stone. According to <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveSupport/Inflector.html">the documentation</a>, these rules are never going to change so that Rails can remain backwards-compatible for older applications:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;The Rails core team has stated patches for the inflections library will not be accepted in order to avoid breaking legacy applications which may be relying on errant inflections. If you discover an incorrect inflection and require it for your application or wish to define rules for languages other than English, please correct or add them yourself.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>Basically, what this means is that Rails provides us with some basic inflections; however, if we want to create our own custom grammar rules (or if we notice something that&rsquo;s incorrect), we have to write our own inflections for our application. It&rsquo;s also worth noting that if we want to create models that are <em>not</em> English words, we&rsquo;d need to write our own pluralize rules for those as well. But before we go about writing completely new inflections, let&rsquo;s first see what inflector methods we have available to us!</p>

<h2>Inflector Methods</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/l41lS9B8KYJ9dYZck" width="480" height="283" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>The <code>ActiveSupport::Inflector</code> module has a handful of public instance methods that are available for us to use. In fact, when I was first learning Rails, I played around with these methods in irb, but didn&rsquo;t really know (much less <em>understand</em>) where they were coming from. But it turns out that the Inflector methods can be super useful! Here are some of my favorites:</p>

<h3><code>humanize</code></h3>

<p>This method is great for displaying an attribute name to end users. It deletes any leading underscores, replaces underscores with spaces, downcase all words (except acronyms), and capitalizes the first word. Basically, it makes your attributes human-readable, which can be helpful for displaying an error message to your user:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">♥ rails console
Loading development environment (Rails 4.1.4)
irb(main):001:0&gt; humanize(author.first_name) 
=&gt; "First name"
</code></pre>

<h3><code>titleize</code></h3>

<p>The <code>titleize</code> method is pretty perfect for our bookstore application. It capitalizes all the words and replaces underscores with spaces:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):002:0&gt; 'of_mice_and_men'.titleize
=&gt; "Of Mice And Men"
</code></pre>

<p><em>Protip: this method is also aliased as <code>titlecase</code>.</em></p>

<h3><code>parameterize</code></h3>

<p>This method replaces special characters in a string so that it can be used in a URL (think sluggable names with hyphens):</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):003:0&gt; 'Of Mice And Men'.parameterize
=&gt; "of-mice-and-men"
</code></pre>

<h3><code>singularize</code></h3>

<p>The <code>singularize</code> method does exactly what you think it would do: it returns the singular form of a word in a string:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):004:0&gt; 'mice'.singularize
=&gt; "mouse"
irb(main):005:0&gt; 'men'.singularize
=&gt; "man"
</code></pre>

<h3><code>pluralize</code></h3>

<p>And the <code>pluralize</code> method does the opposite things: returns the plural form of a word in string format:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):006:0&gt; "mouse".pluralize
=&gt; "mice"
irb(main):007:0&gt; "man".pluralize
=&gt; "men"
</code></pre>

<p>There are tons more Inflector methods that are very <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveSupport/Inflector.html">well-documented</a>. In fact, there are so many great methods that you might be thinking to yourself, <em>why would I ever have to write my own methods?</em></p>

<p>Well, what if we wanted <code>Specimen</code> objects, which needed to be pluralized as <code>Specimens</code>. We could assume that Rails will handle that for us&hellip;or we could double-check:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):008:0&gt; "specimen".pluralize
=&gt; "specimen"
</code></pre>

<p>Oops! It seems like the predefined inflections are taking hold here and parsing &ldquo;men&rdquo; as the plural form of &ldquo;man&rdquo;, like we saw earlier. You know what this means&hellip;time to write our <em>own</em> inflections!</p>

<h2>New Inflection Rules</h2>

<p>One of the coolest public instance methods of the <code>`ActiveSupport::Inflector</code> module is the method that allows us to specify our own inflector rules. This method is appropiately named <code>inflections</code>, and it does some interesting things.</p>

<p>The <code>inflections</code> method yields to a singleton instance of <code>ActiveSupport::Inflector::Inflections</code>. It can be passed an optional locale, which is how we could write inflection rules for other languages; the default locale is English (specified as the argument <code>:en</code>).</p>

<p>We can write our own inflections inside of the <code>config/initializers/inflections.rb</code> file. This file actually already exists and will look like this when we first open it:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby"># Be sure to restart your server when you modify this file.

# Add new inflection rules using the following format. Inflections
# are locale specific, and you may define rules for as many different
# locales as you wish. All of these examples are active by default:
# ActiveSupport::Inflector.inflections(:en) do |inflect|
#   inflect.plural /^(ox)$/i, '\1en'
#   inflect.singular /^(ox)en/i, '\1'
#   inflect.irregular 'person', 'people'
#   inflect.uncountable %w( fish sheep )
# end

# These inflection rules are supported but not enabled by default:
# ActiveSupport::Inflector.inflections(:en) do |inflect|
#   inflect.acronym 'RESTful'
# end
</code></pre>

<p>We can already see how to go about writing our inflections with the examples in this file, including some of the methods we can use, depending on what our edge case is. There are actually a lot of <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveSupport/Inflector/Inflections.html">methods available</a> to us inside of our inflections block, some of the most helpful being <code>plural</code>, <code>singular</code>, <code>uncountable</code>, and <code>irregular</code>. In our case, we&rsquo;re dealing with an irregular inflection wherein <code>specimen</code> needs to be pluralized as <code>specimens</code>, so we&rsquo;ll use the <code>irregular</code> method, which takes two arguments: the singular and the plural form of the word as strings.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">ActiveSupport::Inflector.inflections(:en) do |inflect|
  inflect.irregular 'specimen', 'specimens'
en
</code></pre>

<p>Awesome! Now our entire application will know about this inflection rule. And the really great thing about this is that our new rule that we just wrote is added at the top of this file, which means that our irregular rule for <code>specimen</code> will be the first of the singularization and pluralization rules that is run. This ensures that our rules will always run before any of the preexisting rules that come with <code>ActiveSupport::Inflector</code>.</p>

<p>Whew &mdash; that was quite an inflection adventure! But now the next time we have a grammar mistake, we can fix it easily, just like this slightly strange puppet (is a gopher? A beaver? I don&rsquo;t know!) keeps telling us to do:</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/DIBVWfW8vtQli" width="480" height="269" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>The <code>ActiveSupport::Inflector</code> handles a lot of the grammar rules in Rails. The <code>inflections.rb</code> file is where we can write our own inflection rules. Check out all the preexisting inflections in the Rails <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/92f567ab30f240a1de152061a6eee76ca6c4da86/activesupport/lib/active_support/inflections.rb">source code</a>.</li>
<li>Curious how Rails knows what grammar rules to follow? Check out <a href="http://ilanasufrin.github.io/blog/2014/07/30/a-rails-grammar-lesson/">this blog post</a>, which explains it all.</li>
<li>If you are very brave, dig through the <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/6c75a111995a9aab09e19c2b6a8a42162f689bc6/activesupport/lib/active_support/inflector/inflections.rb">source code</a> for all of the methods available to <code>inflections</code>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Safer SQL: Using ActiveRecord Transactions]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/08/18/safer-sql-using-activerecord-transactions/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-18T08:11:32-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/08/18/safer-sql-using-activerecord-transactions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/Djnfk5gnoNXqM" width="480" height="356" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Is there anything more satisfying than writing concise, perfect line of SQL and then watching it query your database exactly as you expected? Probably not. Writing &mdash; and subsequently watching! &mdash; an efficient database query is one of my favorite parts of building an application.</p>

<p>But if there&rsquo;s one thing about software development that I&rsquo;ve learned over the past few months, it&rsquo;s this: projects can get out of control, rather quickly. You start off with your basic models, but then as you add one feature after another, things can start to get out of hand. At that point, your focus as a developer shifts and spreads out to various things. You can&rsquo;t just care about how readable your code is; you also have to consider how efficient it is, and how different units of your application might be breaking other parts (hopefully not unbeknownst to you!). In other words, you have to consider how defensive and <em>safe</em> your code actually is.</p>

<p>Recently, while writing some background jobs and creating some service objects for a new feature, I realized the importance of executing and enforcing safe code. The good news is that there&rsquo;s a really helpful, life-saving ActiveRecord <strong>transaction</strong> method that allows you to do exactly this. And the really great news? You get to watch your SQL queries execute safely as a result!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Database Handshakes</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/gVYk3rI8YjtAI" width="480" height="422" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>As our application grows, there are inevitably going to be different models that depend upon each other. To make things more complicated, those models are going to have to change as our Users take different actions, and that means that we&rsquo;ll need to update different associated parts of our schema as a result. For example, let&rsquo;s say that we have a background job that&rsquo;s responsible for processing an <code>Order</code> on an <code>User</code>. This background job has a service class that takes care of saving an <code>Order</code> when it has been charged, billing the <code>User</code>, and adding a sale to an <code>Vendor</code> object, which will then be visible on the vendor&rsquo;s dashboard panel/admin page.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">if order.process
    user.charge
    vendor.add_sale
end
</code></pre>

<p>In other words, we&rsquo;re basically transferring money from our <code>User</code> object to our <code>Vendor</code> objects. At first glance, this might not seem like a potentially &ldquo;unsafe&rdquo; set of queries, but here&rsquo;s where things can get a bit tricky: imagine that our <code>User</code>&rsquo;s credit card information is rejected, or for some reason, the charge cannot be created. In that scenario, we&rsquo;d want to handle the errors and make sure that the <code>add_sale</code> method is <em>not</em> called on our <code>Vendor</code> object. However&hellip;we aren&rsquo;t really safeguarding our code against this situation at all, are we?</p>

<p>But, fear not - it&rsquo;s not a totally hopeless situation! In fact, we can take care of this problem pretty easily by using ActiveRecord&rsquo;s <code>transaction</code> blocks.</p>

<p>The <code>transaction</code> method is defined in the Rails source code under the <code>ActiveRecord::Transactions</code> module. This method takes a block, and whenever it is invoked, the block that is passed to it will be executed inside of a <em>database transaction</em>. If, in the course of executing that block, an <code>exception</code> is raised, the database transaction will automatically be rolled back. No SQL will be executed, and no new data will be added to the database</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">Order.transaction do
    @order.process
    @user.charge
    @vendor.add_sale
end
</code></pre>

<p>So what does this mean, exactly? Well, now that we&rsquo;ve wrapped the logic of our three methods inside of a <code>transaction</code> method, we can safely assert that in the case that <em>any</em> of these three methods raises an <code>exception</code> (in other words, fails for any reason), the entire process should fail.</p>

<p>The important piece of this is that we&rsquo;ll never be adding or updating any data (or writing to our database) unless all of these methods are successful. It&rsquo;s crucial for us to ensure that this is the case because we&rsquo;d never want to call the <code>add_sale</code> method and write data to our <code>vendor</code> if the <code>order</code> didn&rsquo;t successfully <code>process</code>, or if our <code>user</code> wasn&rsquo;t successfully <code>charged</code>.</p>

<p>I like to think of these blocks as a &ldquo;handshake&rdquo; between your application and your database: your application and database have an understanding that one will hand off information to the other in a &ldquo;transaction&rdquo;, and when the deal actually goes through, they shake hands and make it official&hellip;or something more poetic. If that made no sense &mdash; or if you&rsquo;re not a big fan of metaphors &mdash; here&rsquo;s how the Rails documentation explains <code>transactions</code>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Transactions are protective blocks where SQL statements are only permanent if they can all succeed as one atomic action. Transactions enforce the integrity of the database and guard the data against program errors or database break-downs. So basically you should use transaction blocks whenever you have a number of statements that must be executed together or not at all.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<h2>The Rules of Transacting</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/cGDgkEeqA78Q" width="480" height="397" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Because ActiveRecord transactions can be easily explained and simplified as a single method, it&rsquo;s easy to forget the idiosyncrasies that make this method work. There are a few things to keep in mind so that we can get the most out of these blocks.</p>

<h3>1. Opening database connections</h3>

<p>A transaction opens up a single database connection. This means that when we call the <code>transaction</code> method, the method can only be invoked on the <em>current</em> database connection. This is important to remember if our application writes to multiple database at once; for example, if our <code>Order</code> and our <code>Vendor</code> data lived in two different databases, we&rsquo;d need to nest our transactions:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">Order.transaction do
    Vendor.transaction do 
        order.process
        user.charge
        vendor.add_sale
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>It&rsquo;s generally a good idea to avoid nested transactions, mostly because the relationship between parent and child transactions can get complicated. This is especially the case because rollbacks are contained <em>inside</em> of their transactions blocks. I think that Mark Daggett explains this pretty well in <a href="http://markdaggett.com/blog/2011/12/01/transactions-in-rails/">his blog</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;ActiveRecord::Rollback does not propagate outside of the containing transaction block and so the parent transaction does not receive the exception nested inside the child. I find it easier to think of nested transactions like the child who dumps its contents into the parent container, leaving the child transaction empty. To ensure a rollback is received by the parent transaction you must add the <code>requires_new: true</code>. option to the child transaction.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<h3>2. Different classes, one transaction</h3>

<p>Because transactions are bound to <em>database connections</em>, we can mix different types of models inside of a <code>transaction</code> block. In fact, that&rsquo;s exactly what we were doing when we wrote our initial transaction:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">Order.transaction do
    @order.process
    @user.charge
    @vendor.add_sale
end
</code></pre>

<h3>3. Class and instance methods</h3>

<p>The great part about <code>transaction</code> is that it is available to us as both a class <em>and</em> an instance method for our ActiveRecord models. What does this mean, exactly? Well, the short answer is that we can write a transaction is lots of different ways, since we can invoke the <code>transaction</code> method on a class or an instance.</p>

<p>For example, we could have written this:
<code>ruby
User.transaction do
    # methods we want to call go here
end
</code></p>

<p>Or this:
<code>ruby
Vendor.transaction do
    # methods we want to call go here
end
</code></p>

<p>Or any of these:
<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="vi">@order</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">transaction</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;p&gt;@user.transaction do</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">end&lt;/</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="vi">@vendor</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">transaction</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p>And if we were writing a method <em>inside</em> of the <code>Order</code>, <code>Vendor</code>, or <code>User</code> classes, these options would have worked as well:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">self.transaction do
end

self.class.transaction do
end
</code></pre>

<p>The key here is that the <code>transaction</code> can be called on <em>any class</em> that inherits from <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>. Why is that the key? Well, you might remember that we initially started off wanting to write a transaction inside of our service object&hellip;right? In that case, we can&rsquo;t use something like <code>transaction do</code>, because <code>self</code> is the service object class, which <em>does <strong>not</strong> inherit</em> from <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>!</p>

<p>So, what do? Well, just call the transaction method onto <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code> directly! there&rsquo;s a quick fix for that.
<code>ruby
ActiveRecord::Base.transaction do
    # methods we want to call go here
end
</code></p>

<p>When in doubt, we can always just call the <code>transaction</code> method onto the <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code> class directly to be sure that it will run.</p>

<h3>4. Exceptions are the rule</h3>

<p>There&rsquo;s one golden rule of the <code>transaction</code> block: it will <strong>only rollback the transaction if an error is raised</strong>.</p>

<p>Why is this important? Well, calling something like <code>save</code> or <code>destroy</code> inside of a transaction will not raise an error; if something goes wrong, these methods will simply return <code>false</code>. Which means that our <code>transaction</code> block will continue, since there was no error raised!</p>

<p>Uh oh&hellip;how to fix? Just use the <code>save!</code> and <code>destroy!</code> methods instead! These are both ActiveRecord methods which raise an exception if they don&rsquo;t execute successfully:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">ActiveRecord::Base.transaction do
    @order.destroy!
    @user.save!
end
</code></pre>

<p>And that&rsquo;s exactly what we need in this case, because we want the entire transaction to be closed if one or both of these methods are unsuccessful, and we want to tell the database that no data has changed. If we really, <em>really</em> wanted to use <code>save</code> instead of <code>save!</code>, we&rsquo;d have to manually <code>raise</code> an error in the block for our transaction to work as expected.</p>

<h2>Transactions Under The Hood</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/iUOzkJmvnFfqM" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>One of the interesting things about how <code>transaction</code> works under the hood has to do with how the <code>save</code> and <code>destroy</code> methods work. It turns out that Rails actually wraps the <code>save</code> and <code>destroy</code> methods in their own <code>transaction</code>s! So, we were using <code>ActiveRecord::Base.transaction</code> all along, without probably ever knowing what was really happening! Pretty crazy, right?</p>

<p>There are a couple reasons that <code>save</code> and <code>destroy</code> are particularly curious. First, because they each occur in their own transactions, this means that we&rsquo;ll never need to write a <code>transaction</code> block to update a single record. In fact, that&rsquo;s exactly what Rails is  doing for us when we call something like <code>@user.save</code> &mdash; it&rsquo;s running a <code>transaction</code> block behind the scenes.</p>

<p>The second reason this is interesting is because of callbacks that are associated with these two methods. A callback hook like <code>after_save</code> is actually part of the same active transaction that was opened when we called <code>@user.save</code>. So, if we wanted our code to execute <em>outside</em> of Rails&#8217; default <code>transaction</code> that wraps around <code>save</code> or <code>destroy</code>, we&rsquo;d want to use callback hooks like <code>after_commit</code> or <code>after_destroy</code>. If we want something specific to happen when the <code>save</code> <code>transaction</code> succeeds, we&rsquo;d have to use the <code>after_commit</code> callback, and if we want something specific to happen when the <code>save</code> <code>transaction</code> fails, we could use the <code>after_rollback</code> hook.</p>

<p>While reading about transactions and the <code>save</code> and <code>destroy</code> methods, I discovered another really interesting method called <code>with_transaction_returning_status</code>. The <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/master/activerecord/lib/active_record/transactions.rb">transactions source code</a> is a bit of a rabbit hole, but if we spend some time reading through it, there&rsquo;s a lot to learn.</p>

<p>In a nutshell, the <code>with_transaction_returning_status</code> is responsible for actually <em>raising</em> an <code>ActiveRecord::Rollback</code>. Somewhere inside of the black box of Rails magic, when we see an error caused by a <code>save</code> transaction that looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>:001 &gt; user = User.find(1)
:002 &gt; user.save
    (0.2ms)  begin transaction
    User Exists (0.6ms)  SELECT * FROM "users" WHERE ("users"."id" = 1)
   (0.1ms)  rollback transaction
 =&gt; false 
</code></pre>

<p>it&rsquo;s actually a method like <code>with_transaction_returning_status</code> that&rsquo;s responsible for causing that rollback to happen! Here&rsquo;s a truncated example of the source code; we can see that this method defines a local <code>status</code> variable, sets and returns the <code>status</code> if the <code>transaction</code> is successful, and <code>raises</code> an error, if the <code>status</code> is not defined:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">def with_transaction_returning_status
    status = nil
    self.class.transaction do
        # some Rails magic here that captures the
        # return value of a save or destroy method,
        # and then sets that to the status.

        raise ActiveRecord::Rollback unless status
    end
    status
end
</code></pre>

<p>The Rails documentation also briefly explains exactly what&rsquo;s happening:</p>

<blockquote><p>Executes <code>method</code> within a transaction and captures its return value as a status flag. If the status is true the transaction is committed, otherwise a ROLLBACK is issued. In any case the status flag is returned.</p></blockquote>

<p>Transactions are all around us, it seems, from the most everyday methods to the more complicated ones that we write ourselves. They&rsquo;re a great way of keeping our code safe while also defending against things like duplicate SQL queries.</p>

<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>ActiveRecord&rsquo;s <code>transaction</code> method takes a block, and will only execute the block and write to your database if no exceptions are raised.</li>
<li>You can defined the <code>transaction</code> method on any class that <em>inherits from</em> <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>, and that transaction will open up a single new database connection.</li>
<li>Check out the Jeff Casimir helpful <a href="https://gist.github.com/jcasimir/1098368">summary of transactions</a> in his Gist. Or, if you&rsquo;re looking for a challenge, head over to the Rails <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveRecord/Transactions/ClassMethods.html">documentation</a> on ActiveRecord transactions.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rolling Out the Redcarpet for Rendering Markdown]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/08/11/rolling-out-the-redcarpet-for-rendering-markdown/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-11T08:47:54-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/08/11/rolling-out-the-redcarpet-for-rendering-markdown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://cdn.lolbrary.com/2013/12/6/lolbrary.com_45273_1386359887.jpg" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 400px; max-height: 500px;"/></p>

<p>Sometimes, it&rsquo;s the little things that matter the most. As cool and complex as your giant application might be, small details like a toggleable button, or beautiful-formatted and styled dropdown select can have the biggest impact on the look and feel of the rest of your application.</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve built out the skeleton of your application and filled in the backend functionality, the next step is to connect the all the logic with your frontend framework. And once you&rsquo;ve done that, you start to see all the gaping holes that you need to fix next. One of the applications that I have been working on recently got to that state. Once I ensured that the user-facing page corresponded to the admin panel, it was time to fix all the little things that I had been putting off until we got the application working!</p>

<p>One of those minute details was rendering markdown. While building out the application, we were just using Ruby string primitives in our database to render text. But no one wants to see a long five-paragraph article rendered as a single, huge block of text, right? So, we had to make our text easily editable on the admin panel and renderable &mdash; that&rsquo;s word, right? &mdash; on the user-facing side. At first, I had no idea how to go about doing this. But it turns out that (no surprise here!) this problem has been solved before! All we had to do next was figure out how to implement someone else&rsquo;s solution on our own application. Luckily, the answer to our prayers is as simple as rolling out the <code>redcarpet</code> gem.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Markdown: What is it?</h2>

<p><img src="http://kirkstrobeck.github.io/whatismarkdown.com/img/markdown.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 400px; max-height: 300px;"/></p>

<p>The Markdown language didn&rsquo;t exist until 2004, when it was created by John Gruber of <a href="http://daringfireball.net/">Daring Fireball</a> blog fame. Unlike markup languages such as HTML or RTF (Rich Text Format), Markdown was created to not have any tags for formatting &ldquo;instructions&rdquo; when rendered. Instead, it is structured to be <a href="http://whatismarkdown.com/">readable without formatting</a> or any tags. Ultimately, the language converts simple text into structurally valid markup HTML (or XHTML).</p>

<p>We interact with Markdown a lot, even though we might not always realize it. Files that end in <code>.md</code>, for example, are written in Markdown, and a lot of blog generators (including octopress and jekyll) use Markdown as their formatting language. In fact, this language is exactly what allows us to write something like this into a code snippet or CMS parser:</p>

<pre><code># I'm a heading

This is a list:

* thing one
* thing two
* thing three

And here's some *italics* and some **bold**.
</code></pre>

<p>which will then be processed by Markdown to render actually <em>this</em> HTML in our templates:</p>

<p>&#8220;`html</p>

<h1>I&#8217;m a heading</h1>




<p>This is a list:</p>




<ul>
  <li>thing one</li>
  <li>thing two</li>
  <li>thing three</li>
</ul>




<p>And here&#8217;s some <em>italics</em> and some <strong>bold</strong>.</p>


<pre><code>
Not only is that incredibly cool, but it's also a powerful templating tool! There's one slight problem, however: our templates don't look anything like this. We have neither any Markdown, nor any HTML! Instead, we're just rendering long strings (saved in our Postgres database as `text` attributes) that look like this:

`Here's a news article about Harper Lee's new novel, Go Set A Watchman, but it has no formatting at all...`

So, how do we get our text to look like the beautiful markup from above? Why, by using a special Markdown gem, of course!

## HTML All Of The Things

Markdown processig in Ruby is made especially easy thanks to a library called `redcarpet`, created by a Github developer named &lt;a href="https://github.com/vmg"&gt;Vicent Marti&lt;/a&gt; (thanks, Vicent!). The library is available as a gem, and its parser doesn't require any additional installed libraries aside from Ruby itself.

Let's get set up by adding it to our `Gemfile`:

`gem "redcarpet"`

and bundling up this gem:

`$ bundle install`

Great. Now we need figure out how to recarpet our application using this library! The first thing I like to do whenever I'm working with a library or gem that's completely new to me is decipher what exactly I'm working with here. Thankfully, the `redcarpet` documentation is really fantastic, and they answer this question almost immediately:

&gt;"The core of the Redcarpet library is the Redcarpet::Markdown class. Each instance of the class is attached to a Renderer object; the Markdown class performs parsing of a document and uses the attached renderer to generate output."

Okay...what does this mean, exactly? Well, it's actually not *too* complicated. The library has a `Redcarpet::Markdown` class, which --- you guessed it --- is going to be responsible for handling the transforming/parsing of Markdown to markup (we'll be using HTML, in our case). But it's also attached to a Renderer object, it seems.

An example will help us visualize what exactly is going on here:

`markdown = Redcarpet::Markdown.new(renderer, extensions = {})`

Interesting! the new instance of our `Redcarpet::Markdown` class takes two arguments, one of which *is* our Renderer object. It also seems to take a hash of `extensions`, but we'll come back to that in a bit.

We know that we want to pass in a renderer to our `Redcarpet::Markdown` class...but what are our options? It turns out that there are two built-in renderers that the `redcarpet` library uses: `Redcarpet::Render::HTML` and `Redcarpet::Render::XHTML`. 

*Protip: the `redcarpet` renderers are actually implemented in C, which means that they are incredibly performant and so much faster than other Ruby Markdown renderers!*

Since we want our articles to render HTML, we'll stick with the former renderer rather than the latter:

`markdown = Redcarpet::Markdown.new(Redcarpet::Render::HTML)`

It's important to note that what's *actually* happening here is that we are creating a new *instance* of an HTML renderer, and passing that to our `Redcarpet::Markdown` object. This is crucial to remember because our `Redcarpet::Render::HTML` can also take its own set of options! When we initialize our HTML renderer, we have the option of passing some flags to it. And then, we pass our HTML renderer to our `markdown` object, which will actually handle parsing it:
</code></pre>

<p>renderer = Redcarpet::Render::HTML.new(render_options)
markdown = Redcarpet::Markdown.new(renderer, extensions)
&#8220;`</p>

<p>We won&rsquo;t add any options to start, but don&rsquo;t forget that this is what&rsquo;s <em>actually</em> happening! Now it&rsquo;s time for a deep breath; next, we&rsquo;ll need to actually implement this <code>markdown</code> object in our application!</p>

<p><img src="http://g-ecx.images-amazon.com/images/G/01/askville/137733_9521259_mywrite/html_cat.jpg" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 500px; max-height: 400px;"/><br></p>

<p>The first thing we&rsquo;ll want to do is add our <code>markdown</code> object to the class that will need our Markdown parser. For our Bookstore application, we&rsquo;ll have a set of news articles that will show up on our homepage when a user signs in. This means that we&rsquo;ll want our <code>Article</code> objects to be able to implement markdown. Since this is something our <em>entire</em> class should be able to do, we&rsquo;ll add our <code>markdown</code> object as a class method to our <code>Article</code> model:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Article &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  class &lt;&lt; self
    def markdown
      Redcarpet::Markdown.new(Redcarpet::Render::HTML)
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This method isn&rsquo;t doing anything aside from creating a new instance of a <code>Redcarpet::Markdown</code> parser, with a <code>Redcarpet::Render::HTML</code> renderer. Next, we&rsquo;ll want to add write a migration that will create another column in our database that will save our markdown content:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddMarkdownContentToArticles &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_column :articles, :markdown_content, :text
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>The reason that we have two different columns for persisting content is simple: we have two different types of content that we&rsquo;re dealing with. The <code>content</code> column in the database is what the admins will edit in the admin panel, while the <code>markdown_content</code> column is what will be rendered to the user.</p>

<p>This will be especially evident when we integrate this with our Ember frontend, which would require us to serialize all the data that Rails is passing to the Ember models. In our <code>ArticleSerializer</code>, we are are only passing our <code>markdown_content</code> through to the frontend:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class ArticleSerializer &lt; ApplicationSerializer
    attributes :id, :slug, :title, :markdown_content, :published_at
end
</code></pre>

<p>On the other hand, in our <code>Admin::ArticleSerializer</code>, which is hooked up to our admin panel, we are <em>only</em> passing the raw <code>:content</code>, which is our content <em>before</em> is has been parsed through our <code>markdown</code> object:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">module Admin
  class ArticleSerializer &lt; ApplicationSerializer
    attributes :id, :slug, :title, :content, :published_at
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Nice! We have everything set up, finally. Let&rsquo;s make sure that we&rsquo;re actually parsing our <code>content</code> and assigning our <code>markdown_content</code> when our article is saved. We can do this by adding a <code>before_save</code> hook, which will call whatever method we pass it right before our <code>Article</code> model is saved:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Article &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  class &lt;&lt; self
    def markdown
      Redcarpet::Markdown.new(Redcarpet::Render::HTML)
    end
  end

  before_save :assign_markdown_content, if: -&gt; { content_changed? }

  def assign_markdown_content
    assign_attributes({
      markdown_content: self.class.markdown.render(content)
    })
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Cool! We wrote a <code>assign_markdown_content</code> method that assigns the <code>markdown_content</code> attribute on our <code>Article</code>. And what exactly is it using to assign the <code>markdown_content</code>? Oh, that&rsquo;s right: our <code>markdown</code> object! We&rsquo;re calling the <code>markdown</code> class method, and passing the <code>Article</code>&rsquo;s content to its <code>render</code> method, which means that the <code>Redcarpet::Markdown</code> instance will parse the content into HTML!</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re also doing a pre-check in our <code>before_save</code> by passing a proc to this callback which will only call the <code>assign_markdown_content</code> method if our <code>content</code> column in the database has changed (isn&rsquo;t that <code>content_changed?</code> method is a cool ActiveRecord trick?). This means that we&rsquo;re not assigning attributes on our <code>Article</code> unless we really need to. This is super efficient because it means avoiding unnecessary queries to our database!</p>

<h2>Carpeting Options</h2>

<p>The last part of this <code>redcarpet</code> magic is rendering our content in our views and adding any options we might need. If we wanted to do this in a simple Rails view, we could just ask the <code>Article</code> object for its <code>markdown_content</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="slim">article
  = @article.markdown_content.html_safe
</code></pre>

<p>We might need to call <code>html_safe</code> on this particular column since Rails will try to escape the content automatically. We could do a similar thing in an Ember view as well, using triple handlebars to handle the HTML safe issue.</p>

<p>Now that we finally have everything working, we can add some cool options to our renderer! You&rsquo;ll remember that the <code>Redcarpet::Markdown</code> class takes a hash of options.</p>

<p>In my opinion, the most helpful and important option to pass in is <code>autolink</code>. It&rsquo;s super crucial if you don&rsquo;t know what your content might look like, since it parses links even when they&rsquo;re not enclosed in <code>&lt; &gt;</code> characters. It will detect autolinks for http, https, and ftp protocols, and it also handles email addresses and links that start with <code>www</code>.</p>

<p>We can pass in this option directly as second arguments after we pass in our <code>Redcarpet::Render::HTML</code> object:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">def markdown
  Redcarpet::Markdown.new(Redcarpet::Render::HTML, autolink: true)
end
</code></pre>

<p>Other helpful options on the <code>Redcarpet::Render::HTML</code> object include <code>tables</code>, <code>space_after_headers</code>, <code>lax_spacing</code>, and <code>highlight</code>. Of course, just as you can pass in options to the markdown object you can do the same for the renderer:</p>

<p><code>Redcarpet::Render::HTML.new(hard_wrap: true, safe_links_only: true, escape_html: true)</code></p>

<p>The <code>escape_html</code> option is particularly interesting because it takes precedence over <code>:no_styles</code>, <code>:no_links</code>, <code>:no_images</code> and <code>:filter_html</code>, which means that any existing html tags will be escaped instead of being removed. I&rsquo;m also pretty sure that it would escape any cats you try to pass in through params as well&hellip;although I haven&rsquo;t tried that one yet.</p>

<p><img src="http://geekandpoke.typepad.com/.a/6a00d8341d3df553ef0120a8b86eae970b-800wi" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 400px; max-height: 500px;"/><br></p>

<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>The <code>redcarpet</code> gem is an awesome way to handle rendering Markdown in Rails. It creates a new instance of a Markdown object, which takes either a HTML or XHTML renderer object. You can also write your own, custom render! Check out the <a href="https://github.com/vmg/redcarpet">documentation</a> to learn more on how to do that.</li>
<li>Want to see a step-by-step Rails tutorial on <code>redcarpet</code>? Check out <a href="http://railscasts.com/episodes/272-markdown-with-redcarpet">this Railscast</a>.</li>
<li>Here&rsquo;s a super <a href="https://richonrails.com/articles/rendering-markdown-with-redcarpet">detailed blog post</a> on implementing <code>redcarpet</code>, with some great code snippets and examples.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Safely Storing Your Assets: Paperclip With AWS + Heroku]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/08/04/safely-storing-your-assets-paperclip-with-aws-plus-heroku/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-04T08:15:32-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/08/04/safely-storing-your-assets-paperclip-with-aws-plus-heroku</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We all know how this scene plays out: you&rsquo;ve created the first iteration of your application and you&rsquo;re ready to test it out in production. You can&rsquo;t wait to see what it looks like live, and you want people to be able to start playing with it! Everything seems to go smoothly without any glitches while deploying until you go to your app on Heroku and see&hellip;<em>a broken image icon</em>. Tada!</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/EVJBgyC41ItfW" width="480" height="208" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>This happened to me recently, and boy was it disheartening. I was all excited because I had used <code>paperclip</code> to get some pretty cool <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/28/clipping-images-for-rails-using-paperclip/">image uploading functionality</a> on my application, but it didn&rsquo;t seem like it was working. It turns out, however, that an application in development is one thing; the same app in production is another game entirely.</p>

<p>While developing an application, our environments are configured in a certain way. It&rsquo;s easy to forget that things will change once we deploy what we&rsquo;ve been working on. Being able to implement something like the <code>paperclip</code> gem in development doesn&rsquo;t easily carry over to your production environment &ndash; unless, of course, you know what tool to use. Luckily, there&rsquo;s a great gem that was created specifically to make the transition from development to production quick and easy: the <code>aws-sdk</code> gem, Amazon Web Services&#8217; Software Development Kit that was created to use with Rails applications for storing your static assets in your AWS Simple Storage bucket. And once you know how to set it up with your Heroku account, you can get rid of that pesky broken image icon once and for all!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Street Cred For The Web: S3 Credentials</h2>

<p>Amazon Web Services&#8217; Simple Storage Service (S3) is a one of the most important platform services that a web developer can use. At its most basic level, it&rsquo;s a store that allows us to store important assets that we&rsquo;ll need for our application, including things like media files, pdfs, attachments, and anything that our users may upload.</p>

<p>The <em>really</em> cool thing about AWS is that it allows us to store all those files offsite &ndash; that is to say, <em>not</em> on our Heroku application, and instead using a third-party service. Pretty amazing, right?</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/GHTwlFLITq7v2" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>This is particularly important as our application starts to grow, and we are forced to scale to size. It also makes our application super fast, since our files aren&rsquo;t being stored within our application itself, which means that we don&rsquo;t need to use our filesystem to retrieve all those assets.</p>

<p>When it comes to integrating your application with AWS S3, however, the most important step is establishing your credentials. In fact, we can&rsquo;t even hook up our <code>paperclip</code> configurations &ndash; or really, <em>any</em> configurations, for that matter &ndash; without our S3 credentials. So, where can we find them?</p>

<p>Well, first we need to know where to look. And in order to know where to look, we have to know how S3 is structured. Thankfully, S3&rsquo;s architecture is pretty simple to understand: everything is just contained in a bucket. We can name our bucket anything that we want, so long as it&rsquo;s a unique name across the Amazon system. A common convention is to name your bucket similarly to your application or repository&rsquo;s name (for example, <code>booklit-website</code>). Once we name our bucket, all of our files sent to S3 will be stored inside and belong to our bucket. An important thing to note is that <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/22173939">there are no directories</a> within a bucket; the S3 bucket itself is a top-level container.</p>

<p>Now, how can we access this unique bucket of ours? Using our credentials, of course! In order for us to access the S3 API, we need two things: an <strong>AWS Access Key ID</strong> and an <strong>AWS Secret Access Key</strong>. The access key id identifies our S3 user account, while the secret access key is our &ldquo;password&rdquo; (at least we should think of it as a password, it&rsquo;s a bit more complicated than that) for our account.</p>

<p>We can get these two pieces of information from the &ldquo;Security Credentials&rdquo; section of the AWS console menu when we log into our AWS account. But these keys aren&rsquo;t really helpful until we hook up our S3 bucket with our application. I suppose that&rsquo;s what we should do next!</p>

<h2>Keeping Secrets With <code>.env</code></h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/12ROKMe0xvJilW" width="480" height="391" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s one golden rule when it comes to our credentials: we should <strong>never, <em>ever</em> store them in a file or commit them to source control</strong>. We never, ever want our credentials to be potentially exposed to anyone via our Github repository, and yet we definitely need our credentials to exist <em>somewhere</em> within our application, don&rsquo;t we? Otherwise we won&rsquo;t be able to tell <code>paperclip</code> where to upload our files and assets. Uh oh&hellip;what do?</p>

<p>Enter <strong>environment variables</strong> to the rescue! There are a few different ways to use environment variables in a Rails application to store our credentials without actually committing them into a file. My favorite way to do this is by creating a <code>.env</code> file in the top-level directory of my application (in our case, <code>booklit-website/.env</code>). Because this file has a <code>.</code> at the beginning, it&rsquo;s actually a hidden file and won&rsquo;t be committed. To double check that this is the case, we can open up our <code>.gitignore</code> file, and make sure that our <code>.env</code> file is included as one of the files that Git should &ldquo;ignore&rdquo; while committing:</p>

<pre><code># See https://help.github.com/articles/ignoring-files for more about ignoring files.

# Ignore Environment Configuration Files
config/database.yml
.env
</code></pre>

<p>This means that we can safely put our important AWS credentials inside of our <code>.env</code> file:</p>

<pre><code>AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID=our-id-goes-here
AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY=our-access-key-goes-here
AWS_S3_REGION=us-east-1
AWS_S3_BUCKET=booklit-website-bucket
</code></pre>

<p>In addition to the Access Key Id and Secret Access Key that we grabbed from our account information page on the AWS S3 portal, we also put in our S3 Region (the US East Coast), and our S3 Bucket Name (don&rsquo;t try to hack it because it is very much <em>not a real thing</em>).</p>

<p>Okay, this hidden file with our environment variables is cool and all, but how do we actually <em>retrieve</em> these variables? Well, it&rsquo;s actually pretty easy. We can treat the variables in our <code>.env</code> file like items in a hash; if we want to access the value of an item in a hash, we can just reference the value via its key, right? The same applies here. If we want to access our <code>AWS_S3_BUCKET</code> name, we can use <code>ENV['AWS_S3_BUCKET']</code> anywhere in our application in order to access it!</p>

<p>Awesome! We have just one last step before we can finally hook up all of these variables with <code>paperclip</code> and Heroku: we need to create an <code>.env.example</code> file! This is a pretty neat convention that I really liked the first time I saw it, and have since adopted. You&rsquo;ll remember that our <code>.env</code> file is being ignored by our <code>.gitignore</code> file whenever we commit our repository or push it up to Github. This is great, obviously, since we don&rsquo;t want our private credentials to ever be public. There is one downside, however: if someone clones our repository, they&rsquo;ll never know that we even <em>have</em> a <code>.env</code> file, much less what environment variables we have defined inside of it, which means that when they try to run our application or worse, when they try to collaborate with us on it, they&rsquo;ll hit a huge roadblock, and ruby will break and not know where to look while trying to read something like <code>ENV['AWS_S3_BUCKET']</code> from within the application.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a quick fix for this: create an &ldquo;example&rdquo; <code>.env</code> file called &ndash; you guessed it &ndash; <code>.env.example</code>. We should make sure that this does <em>not</em> get included in our <code>.gitignore</code> file. Instead, we want it to be committed with our repository. It&rsquo;s also important to note that we&rsquo;re still not going to include <em>our</em> credentials in here; instead, all we&rsquo;ll do is setup our <code>.env.example</code> file as an example of how someone else should create their <code>.env</code> file when they clone or fork our repository:</p>

<pre><code>AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID=xxxxxx
AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY=xxxxxx
AWS_S3_REGION=xxxxxx
AWS_S3_BUCKET=xxxxxx
</code></pre>

<p>Now that we&rsquo;ve finally got all these variables right where we want them, we can finally get to the good stuff!</p>

<h2>Configuring Paperclip And Heroku</h2>

<p>It may seem like we spent a lot of time setting things up, but it&rsquo;s all about to come together! We initially started off planning to use the <code>aws-sdk</code> gem. Now it&rsquo;s time to implement it in the context of the <code>paperclip</code> gem and configure it to work with our Heroku deploy.</p>

<p>First we&rsquo;ll add it to our <code>Gemfile</code> (<code>gem 'aws-sdk', '~&gt; 2'</code>) and then run <code>bundle install</code>. Now our <code>Gemfile</code> should have both <code>aws-sdk</code> and <code>paperclip</code>.</p>

<p>Next, we&rsquo;ll want to head over to where all the configurations for our <em>production</em> environment are &ndash; namely, our <code>production.rb</code> file, which exists inside of our <code>config/environments</code> directory. It&rsquo;s important to make sure that we&rsquo;re not setting any Heroku configurations inside of our <code>development.rb</code> file, which only runs inside of our development environment. Since we know we&rsquo;ll be deploying only the production environment configurations to Heroku, all of our Heroku setup should always live inside of our production environment.</p>

<p>Inside of our <code>production.rb</code> file, we&rsquo;ll want to add the following configurations:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">config.paperclip_defaults = {
  storage: :s3,
  s3_credentials: {
    bucket: ENV['AWS_S3_BUCKET'],
    access_key_id: ENV['AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID'],
    secret_access_key: ENV['AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY']
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>These lines are how we specify <a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/paperclip-s3">AWS configuration variables</a> for our production environment. If we wanted to test whether we had set all this up properly, we could copy these lines into our <code>development.rb</code> and test out our S3 uploads on our local server.</p>

<p>Last, but certainly not least, we want to set these configurations up on Heroku. If we don&rsquo;t do this final step in the process, Heroku won&rsquo;t know where to look for our credentials, which means that it won&rsquo;t know where our images are being hosted when it looks inside of our <code>s3_credentials</code> hash!</p>

<p>If we haven&rsquo;t already, we&rsquo;ll want to create an application container on Heroku by running this command in the terminal:</p>

<pre><code>$ heroku create
</code></pre>

<p>And then we&rsquo;ll want to push our code to our Heroku container and run any pending migrations:</p>

<pre><code>$ git push heroku master
$ heroku rake db:migrate
</code></pre>

<p>These first two steps are only necessary if we&rsquo;ve never deployed to Heroku before. If we have, then all we really need to do is set our AWS S3 configuration variables:</p>

<pre><code>$ heroku config:set S3_BUCKET_NAME=our_bucket_name
$ heroku config:set AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID=our_access_key_id
$ heroku config:set AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY=our_secret_access_key
</code></pre>

<p>Now the moment of truth: we can run <code>heroku open</code> and see&hellip;all of our images live! Next time someone tells us we have to figure out how to safely store our assets, we&rsquo;ll know that it ain&rsquo;t no thing. We got this.</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/A4HCrFVdbxZpS" width="480" height="284" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Environment variables are how we can store our secret credentials; they live inside of the <code>.env</code> file and should never be committed to source control! Want to read more about env variables in Rails? Check out this great <a href="http://bayendor.github.io/blog/2015/01/16/managing-rails-environment-variables/">blog post</a> and this super <a href="http://railsapps.github.io/rails-environment-variables.html">informative tutorial</a>.</li>
<li>The <code>aws-sdk</code> gem is an easy way to integrate <code>paperclip</code> and AWS S3. You can dive into the gem&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/aws/aws-sdk-ruby">source code</a> to learn more!</li>
<li>Heroku has some fantastic guides on how to <a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/s3#s3-setup">set up S3</a> and how to upload files to S3 <a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/paperclip-s3">using paperclip</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clipping Images for Rails: Using Paperclip]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/28/clipping-images-for-rails-using-paperclip/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-28T08:42:36-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/28/clipping-images-for-rails-using-paperclip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.officemuseum.com/1894_Gem_Paper_Clip_adv_discovered_by_The_Early_Office_Museum.JPG" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"/></p>

<p>They say that a picture is worth a thousand words. How they came up with a such a nice, conveniently specific number number I&rsquo;ll never know. But what I do know is that everything on the web is just data floating around in cyberspace. And when I say everything, I really do mean <em>everything</em> &ndash; including pictures!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve worked on a few different projects that have required building out an interface to allow a user or an admin to upload images. The first time that I had to do this, I knew that there were a few different Rails gems out there to help make this magic happen. But I didn&rsquo;t really understand what was going on when I implemented these gems the first time around. To be quite honest, the first time I had to implement file uploading, I just followed the setup steps rather blindly. Now that I&rsquo;ve had to solve the same problem multiple times, however, I feel a bit more comfortable with the process.</p>

<p>There are a few different gems out there for handing file attachment in Rails, but my favorite one to use so far has been <strong>paperclip</strong>. Created by the super cool developers over at <a href="https://github.com/thoughtbot/paperclip">ThoughtBot</a>, the paperclip gem is fairly simple and straightforward to use. The reason that I like this gem in particular is that it fits seamlessly into the Rails framework. Files and attachments are treated just like an attribute on an ActiveRecord object, which makes the setup process both easy and intuitive. However, that doesn&rsquo;t mean that it&rsquo;s not intimidating at first! Luckily, we&rsquo;re going to walk through using the paperclip gem together.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>How To Start Clipping</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/xXG9gNuwQcN1u" width="480" height="425" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Since <code>paperclip</code> is a gem, the first thing we&rsquo;ll have to do before we really get started on clipping anything is add it to our <code>Gemfile</code>:</p>

<p><code>gem "paperclip", "~&gt; 4.3"</code></p>

<p>and then <code>bundle install</code>, because it&rsquo;s what all the cool kids do. This is also a good time to make sure that we have <code>ImageMagick</code>, which is one of <code>paperclip</code>&rsquo;s dependencies. (We can always run <code>brew install imagemagick</code> to install it if we don&rsquo;t have it already.)</p>

<p>Now it&rsquo;s time to get clipping! And take a look at our schema, obvs. For our Bookstore app, we want each of our authors to have a headshot image uploaded and associated with their work. This is going to be super important from a user experience point of view, and it will be something that will be displayed on the show page of any given author.</p>

<p>There are two ways to go about actually adding an attachment to our model; one of them is is a bit easier because it generates a migration for you. But we&rsquo;ll go ahead and write our own migration to start.</p>

<p>We already have an <code>Author</code> model and migration. What we need to do is add an <code>attachment</code> column that&rsquo;ll handle everything from file uploading to associating a file with a specific <code>Author</code> object. So, we can just write a migration (<code>rails g migration AddProfileMediaToAuthors</code>) that will add an <code>attachment</code> column to our <code>Authors</code> table:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddProfileMediaToAuthors &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def self.up
    add_attachment :authors, :profile_media
  end

  def self.down
    remove_attachment :authors, :profile_media
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>We&rsquo;ll call our attachment columns <code>profile_media</code> to preemptively namespace the different types of attachments that we might have on a single <code>Author</code>&rsquo;s page. And just in case you needed a little refresher on the difference between the <code>up</code> and <code>down</code> methods, head <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/05/19/the-secret-life-of-your-database-part-1-migrations/">over here</a>.</p>

<p>Okay, now we&rsquo;ll run <code>rake db:migrate</code>, and take a look at our <code>schema.rb</code> file. Let&rsquo;s see what happened:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">create_table "authors", force: :cascade do |t|
    t.string   "firstname"
    t.string   "lastname"
    t.datetime "created_at",         null: false
    t.datetime "updated_at",         null: false
    t.string   "profile_media_file_name"
    t.string   "profile_media_content_type"
    t.integer  "profile_media_file_size"
    t.datetime "profile_media_updated_at"
end
</code></pre>

<p>Interesting! So our <code>add_attachment</code> method actually did a lot of things for us, didn&rsquo;t it? That&rsquo;s because it&rsquo;s actually a helper method does a lot of important things that <code>paperclip</code> relies on:</p>

<ol>
<li>It adds a <code>file_name</code> for our attachment.</li>
<li>It adds a <code>content_type</code> for our attachments, which will be the <em>mime type</em> of our images.</li>
<li>It adds the <code>file_size</code> of our attachments.</li>
<li>It creates a <code>updated_at</code> column, which is particularly useful since we can order and sort our attachments/images by <code>datetime</code> format.</li>
</ol>


<p>Now we need to hook up our database migration with the corresponding model!</p>

<h2>Objects With Attached Files</h2>

<p><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_khdFP9RCQSw/TSPePSmnscI/AAAAAAAAAK4/My8FyIo8Xuo/s1600/a-jpeg-is-worth-approximately-a-thousand-words.gif" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"/></p>

<p>Inside of our <code>Author</code> class, we need want to add one very important line to our model: <code>has_attached_file</code>. The important thing about this method is that it needs to correspond to whatever we named our attachment in our migrations from earlier. In our case, we called our attachments <code>profile_media</code>, so that&rsquo;s exactly what we&rsquo;ll use inside of our model as well:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Author &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  has_attached_file :profile_media, 
    styles: { 
        large: "500x500", 
        medium: "300x300", 
        thumb: "100x100" 
    }, 
    default_url: "/images/:style/missing_profile_media.png"
end
</code></pre>

<p>This line sets up a few defaults for us and gives us the option of having a few different sizes for our <code>profile_media</code>. The <code>default_url</code> can be helpful if we ever want to give our attachment url a default and avoid an instance of <code>nil</code>. The sizes that we specify here are what we&rsquo;ll use inside of our views:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">= link_to image_tag(author.profile_media.url(:thumb)), author.profile.url
</code></pre>

<p>But the most important part of making all of this work is, of course, permitting our media to be seen! (I&rsquo;m looking at you, strong params!). All we need to do is add our attachment name (<code>profile_media</code>) to our permitted parameters, which is already being used by our controller actions:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AuthorsController &lt; ApplicationController
    def create
        author = Author.create(author_params)
    end

    private
      def author_params
        params.require(:author).permit(:firstname, :lastname, :profile_media)
      end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Pretty simple, right? But these are just the bare bones of <code>paperclip</code>. We can spice things up a bit, too!</p>

<h2>Validating And Customizing Our Clippings</h2>

<p>Once we have the gem up and working, it&rsquo;s super easy to add some bells and whistles and write it to fit our application&rsquo;s specific standards. The developers at ThoughtBot actually have several different validators that we can implement, including <code>AttachmentContentTypeValidator</code>, <code>AttachmentPresenceValidator</code>, and <code>AttachmentSizeValidator</code>. Personally, however, I prefer the old school helper methods, which function in exactly the same way.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s add a <code>validates_attachment_content_type</code> to our <code>Author</code> class, and validate that the content being uploaded is actually an <code>image</code>. We can do that with a nice regular expression:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Author &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    has_attached_file :profile_media, 
        styles: { 
            large: "500x500", 
            medium: "300x300", 
            thumb: "100x100" 
        }, 
        default_url: "/images/:style/missing_profile_media.png"

    validates_attachment_content_type :profile_media, content_type: /\Aimage\/.*\Z/
end
</code></pre>

<p>We can also validate the size and presence of our attachment as well:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">validates :profile_image, attachment_presence: :true

validates_attachment_size :profile_media, size: { in: 0..100.kilobytes }
</code></pre>

<p>And what about deleting attachments? Well, because <code>paperclip</code> is designed to work so well with ActiveRecord, any attachment we create is treated just like an attribute. As the documentation explains,</p>

<blockquote><p>The intent behind <code>paperclip</code> was to keep setup as easy as possible and to treat files as much like other attributes as possible. This means they aren&rsquo;t saved to their final locations on disk, nor are they deleted if set to nil, until ActiveRecord::Base#save is called. It manages validations based on size and presence, if required.</p></blockquote>

<p>Since the only way to delete an attachment is by setting the attribute to <code>nil</code>, there are a few different ways to actually go about deleting attachments. One implementation that I like to use is writing a custom method that checks whether an <code>Author</code> object has it&rsquo;s <code>profile_media</code> attribute equal to <code>nil</code> before saving it:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Author &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    before_save :delete_profile_media, 
        if: -&gt; { remove_profile_media == '1' &amp;&amp; !profile_media_updated_at_changed? }

    attr_accessor :remove_profile_media

    private
        def delete_profile_media
            self.profile_media = nil
        end
end
</code></pre>

<p>In this structure, I also create an attribute on my <code>Author</code> object called <code>remove_profile_media</code>, which will either be <code>0</code> or <code>1</code>, based on whether a box on a form has been checked or not. If the button is checked, <code>remove_profile_media</code> will be set to <code>1</code>, and I&rsquo;ll call the <code>delete_profile_media</code> method in my <code>before_save</code> hook.</p>

<p>If deleting data is something that scares you (or if you&rsquo;re a fan of the <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> gem) there&rsquo;s also another option. You can just preserve your files along with your &ldquo;soft deleted&rdquo; models:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Author &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
    has_attached_file :profile_media, {
        preserve_files: "true",
    }
end
</code></pre>

<p>This extra line prevents any data in our <code>profile_media</code> columns from being completely erased when the model is soft deleted. The good news here is that when the object is restored later on, our images will be too! And that is just as good of a reason as any to celebrate!</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/osMIREQbo3s2c" width="480" height="255" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>The <code>paperclip</code> gem really needs only two things to function properly: a <code>has_attached_file :attachment</code> in the model and an <code>attachment_file_name</code> column in the database. The <code>attachment_content_type</code> is only required if you&rsquo;re going to use content type validation.</li>
<li>If you want to see some <code>paperclip</code> in action, check out this <a href="http://railscasts.com/episodes/134-paperclip">RailsCast</a> that covers all the basics.</li>
<li>Want to dive into the <code>paperclip</code> source code? Go for it! Perhaps you can start by checking out their well-documented <a href="http://www.rubydoc.info/gems/paperclip/Paperclip/ClassMethods">class methods</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
