<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails | Words and Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-27T21:17:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vaidehi Joshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Embrace Your Inner Paranoia: Using Acts_as_paranoid]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/01/27/embrace-your-inner-paranoia-use-acts-as-paranoid/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-27T19:36:16-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/01/27/embrace-your-inner-paranoia-use-acts-as-paranoid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I started my very first job as a software engineer! It&rsquo;s been super exciting, slightly terrifying, and sometimes overwhelming. I think one of the trickiest parts of starting as a new engineer at a company is the onboarding process.</p>

<p>It might seem kind of scary, but if you think about it, it&rsquo;s actually pretty fun. You get to dive down a rabbit hole and look at production code that you didn&rsquo;t write. It&rsquo;s getting a new puzzle that you haven&rsquo;t solved yet: you try to figure out how one thing connects to another, where modules and methods exist, how things are namespaced, not to mention learning about new frameworks and gems. I feel like I&rsquo;m entering into new dimensions and travelling through a space-time continuum or something. This also might be attributed to the fact that I&rsquo;ve been  listening exclusively to the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YOWSTtXxf9s">Interstellar soundtrack</a> for the past two days, but whatever &ndash; you get the point.</p>

<p>My favorite part of the onboarding process is how much I&rsquo;ve been learning. Every new class or module definition brings a new piece of the puzzle that I&rsquo;ve never seen before, but can&rsquo;t wait to learn about. It&rsquo;s kind of crazy that I get paid to read and learn all day, every day &ndash; that&rsquo;s the dream, right?</p>

<p>Anyways, all of this is to say that I&rsquo;ve found and learned about some cool stuff! For example this little ditty: <code>acts_as_paranoid</code>. I saw this in a class definition and my first thought was literally: <em>Damn, that&rsquo;s a great name for a validation!</em> But as it turns out, it&rsquo;s not actually a validation &ndash; it&rsquo;s Rails magic!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Start acting paranoid!</h2>

<p>Okay, I lied: <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> not actually <em>magic</em> &ndash; it&rsquo;s a Rails ActiveRecord plugin. But it&rsquo;s still pretty magical, you guys! So, what does it do? Well, it helps you be less paranoid about deleting stuff by accident (hence the name). Essentially, <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> allows you to make soft deletes in Rails. That means that it gives you the flexibility to delete an object without actually deleting it from the database.</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/VpbctjT9VrALS" width="480" height="260" frameBorder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Does this sound like black magic yet? Just wait, you&rsquo;re about to see some real magic.</p>

<h2>So&hellip;how do I starting acting paranoid?</h2>

<p>In my example, I&rsquo;ll be implementing <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> on some <code>Book</code> objects in my eCommerce bookstore app. Using <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> is relatively simple. You can break it down into two simple steps:</p>

<p>First, add <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> to your class definition:
<code>ruby
class Book &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  acts_as_paranoid
end
</code></p>

<p>Then, add a column to the database for that class called <code>deleted_at</code>, which is set to a <code>datetime</code> format:
<code>ruby
class AddDatetimeToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_column :books, :deleted_at, :datetime
  end
end
</code></p>

<h2>Ok, I&rsquo;m getting paranoid now &ndash; how does this work?</h2>

<p>So, we have another column in our <code>Books</code> table that has a <code>deleted_at</code> column with a type of <code>:datetime</code>. Now, this is where the magic happens: the <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> plugin actually <em>overrides</em> ActiveRecord&rsquo;s <code>find</code>, <code>count</code>, and <code>destroy</code> methods. So now when we call the <code>destroy</code> method on a <code>Book</code> object, instead of actually deleting the object, the object&rsquo;s <code>deleted_at</code> field will be set to the current date and time.</p>

<p>And, if we call the <code>find</code> method on all of our <code>Book</code> objects, the one we just &ldquo;deleted&rdquo; won&rsquo;t show up! Instead, only the objects that <em>don&rsquo;t</em> have a value in their <code>deleted_at</code> column will render.</p>

<p>So, calling <code>@book.destroy</code> doesn&rsquo;t delete a row from the database; it actually just updates the row by giving a datetime to the object&rsquo;s <code>deleted_at</code> field. If you&rsquo;re into SQL queries, this is what&rsquo;s going on:</p>

<p><code>UPDATE books SET deleted_at = '2015-01-27 19:36:16' WHERE (id = 50)</code></p>

<p>The <code>Book</code> object with an id of <code>50</code> isn&rsquo;t <em>actually</em> deleted from the database, even though it will appear so in all of our views, and to our users/admins.</p>

<h2>But who needs soft deletes, anyways?</h2>

<p>I actually didn&rsquo;t realize the use case for soft deletes at first. But it turns out that they are incredibly helpful when building out large, more complicated Rails applications.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s important to remember that Ruby is an object-oriented programming language. Any object that has an association with another object inherently relies upon it. In my bookstore app example, a <code>Book</code> object would belong to a <code>Order</code> object, and also be associated with a <code>User</code> object of some sort. If you think about the appliation on a broader, less granular level, you might realize that deleting any given <code>Book</code> object could actually have serious repercussions.</p>

<p>For example, you might want to see a <code>Book</code> object that was ordered in the past, even if that <code>Book</code> has since been deleted from a store. Perhaps you want to view the details of a <code>Shipment</code> object, even if that shipment was cancelled. Or, you might want to see an order that was placed by a <code>User</code> who may have deactivated their account months ago.</p>

<p>The <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> plugin helps you access all of this information, without keeping you up at night, wondering whether you deleted the wrong row from the database. Because honestly, who has time for that? Not this kitty, for sure:</p>

<p><img src="https://idp05.files.wordpress.com/2008/03/paranoid-cat.jpg" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>The <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> plugin modifies ActiveRecord methods and allows you to implement soft deletes on your Ruby objects. Just remember to include it in your class definition and add a <code>deleted_at</code> column to your migration, with a type of <code>datetime</code>.</li>
<li>Want to see another example of disabling records using <code>acts_as_paranoid</code>? Check out <a href="https://www.safaribooksonline.com/library/view/rails-cookbook/0596527314/ch14s11.html">this blog post</a>.</li>
<li>To read more about <code>acts_as_paranoid</code> and its many caveats, check out <a href="https://github.com/ActsAsParanoid/acts_as_paranoid/">the easy-to-follow documentation</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tidying Up Those Views: Using Decorators in Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/01/13/tidying-up-those-views-using-decorators-in-rails/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-13T22:53:10-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/01/13/tidying-up-those-views-using-decorators-in-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I had my first full-day technical interview. It was a thrilling experience, and so much more fun than I expected. Part of that was because I viewed the whole experience not as an evaluation, but rather an opportunity to learn as much as I could from experienced developers. I also knew that, irrespective of whether I did well or not, I&rsquo;d learn some new technologies and tricks. And boy, was that the truth.</p>

<p>I left the interview with a long list of things I&rsquo;d never heard of (<em>why hello, blog posts for the next five Tuesdays!</em>), one of which included the use of decorators in Rails. I was actually kind of surprised that I had never encountered decorators while building my own Rails apps, but it turns out that these are actually pretty advanced topics and there&rsquo;s a good amount of <a href="https://bibwild.wordpress.com/2012/12/19/the-simplest-rails-decorator-implementation-that-just-might-work/">debate on how and when to use decorators</a>, and <a href="http://thepugautomatic.com/2014/03/draper/">whether or not they&rsquo;re actually useful</a>.</p>

<p>But hey, none these discussions apply or make any sense unless you know <em>what</em> a decorator actually is. So, let&rsquo;s find out!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a well-known fact that your Rails model should be fat, and your controllers should be skinny. But what about your views? Well, there are varying schools of thought on the MVC framework and how it should function. Steve Klabnik <a href="http://blog.steveklabnik.com/posts/2011-12-30-active-record-considered-harmful">argued that views should have no logic</a>, stating that otherwise &ldquo;They&rsquo;re hard to test, they&rsquo;re hard to read, and it&rsquo;s not just a slippery slope, but a steep one. Things go downhill rapidly.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I really liked the way that John Otander described how views should function in <a href="http://johnotander.com/rails/2014/03/07/decorators-on-rails/">his blog post on decorators</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Your views should be stupid. I like to use the analogy that views should read similarly to a shopping list. There shouldn&rsquo;t be any complexity or logic.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>I decided to look back at <a href="https://flatiron-cabbie.herokuapp.com/">Cabbie</a>, one of my first projects, and check out the shape of my own views. This app basically was a review system (think Yelp) for New York City cab drivers. We had models such as Users, Drivers, Reviews, etc.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a taste of our driver show page:</p>

<p>&#8220;`erb</p>

<div class="driver-info">
  <%= @driver.medallion_number %>
  <% if @driver.medallion_number.length == 4 %>
    Medallion Number: <%= @driver.medallion_number %>
  <% else %>
    License Number: <%= @driver.medallion_number %>
  <% end %>
</div>


<p>&#8220;`</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/jrK9MW7x3GkOk" width="480" height="199" frameBorder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s pretty much the face I made when I looked at this code with a fresh set of eyes. This is one tiny little snippet of code, but imagine many more conditionals and much more logic in this view, and you get the idea. Not a pretty picture.</p>

<p>A couple things seemed problematic about this code:</p>

<ol>
<li>The first problem was that the view had to do the logic of figuring out whether a driver had a four-digit medallion number (NYC taxi) or a longer medallion number (an Uber driver). How could we fix this? Well, we could abstract this into a method in the class.</li>
<li>The second problem: why is it the <code>Driver</code> object&rsquo;s job to keep track of this? Do we really need a helper method in this case? All we really need this logic for is in rendering the view. We could make it its own class that inherits from the Driver class, maybe?</li>
<li>Ok, the third problem: we know what we want &ndash; a <code>Driver</code> object that has some special functionality when it comes to presenting it in the view. But how do we get it? We want to extend the behavior of the <code>Driver</code> class purely for decorative purposes. Sounds like a job for a <strong>decorator</strong>!</li>
</ol>


<p>So, what is a decorator, you might ask? Well, firstly, it&rsquo;s actually known as the <strong>decorator pattern</strong>. An aspect of object-oriented programming, decorators allow you to add functionality to an object, but also retains all the other methods that belong to that object&rsquo;s class. It&rsquo;s a great tool to use when you want to implement and/or encapsulate certain methods that are only used in the view, and yet still have access to all the other properties of that object.</p>

<p>The best way to learn what a decorator does is to try and use it yourself and see what happens. I implemented my decorator on my Cabbie app, using the <a href="https://github.com/drapergem/draper">Draper gem</a>.</p>

<p>First, you&rsquo;ll want to make sure you add <code>gem 'draper'</code> to your Gemfile.</p>

<p>Next, you&rsquo;ll want to generate the decorator for whatever object you want to &lsquo;decorate&rsquo;. In my case, I wanted to implement it on the driver object, so I typed <code>rails generate decorator Driver</code> into my terminal.</p>

<p>Then, add <code>.decorate</code> to your object in the appropriate controller. Here&rsquo;s how I did it in my <code>DriversController</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class DriversController &lt; ApplicationController

  def show
    @driver = Driver.find(params[:id]).decorate
  end

  def search
    @driver = Driver.find_by(:medallion_number =&gt; params[:medallion_number].upcase).decorate
  end

end
</code></pre>

<p>After generating your decorator, you&rsquo;ll notice that there&rsquo;s a new directory in your <code>/app</code> file called <code>decorators</code>. Nothing to be scared of here: it&rsquo;s just a class that inherits from the Draper Decorator gem. Here&rsquo;s where you&rsquo;ll add any additonal functionality you want your &lsquo;decorated&rsquo; object to have.</p>

<p>In my case, I wanted to abstract away the Driver&rsquo;s medallion/license number away and encapsulate it into a method. I created an <code>id_number</code> method in my decorator file:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class DriverDecorator &lt; Draper::Decorator
  delegate_all

  def id_number
    if medallion_number.length == 4
      "Medallion Number: #{medallion_number}"
    else
      "License Number: #{medallion_number}"
    end
  end

end
</code></pre>

<p>Okay, you still with me? Here&rsquo;s the satisfying part. Cut out all that ridiculous erb from your view &ndash; we don&rsquo;t need that anymore! Instead, we&rsquo;ll just call on the decorator method that we wrote for exactly this purpose. Ready? Okay. Let&rsquo;s do this:</p>

<p>&#8220;`erb</p>

<div class="driver-info">
  <%= @driver.id_number %>
</div>


<p>&#8220;`</p>

<p>LOOK. AT. THAT. No iterations. No <code>if</code>/<code>elsif</code>/<code>end</code> keywords. One method, being called on exactly one object. No logic at all. You can read this and know exactly what we&rsquo;re trying to render. <em>Beautiful</em>.</p>

<p>As lovely as this looks, it&rsquo;s also important to keep in mind that this is an advanced topic and not always necessary. Only use decorators if they&rsquo;ll actually clean up your code and be helpful.</p>

<p>And on that note, there&rsquo;s only one thing left to do: Get tidying, kids!</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/s90QFDMh0RAIg" width="480" height="269" frameBorder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Using a decorator isn&rsquo;t always the right answer. Make sure you&rsquo;re comfortable with the MVC framework and that you really need to use a decorator before you go about implementing one.</li>
<li>If you want a more in-depth introduction to presenters and decorators, check out <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xf7i44HJ_1o">this RailsConf presentation by Mike Moore</a>.</li>
<li>If this is still confusing, read more code examples; there are lots of <a href="http://robots.thoughtbot.com/evaluating-alternative-decorator-implementations-in">really</a> <a href="https://bibwild.wordpress.com/2012/12/19/the-simplest-rails-decorator-implementation-that-just-might-work/">good</a> <a href="http://robots.thoughtbot.com/tidy-views-and-beyond-with-decorators">blog</a> <a href="http://johnotander.com/rails/2014/03/07/decorators-on-rails/">posts</a> that implement decorators.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
