<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sql | Words and Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/categories/sql/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-03T17:46:08-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vaidehi Joshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Safer SQL: Using ActiveRecord Transactions]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/08/18/safer-sql-using-activerecord-transactions/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-18T08:11:32-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/08/18/safer-sql-using-activerecord-transactions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/Djnfk5gnoNXqM" width="480" height="356" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Is there anything more satisfying than writing concise, perfect line of SQL and then watching it query your database exactly as you expected? Probably not. Writing &mdash; and subsequently watching! &mdash; an efficient database query is one of my favorite parts of building an application.</p>

<p>But if there&rsquo;s one thing about software development that I&rsquo;ve learned over the past few months, it&rsquo;s this: projects can get out of control, rather quickly. You start off with your basic models, but then as you add one feature after another, things can start to get out of hand. At that point, your focus as a developer shifts and spreads out to various things. You can&rsquo;t just care about how readable your code is; you also have to consider how efficient it is, and how different units of your application might be breaking other parts (hopefully not unbeknownst to you!). In other words, you have to consider how defensive and <em>safe</em> your code actually is.</p>

<p>Recently, while writing some background jobs and creating some service objects for a new feature, I realized the importance of executing and enforcing safe code. The good news is that there&rsquo;s a really helpful, life-saving ActiveRecord <strong>transaction</strong> method that allows you to do exactly this. And the really great news? You get to watch your SQL queries execute safely as a result!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Database Handshakes</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/gVYk3rI8YjtAI" width="480" height="422" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>As our application grows, there are inevitably going to be different models that depend upon each other. To make things more complicated, those models are going to have to change as our Users take different actions, and that means that we&rsquo;ll need to update different associated parts of our schema as a result. For example, let&rsquo;s say that we have a background job that&rsquo;s responsible for processing an <code>Order</code> on an <code>User</code>. This background job has a service class that takes care of saving an <code>Order</code> when it has been charged, billing the <code>User</code>, and adding a sale to an <code>Vendor</code> object, which will then be visible on the vendor&rsquo;s dashboard panel/admin page.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">if order.process
    user.charge
    vendor.add_sale
end
</code></pre>

<p>In other words, we&rsquo;re basically transferring money from our <code>User</code> object to our <code>Vendor</code> objects. At first glance, this might not seem like a potentially &ldquo;unsafe&rdquo; set of queries, but here&rsquo;s where things can get a bit tricky: imagine that our <code>User</code>&rsquo;s credit card information is rejected, or for some reason, the charge cannot be created. In that scenario, we&rsquo;d want to handle the errors and make sure that the <code>add_sale</code> method is <em>not</em> called on our <code>Vendor</code> object. However&hellip;we aren&rsquo;t really safeguarding our code against this situation at all, are we?</p>

<p>But, fear not - it&rsquo;s not a totally hopeless situation! In fact, we can take care of this problem pretty easily by using ActiveRecord&rsquo;s <code>transaction</code> blocks.</p>

<p>The <code>transaction</code> method is defined in the Rails source code under the <code>ActiveRecord::Transactions</code> module. This method takes a block, and whenever it is invoked, the block that is passed to it will be executed inside of a <em>database transaction</em>. If, in the course of executing that block, an <code>exception</code> is raised, the database transaction will automatically be rolled back. No SQL will be executed, and no new data will be added to the database</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">Order.transaction do
    @order.process
    @user.charge
    @vendor.add_sale
end
</code></pre>

<p>So what does this mean, exactly? Well, now that we&rsquo;ve wrapped the logic of our three methods inside of a <code>transaction</code> method, we can safely assert that in the case that <em>any</em> of these three methods raises an <code>exception</code> (in other words, fails for any reason), the entire process should fail.</p>

<p>The important piece of this is that we&rsquo;ll never be adding or updating any data (or writing to our database) unless all of these methods are successful. It&rsquo;s crucial for us to ensure that this is the case because we&rsquo;d never want to call the <code>add_sale</code> method and write data to our <code>vendor</code> if the <code>order</code> didn&rsquo;t successfully <code>process</code>, or if our <code>user</code> wasn&rsquo;t successfully <code>charged</code>.</p>

<p>I like to think of these blocks as a &ldquo;handshake&rdquo; between your application and your database: your application and database have an understanding that one will hand off information to the other in a &ldquo;transaction&rdquo;, and when the deal actually goes through, they shake hands and make it official&hellip;or something more poetic. If that made no sense &mdash; or if you&rsquo;re not a big fan of metaphors &mdash; here&rsquo;s how the Rails documentation explains <code>transactions</code>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Transactions are protective blocks where SQL statements are only permanent if they can all succeed as one atomic action. Transactions enforce the integrity of the database and guard the data against program errors or database break-downs. So basically you should use transaction blocks whenever you have a number of statements that must be executed together or not at all.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<h2>The Rules of Transacting</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/cGDgkEeqA78Q" width="480" height="397" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Because ActiveRecord transactions can be easily explained and simplified as a single method, it&rsquo;s easy to forget the idiosyncrasies that make this method work. There are a few things to keep in mind so that we can get the most out of these blocks.</p>

<h3>1. Opening database connections</h3>

<p>A transaction opens up a single database connection. This means that when we call the <code>transaction</code> method, the method can only be invoked on the <em>current</em> database connection. This is important to remember if our application writes to multiple database at once; for example, if our <code>Order</code> and our <code>Vendor</code> data lived in two different databases, we&rsquo;d need to nest our transactions:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">Order.transaction do
    Vendor.transaction do 
        order.process
        user.charge
        vendor.add_sale
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>It&rsquo;s generally a good idea to avoid nested transactions, mostly because the relationship between parent and child transactions can get complicated. This is especially the case because rollbacks are contained <em>inside</em> of their transactions blocks. I think that Mark Daggett explains this pretty well in <a href="http://markdaggett.com/blog/2011/12/01/transactions-in-rails/">his blog</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;ActiveRecord::Rollback does not propagate outside of the containing transaction block and so the parent transaction does not receive the exception nested inside the child. I find it easier to think of nested transactions like the child who dumps its contents into the parent container, leaving the child transaction empty. To ensure a rollback is received by the parent transaction you must add the <code>requires_new: true</code>. option to the child transaction.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<h3>2. Different classes, one transaction</h3>

<p>Because transactions are bound to <em>database connections</em>, we can mix different types of models inside of a <code>transaction</code> block. In fact, that&rsquo;s exactly what we were doing when we wrote our initial transaction:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">Order.transaction do
    @order.process
    @user.charge
    @vendor.add_sale
end
</code></pre>

<h3>3. Class and instance methods</h3>

<p>The great part about <code>transaction</code> is that it is available to us as both a class <em>and</em> an instance method for our ActiveRecord models. What does this mean, exactly? Well, the short answer is that we can write a transaction is lots of different ways, since we can invoke the <code>transaction</code> method on a class or an instance.</p>

<p>For example, we could have written this:
<code>ruby
User.transaction do
    # methods we want to call go here
end
</code></p>

<p>Or this:
<code>ruby
Vendor.transaction do
    # methods we want to call go here
end
</code></p>

<p>Or any of these:
<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="vi">@order</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">transaction</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;p&gt;@user.transaction do</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">end&lt;/</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="vi">@vendor</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">transaction</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p>And if we were writing a method <em>inside</em> of the <code>Order</code>, <code>Vendor</code>, or <code>User</code> classes, these options would have worked as well:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">self.transaction do
end

self.class.transaction do
end
</code></pre>

<p>The key here is that the <code>transaction</code> can be called on <em>any class</em> that inherits from <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>. Why is that the key? Well, you might remember that we initially started off wanting to write a transaction inside of our service object&hellip;right? In that case, we can&rsquo;t use something like <code>transaction do</code>, because <code>self</code> is the service object class, which <em>does <strong>not</strong> inherit</em> from <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>!</p>

<p>So, what do? Well, just call the transaction method onto <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code> directly! there&rsquo;s a quick fix for that.
<code>ruby
ActiveRecord::Base.transaction do
    # methods we want to call go here
end
</code></p>

<p>When in doubt, we can always just call the <code>transaction</code> method onto the <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code> class directly to be sure that it will run.</p>

<h3>4. Exceptions are the rule</h3>

<p>There&rsquo;s one golden rule of the <code>transaction</code> block: it will <strong>only rollback the transaction if an error is raised</strong>.</p>

<p>Why is this important? Well, calling something like <code>save</code> or <code>destroy</code> inside of a transaction will not raise an error; if something goes wrong, these methods will simply return <code>false</code>. Which means that our <code>transaction</code> block will continue, since there was no error raised!</p>

<p>Uh oh&hellip;how to fix? Just use the <code>save!</code> and <code>destroy!</code> methods instead! These are both ActiveRecord methods which raise an exception if they don&rsquo;t execute successfully:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">ActiveRecord::Base.transaction do
    @order.destroy!
    @user.save!
end
</code></pre>

<p>And that&rsquo;s exactly what we need in this case, because we want the entire transaction to be closed if one or both of these methods are unsuccessful, and we want to tell the database that no data has changed. If we really, <em>really</em> wanted to use <code>save</code> instead of <code>save!</code>, we&rsquo;d have to manually <code>raise</code> an error in the block for our transaction to work as expected.</p>

<h2>Transactions Under The Hood</h2>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/iUOzkJmvnFfqM" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>One of the interesting things about how <code>transaction</code> works under the hood has to do with how the <code>save</code> and <code>destroy</code> methods work. It turns out that Rails actually wraps the <code>save</code> and <code>destroy</code> methods in their own <code>transaction</code>s! So, we were using <code>ActiveRecord::Base.transaction</code> all along, without probably ever knowing what was really happening! Pretty crazy, right?</p>

<p>There are a couple reasons that <code>save</code> and <code>destroy</code> are particularly curious. First, because they each occur in their own transactions, this means that we&rsquo;ll never need to write a <code>transaction</code> block to update a single record. In fact, that&rsquo;s exactly what Rails is  doing for us when we call something like <code>@user.save</code> &mdash; it&rsquo;s running a <code>transaction</code> block behind the scenes.</p>

<p>The second reason this is interesting is because of callbacks that are associated with these two methods. A callback hook like <code>after_save</code> is actually part of the same active transaction that was opened when we called <code>@user.save</code>. So, if we wanted our code to execute <em>outside</em> of Rails&#8217; default <code>transaction</code> that wraps around <code>save</code> or <code>destroy</code>, we&rsquo;d want to use callback hooks like <code>after_commit</code> or <code>after_destroy</code>. If we want something specific to happen when the <code>save</code> <code>transaction</code> succeeds, we&rsquo;d have to use the <code>after_commit</code> callback, and if we want something specific to happen when the <code>save</code> <code>transaction</code> fails, we could use the <code>after_rollback</code> hook.</p>

<p>While reading about transactions and the <code>save</code> and <code>destroy</code> methods, I discovered another really interesting method called <code>with_transaction_returning_status</code>. The <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/master/activerecord/lib/active_record/transactions.rb">transactions source code</a> is a bit of a rabbit hole, but if we spend some time reading through it, there&rsquo;s a lot to learn.</p>

<p>In a nutshell, the <code>with_transaction_returning_status</code> is responsible for actually <em>raising</em> an <code>ActiveRecord::Rollback</code>. Somewhere inside of the black box of Rails magic, when we see an error caused by a <code>save</code> transaction that looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>:001 &gt; user = User.find(1)
:002 &gt; user.save
    (0.2ms)  begin transaction
    User Exists (0.6ms)  SELECT * FROM "users" WHERE ("users"."id" = 1)
   (0.1ms)  rollback transaction
 =&gt; false 
</code></pre>

<p>it&rsquo;s actually a method like <code>with_transaction_returning_status</code> that&rsquo;s responsible for causing that rollback to happen! Here&rsquo;s a truncated example of the source code; we can see that this method defines a local <code>status</code> variable, sets and returns the <code>status</code> if the <code>transaction</code> is successful, and <code>raises</code> an error, if the <code>status</code> is not defined:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">def with_transaction_returning_status
    status = nil
    self.class.transaction do
        # some Rails magic here that captures the
        # return value of a save or destroy method,
        # and then sets that to the status.

        raise ActiveRecord::Rollback unless status
    end
    status
end
</code></pre>

<p>The Rails documentation also briefly explains exactly what&rsquo;s happening:</p>

<blockquote><p>Executes <code>method</code> within a transaction and captures its return value as a status flag. If the status is true the transaction is committed, otherwise a ROLLBACK is issued. In any case the status flag is returned.</p></blockquote>

<p>Transactions are all around us, it seems, from the most everyday methods to the more complicated ones that we write ourselves. They&rsquo;re a great way of keeping our code safe while also defending against things like duplicate SQL queries.</p>

<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>ActiveRecord&rsquo;s <code>transaction</code> method takes a block, and will only execute the block and write to your database if no exceptions are raised.</li>
<li>You can defined the <code>transaction</code> method on any class that <em>inherits from</em> <code>ActiveRecord::Base</code>, and that transaction will open up a single new database connection.</li>
<li>Check out the Jeff Casimir helpful <a href="https://gist.github.com/jcasimir/1098368">summary of transactions</a> in his Gist. Or, if you&rsquo;re looking for a challenge, head over to the Rails <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveRecord/Transactions/ClassMethods.html">documentation</a> on ActiveRecord transactions.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[All the Columns Fit to Index: Unique + Compound Indexing]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/21/all-the-columns-fit-to-index-unique-plus-compound-indexing/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-21T08:02:04-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/21/all-the-columns-fit-to-index-unique-plus-compound-indexing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/MMEfo9QQgKInK" width="480" height="269" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Database indexing: the last frontier. Well, okay, not the <em>last</em> frontier perse&hellip;more like the frontier that I&rsquo;ve been reading about a lot recently. While learning about writing about <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/14/writing-smart-migrations-references-reversible-and-indexes/">smart and efficient</a> migrations, I stumbled upon a rabbit hole that I had to restrain myself from going down: the rabbit hole of <strong>database indexing</strong>. But this week, I allowed myself to explore and learn some more about how indexes work.</p>

<p>As the cat gif above might already suggest, an index in a database is much like an index in a book: a place where you can quickly look up the exact information that you need. We already know that indexing can be super helpful when it comes to application performance. Using indexes forces our database to use integers to look up rows &ndash; which are just representations of items or objects &ndash; in our database. The reason that they&rsquo;re so efficient is because looking up something in a database is both fast <em>and</em> cheap if we use an integer to do it (using a string on the other hand, is much, much slower and more expensive). By implementing a simple index, we can speed up a single query by seconds!</p>

<p>But it turns out that even a single index can be complicated. And that&rsquo;s because there are so many kinds of indexes available for us to use. In fact, there&rsquo;s a whole <em>world</em> of different types of database indexes out there. Of course, knowing the options available to us when it comes to database indexing is just half the battle; the other half is knowing when it&rsquo;s the right time to use all these different types of indexes. The best way to learn is by playing around with some indexing ourselves &ndash; so let&rsquo;s dive in!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Indexes All Around Us</h2>

<p>The most common index type that we have dealt with so far are <strong>single-column</strong> indexes. They work pretty much exactly as their name would suggest: they create an index on a specific column of a database. So far, almost all of the indexes we&rsquo;ve generated have been indexed on a specific single column of a table.</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/bjDq7WCjstuPS" width="480" height="329" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s think for a second: when we use a PostgreSQL to run a migration, the one column that always gets generated is an <code>id</code> column, which is unique for every row in that database, even if the object is deleted. If we think about it, that&rsquo;s an example of an index. In fact, PostgreSQL automatically generates an index for the primary key of any table, and always generates a new, unique key for each new row in the database.</p>

<p>One of the very first migrations we ran for our Bookstore application looked like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class CreateBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    create_table :books do |t|
      t.string :title
    end 
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>and generated a tiny little table, which didn&rsquo;t have all that much &ndash; but it did have an index as its <code>id</code> primary key column, which we can confirm by looking at our <code>structure.sql</code> file:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">CREATE TABLE books (
    id integer NOT NULL,
    title character varying(255)
)
</code></pre>

<p>The advantage of having an <code>id integer</code> column here is that our database can very easily look up a specific row in our <code>books</code> table by using the index. We can also see that there&rsquo;s automatically a <code>NOT NULL</code> validation that prevents any row in the database from being created <em>without</em> an <code>id</code>. This isn&rsquo;t something that we wrote &ndash; this is something that Postgres does automatically! And although it might seem pretty obvious and a bit simple right now, it&rsquo;s important to note &ndash; especially since indexes can get rather complicated, rather fast.</p>

<p>Another form of indexing that we&rsquo;ve played around with is adding our own indexes to <code>has_many</code> and <code>belongs_to</code> associations, often by using <code>references</code> to alias those relationships:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_reference :books, :genre, index: true
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>And if we already have a relationship set up, we can just write a quick migration to manually add an index to our <code>books</code> table:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreIndexToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_index :books, :genre
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This migration adds an index on <code>genre_id</code> column within our <code>books</code> table, which makes it very quick and easy to look up a book by it&rsquo;s corresponding genre. This is still only a single-column, or <strong>independent index</strong>, because it is only dealing with a single column within a database table. But if there are single indexes, that must mean that the idea of &ldquo;multiple&rdquo; indexes is also must be a real thing, right?</p>

<h2>Two Indexes Are (Sometimes) Better Than One</h2>

<p>Indexes are easy to add; what&rsquo;s harder is knowing what <em>kind</em> of index to add. Sometimes, a single-column index does the trick. But it&rsquo;s also possible that it&rsquo;s quite the right tool for the job.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say that we are doing an overhaul on our Bookstore application and scaling for size. We&rsquo;ve decided that in addition to selling our own curated selection of books, we&rsquo;re also going to allow new, lesser-known bookstores to sign up for our service and sell their own books. Our vendors will have their own admin panel (think vendor portal), and the bookstore staff will have a separate admin panel from which to monitor all the sales across all the vendors who are signed up for our service.</p>

<p>All of our admins (staff and vendors) have an <code>user_id</code>. But, our staff and our vendors aren&rsquo;t just simple users of our application &ndash; they have special roles, and need access to specific pages, depending on their roles. Our admins also have an <code>admin_id</code> in addition to their base <code>user_ids</code>, while our vendors have a <code>vendor_id</code>, based on their roles as smaller-scale booksellers who will be using our software to sell their products.</p>

<p>Within our staff admin panel, we want our admins to be able to quickly view all sales across our signed up vendors, in addition to one specific vendors sales reports. If an admin logs into the admin panel and clicks on a specific bookseller, the panel should immediately load all the information pertinent to that specific vendor.</p>

<p>The first thing we might think to do is what we already know &ndash; namely, add an index on the columns we know we want to look up:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddIndexesToUsers &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
    def change
        add_index :users
        add_index :users, :vendor_id
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>However, these indexes don&rsquo;t actually do what we think they&rsquo;ll do. This adds an index to the primary key column on our <code>users</code> table, which will allow us to quickly look up a single <code>User</code>. It also adds an index to our <code>vendor_id</code> column, and allows us to look up a <code>User</code> instance based on its <code>vendor_id</code>, if it has one.</p>

<p>But here&rsquo;s the rub: we&rsquo;re only adding a single index in this migration. That is to say, we&rsquo;re adding an index on our <code>user_ids</code>, and we&rsquo;re adding an index on our <code>vendor_ids</code>. What we <em>really</em> need is an index that first sorts our data by <code>user_id</code>, and then filters down to the users that match our <code>vendor_id</code>.</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/PUBxelwT57jsQ" width="480" height="332" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t worry, this is totally doable! We just need to index <em>two</em> columns, instead of one. Actually, there&rsquo;s a perfect name &ndash; or set of names &ndash; for what we need: a <strong>compound index</strong> (aka a concatenated, multi-column, composite or combined index).</p>

<p>Ultimately, we want our database to execute a query that looks something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT * FROM users WHERE user_id = ? AND vendor_id = ?;
</code></pre>

<p>so that we can avoid writing a SQL statement in our <code>UsersController</code> like we have now (ew, let&rsquo;s not do that):</p>

<pre><code>class UsersController &lt; ApplicationController
    def sign_in
        @user = User.where("user_id = ? AND vendor_id = ?", params[:user_id], params[:vendor_id])
        # authenticate and sign in the vendor
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>So how are we going to manage all of this, you might ask? Well, pretty easily. Writing a compound index is almost as easy as writing a single-column index:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddIndexesToUsers &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
    def change
        add_index :users, [:id, vendor_id]
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>And that&rsquo;s it! But what&rsquo;s happening, exactly? Well, we&rsquo;re still creating a single index, but we&rsquo;re doing it across multiple columns. The first column (<code>user_id</code>) is the primary &ldquo;sort criterion&rdquo;, and the second column (<code>vendor_id</code>) is the secondary &ldquo;sort criterion&rdquo;. The important thing to remember here is that <em>order matters</em>. We&rsquo;ll only ever look up a vendor by <code>user_id</code> first, and then by <code>vendor_id</code>. This makes sense if you think about it, since we&rsquo;ll first want to authenticate by the user currently logged in (in other words, using the current session).</p>

<p>I really liked the way that Markus Winand describes two-column indexing on <a href="http://use-the-index-luke.com/sql/where-clause/the-equals-operator/concatenated-keys">his blog</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The ordering of a two-column index is therefore like the ordering of a telephone directory: it is first sorted by surname, then by first name. That means that a two-column index does not support searching on the second column alone; that would be like searching a telephone directory by first name.</p></blockquote>

<p>Compound indexes are super cool because they let you quickly look up the first field/column in a database, and then quickly look up <em>another</em> field/column in a database &ndash; but only within the records that were returned by the first index. At the end of the query, you&rsquo;ll only have rows that satisfy parts of that <code>AND</code> SQL query we wrote earlier!</p>

<h2>Indexes Like None Other</h2>

<p>I think we can all agree that indexing can help us narrow down a lot of rows in a database and is probably the coolest filtration system ever invented by and for developers. But that&rsquo;s not all that indexes can do! They can also prevent some pretty sticky situations that we often overlook.</p>

<p>By now, something that we&rsquo;re all familiar with is validations. One of the most common kinds of validations that we see in our Rails models all of the time is <code>uniqueness:true</code>, or <code>validates_uniqueness_of</code>. However, here&rsquo;s something we don&rsquo;t always think about (or perhaps never even realized): these validations only occur at the the ActiveRecord level. And this fact can pose some problems.</p>

<p>Imagine two vendors are signing up to use our Bookstore app. They both want to name their store the same thing, but we definitely don&rsquo;t want that to happen. So we add this line to our <code>Users</code> table:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">module User
    class Vendor &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
      validates :store_name, presence: true, uniqueness: true
    end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Cool, so this is fine then, right? Wrong! Because we just sent out an email blast telling all these potential vendors that they could sign up for a free 60-day trial. Now, all of a sudden, tons of vendors are signing up! And it just so happens, that two of them signed up at almost the exact same second, and wanted to use the same name: <code>Super Cool Books</code> (I know, I know, what are the chances, right?!)</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the problem: the moment that both of these potential vendors signed up for our service, no row in our polymorphic <code>vendors</code> database existed with a <code>store_name</code> that corresponded to the string, <code>Super Cool Books</code>. So what did ActiveRecord do? It created a new row! Actually&hellip;it created <em>two</em> new rows. At almost the exact same time. With the <em>exact same store name</em>. Uh oh.</p>

<p>So how can we fix this? We need to take our <code>uniqueness</code> validation down another level. In fact, we need to make our <em>database</em> responsible for validating uniqueness. And we can do this by adding a <strong>unique index</strong>.</p>

<p>Again, this is pretty easy. We just need to add a <code>unique: true</code> constraint on the column that we want to be able to index:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddStoreNameIndexToVendors
  def change
    add_index :vendors, :store_name, unique: true
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now, when two vendors try to sign up to be called <code>Super Cool Books</code>, only one will actually be able to have that name. As soon as an unique index is created on the <code>store_name</code> column of our <code>vendors</code> database, any other record that tries to be created with that index will raise a <code>ActiveRecord::RecordNotUnique</code> error. This is going to be super helpful to us in avoiding inconsistant data, particularly when we know that a lot of data is going to be created at once.</p>

<p>The world of indexes is mostly uncharted territory. It&rsquo;s also important to keep in mind that you never want to create <em>too</em> many indexes, and only ones that we actually need, since they will <a href="http://www.rubyonrails365.com/low-hanging-fruits-for-better-sql-performance-in-rails/">slow down</a> the &ldquo;write&rdquo; time to the database (whenever we use SQL commands like <code>UPDATE</code> or <code>CREATE</code>, for example). But that doesn&rsquo;t mean we can&rsquo;t learn about the different kinds of indexes that exist and be completely wowed at how amazing databases are. See, this cat is completely floored &ndash; and quite frankly, I am too:</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/vSSdLSLbGIXio" width="480" height="453" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>There are three main types of indexing: <em>single-column</em>, <em>compound</em>, and <em>unique</em> indexes. Compound indexes create an index on two ore more columns in a database, while unique indexes create a restraint on a single column index.</li>
<li>This <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/1049392">StackOverflow answer</a> is the best explanation of how compound indexes actually work in terms of running a query. If you&rsquo;re still confused, give it a read!</li>
<li>Uniqueness validations are super cool! Read more about them over <a href="https://robots.thoughtbot.com/the-perils-of-uniqueness-validations">here</a>, and check out some real-life examples of how to use them <a href="http://nyonura.com/blog/2014/Partial-Indexes-with-PostgreSQL-and-Rails/">here</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing Smart Migrations: References, Reversible, and Indexes]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/14/writing-smart-migrations-references-reversible-and-indexes/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-14T08:47:19-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/14/writing-smart-migrations-references-reversible-and-indexes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/SUtPZfyDenHoY" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>All it takes is a single feature to make you realize how well &ndash; or perhaps not so well &ndash; you&rsquo;ve written your application. Depending on if you&rsquo;ve done a good job of separating concerns, abstracting and encapsulating bits of functionality into cohesive code, and just generally not repeating yourself&hellip;well, you&rsquo;ll probably be way more enthusiastic about adding a huge new feature to an already massive application. But if you haven&rsquo;t done any of those things&hellip;well, you might find yourself doing a massive rewrite of your codebase just to implement a single feature.</p>

<p>Luckily, the application I started adding a feature to last week is pretty well-built, which makes it flexible enough to add new functionality relatively easily. Yet even the most well-thought-out applications need to be teased apart and glued back together during the course of their lives. Often times, a big part of building out a new feature is restructuring the architecture of your application. When you&rsquo;re working with larger code bases (legacy code in particular), that can be the most daunting task. But a lot of the intimidation of that begins to dissipate once you know how to go about restructuring a schema which already exists without breaking all the the things.</p>

<p>The first step in this process is writing migrations to change how the objects in your application and database relate to one another. Of course, knowing how to write the proper migration to suit your needs is just half the battle; the other half is writing a migration that makes object lookup in your database efficient and super fast. Even though I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/05/19/the-secret-life-of-your-database-part-1-migrations/">written about migrations</a> before, I&rsquo;m learning that there&rsquo;s always so much more to know. So, let&rsquo;s get learning!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Referencing Your References</h2>

<p>A really quick way to clean up our code is by changing the way that we create associations between objects from within our migrations. One feature we&rsquo;ll want to add is to have our <code>Book</code>s belong to a <code>Genre</code>. So far, we&rsquo;ve categorized our <code>Author</code>s by genre, but we&rsquo;ll want to be able to sort and organize our <code>Book</code> objects in a similar way.</p>

<p>We often use <code>belongs_to</code> and <code>has_many</code> inside of our migrations, which is totally valid. But in this case, it probably makes more sense to use something called <code>references</code>. According to the Rails <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/88aa2efd692619e87eee88dfc48d608bea9bcdb4/activerecord/lib/active_record/connection_adapters/abstract/schema_definitions.rb#L421">source code</a>, <code>references</code> is just an alias of <code>belongs_to</code>. But, a <code>Book</code> doesn&rsquo;t really &ldquo;belong to&rdquo; a <code>Genre</code>, it&rsquo;s more that it should be able to &ldquo;reference&rdquo; the genre that it&rsquo;s associated with. We can add a reference fairly easily just like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_reference :books, :genre
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This will create a <code>genre_id</code> column inside of our <code>Books</code> table. We could also have done this initially inside of a <code>change</code> method, and written something like <code>t.references(:genre)</code> inside of our migration method. We also have the option to add a <code>type</code>, and specify whether the reference is a <code>polymorphic</code> association or not, as explained by the <a href="http://apidock.com/rails/ActiveRecord/ConnectionAdapters/Table/references">Rails API</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p><code>references</code>: Adds a reference. Optionally adds a type column, if :polymorphic option is provided. The reference column will be an integer by default, the :type option can be used to specify a different type. A foreign key will be created if a foreign_key option is passed.</p></blockquote>

<p>Using <code>references</code> instead of a typical <code>has_many</code> and <code>belongs_to</code> gives us a bit more flexibility moving forward, especially if we know that we&rsquo;ll be adding different types of associations in the long run.</p>

<h2>Reverse, reverse!</h2>

<p>One big feature we want to add to our Bookstore app is giving our <code>Books</code> a rating. There&rsquo;ll be some slightly complicated logic on the backend for this feature to actually work, since we&rsquo;ll need to update a <code>Book</code>&rsquo;s rating every single time a <code>User</code> rates it. But, let&rsquo;s not worry too much about how that logic will be implemented just yet. Instead, it&rsquo;ll be more helpful to break down this larger problem into a few smaller, bite-sized pieces.</p>

<p>First things first: do what we know. And we know that we&rsquo;ll need to give every <code>Book</code> a <code>rating</code> attribute. We&rsquo;ll want this to use Ruby BigDecimal, so we&rsquo;ll specify that in our migration. This migration will start out pretty simple, since all we want to do is just give our <code>Book</code>s a new attribute:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddRatingColumnToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_column :books, :rating, :decimal
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>If we run <code>rake db:migrate</code>, and then open up our console, we can very quickly check that this added a column, just as we expected:</p>

<pre><code>♥ rails c
&gt; Book.all.pluck(:rating)
# =&gt; [nil, nil, nil, nil, nil, nil]
</code></pre>

<p>Uh oh, that&rsquo;s not so great. We really don&rsquo;t want all of the <code>Book</code>s that are <em>already</em> inside of our database to have <code>nil</code> values for their <code>rating</code>. Honestly, a more accurate representation of their <code>rating</code> would just be <code>0</code>, since none of our <code>User</code>s have actually given these products a rating yet.</p>

<p>What would be really nice is if we could do <em>two</em> things within this single migration: give our <code>Books</code> a <code>rating</code> column (done!), and set all of our pre-existing <code>Books</code> to have a <code>rating</code> of <code>0</code>. How can we do that? Well, by using <code>reversible</code>, of course!</p>

<p>We already know that we can use the <code>up</code> and <code>down</code> methods to migrate &ldquo;up&rdquo; and &ldquo;down&rdquo; the history or &ldquo;life&rdquo; of our database. But there&rsquo;s also another handy method that can help us out here, called <code>reversible</code>. Here&rsquo;s what the <a href="http://edgeguides.rubyonrails.org/active_record_migrations.html">Rails Guides</a> say about <code>reversible</code>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Complex migrations may require processing that Active Record doesn&rsquo;t know how to reverse. You can use <code>reversible</code> to specify what to do when running a migration and what else to do when reverting it. Using <code>reversible</code> will ensure that the instructions are executed in the right order too.</p></blockquote>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/11EAsNbNMMcO3u" width="480" height="148" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>So how can we implement <code>reversible</code> here? Well, to start, we need a reversible block, which takes a direction. If you&rsquo;re thinking that the direction should be <code>up</code> or <code>down</code>, you&rsquo;d be right! Since we&rsquo;re only adding a column in this migration, we don&rsquo;t need to worry about a <code>down</code> method, since migrating down will automatically just drop the <code>rating</code> column that we&rsquo;re adding. What we do need to do is make sure that when we migrate <em>up</em>, we&rsquo;re also updating our current <code>Book</code> records. We can do that by specifying the <code>up</code> method on our direction, and then pass a block to <code>reversible</code> telling it what to do:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddRatingColumnToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_column :books, :rating, :decimal

    reversible do |direction|
      direction.up { Book.update_all(rating: 0.0) }
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Cool, this migration seems great. Now, we&rsquo;re not only adding a <code>rating</code> column to our <code>Books</code> table, but we&rsquo;re also updating all of our pre-existing <code>Book</code> objects so that they have some default value for their <code>rating</code>. Nothing about this should break ever, right?</p>

<p>Wrong! Why? Because we can rename anything we want at any time&hellip;and then forget to change all of our files. When we decide to start selling music or movies and go full-on Amazon in our application, we&rsquo;ll probably want to rename our <code>Books</code> table to something like <code>Product</code> or <code>Item</code>. We&rsquo;ll create a new migration to rename our table, change our model names, and everything will be fine. Except for one teeny, tiny little problem: when we decide to deploy to Heroku and try to run <code>rake db:migrate</code>, everything will explode. And why might that happen? Well, because we renamed our table, and now we&rsquo;re trying to run a migration on a <code>Books</code> table for a <code>Book</code> model, which, at this moment in time, <em>doesn&rsquo;t even exist</em>.</p>

<p>So, how can we fix this? Well, we can actually define a <code>Book</code> model inside of this very migration file. And, we can do it all in a single line:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddRatingColumnToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  class Book &lt; ActiveRecord::Base; end

  def change
    add_column :books, :rating, :decimal

    reversible do |direction|
      direction.up { Book.update_all(rating: 0.0) }
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Nice! Now, even if we forget to rename our old migrations, we can be sure that ActiveRecord won&rsquo;t complain if it can&rsquo;t find a <code>Book</code> model when this migration tries to run. In fact, it will <em>always</em> find a model no matter what we might rename our model or table to in the future because we&rsquo;ve defined an empty <code>Book</code> class inside of this migration file. We can be sure that this is the case because Ruby will first look for a class declaration inside of a file before searching anywhere else!</p>

<h2>Index All The Things</h2>

<p>Okay, time to get efficient. Let&rsquo;s look back at our first migration, where we were adding <code>Genre</code>s to <code>Book</code>s:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_reference :books, :genre
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This is fine, but there&rsquo;s one slight problem here: what if we only have a few <code>Genre</code>s, but a ton of <code>Book</code>s? When we want to run a method like <code>where</code> or <code>sort_by</code>, how will our application handle this? Well, without even testing out our query, we know it&rsquo;s not going to go so well. And why not? Because, as it stands, our application will have to sort through <em>every single one</em> of our books to find the ones that match our query. And after a couple hundred or thousands of books, this is going to massively slow down our application.</p>

<p>But, we&rsquo;re smart enough to foresee that problem! We&rsquo;ll outsmart our application from the get-go, and just write a smart migration to begin with:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_reference :books, :genre, index: true
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>If we open up our <code>db/structure.sql</code>, we&rsquo;ll see this:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">CREATE TABLE books (
  rating numeric(10,2),
  genre_id integer
);

CREATE INDEX index_books_on_genre_id ON books USING btree (genre_id);
</code></pre>

<p>This created an <code>index</code> on our <code>Books</code> table, which is referenced to <code>Genre</code>. This is pretty amazing, because it means that our table will now use integers (not strings or any other data type) to look up an item on our table. Integer lookup is the cheapest and fastest way to look up an item in a database, which means that it&rsquo;s going to speed up our database like crazy!</p>

<p>We also could have just written a completely new migraiton for this as well, which would implement the <code>add_index</code> method:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreIndexToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_index(:books, :genre)
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>We could also use the <code>add_index</code> method to create unique indexes, or named indexes, as highlighted in the <a href="http://apidock.com/rails/ActiveRecord/ConnectionAdapters/SchemaStatements/add_index">documentation</a>. Sometimes, it&rsquo;s actually <a href="http://makandracards.com/makandra/32353-psa-index-true-in-rails-migrations-does-not-work-as-you-d-expect">safer</a> to use the <code>add_index</code> method rather than <code>index: true</code>.</p>

<p>Now our migrations are not just clear and concise, but they&rsquo;re also helping our application run smoother and quicker in the process. Writing smart migrations can not only save us a lot of time down the road, but they make feature-writing a lot more fun! Not as fun as running wildly through the safari, but hey &ndash; it&rsquo;s a close second:</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/cyrx5VQ8PiWoE" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Using <code>references</code> in a migration is the same as <code>belongs_to</code>, but can make your code more clear. The <code>reversible</code> method is great for specifying how your migration should handle a reverse migration. Indexes are an easy way of adding an iteger column to speed up database queries.</li>
<li>Need to see another example of manipulating data from within a migraiton? This <a href="http://railsguides.net/change-data-in-migrations-like-a-boss/">blog post</a> walks through some great examples using the <code>up</code> and <code>down</code> methods.</li>
<li>Check out this great <a href="https://www.reinteractive.net/posts/178-reversible-migrations-with-active-record">post</a> on how to implement <code>reversible</code> in different situations!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Secret Life of Your Database, Part 2: Join Tables]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/05/26/the-secret-life-of-your-database-part-2-join-tables/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-26T08:02:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/05/26/the-secret-life-of-your-database-part-2-join-tables</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://daviddickball.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/sql-join.gif" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>When it comes to databases, there are generally two schools of thought. There are those people who love them, and there are those people who just hate them. While I wholeheartedly admit that I belong to the former camp of believers, I can understand why someone would subscribe to the latter group. Databases are hard! They&rsquo;re beautiful and super fun once you understand how to manipulate them, but until you get to that point, they&rsquo;re pretty much just hard.</p>

<p>I think that a large part of what makes databases hard to understand is the sheer amount of things you can do with the data it contains. Between database migrations, which we unpacked <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/05/19/the-secret-life-of-your-database-part-1-migrations/">last week</a>, and writing SQL queries that actually do what you want them to do, it&rsquo;s really easy to just throw your hands up in the air and give up completely. But, you shouldn&rsquo;t! And I hope that, after reading this post, you won&rsquo;t! Because <em>databases are beautiful</em> (that should be on a t-shirt somewhere), and you just have to get to know them a little bit.</p>

<p>So, what should we get to know about them? Well, the scariest part, of course: <strong>join tables</strong>. Join tables are used to combine two sets of data from two different tables. Depending on what you query the database for, different values can be returned. No matter the size of your application, you&rsquo;re probably going to have at least a few tables, and usually many more. Most of the time, the data in a single table by itself isn&rsquo;t super useful; when it&rsquo;s combined with another database&rsquo;s information, however, then things really get cooking. Join tables are how we get specific information from two different datasets (or two different database tables). There are seven different types of join tables, but there are three in particular that I&rsquo;ve encountered time and again. Let&rsquo;s explore the differences between inner joins, left outer joins, and right outer joins.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Know Thy Data</h2>

<p>Before we get too deep into join syntax, let&rsquo;s take a look at our data! We&rsquo;ll stick with the schema from our eCommerce bookstore application. Since we don&rsquo;t have any real users yet, we can just populate our database with some fake, super fun seed data.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer</em>: I may or may not have gotten carried away when making the seed data. Anyways, here&rsquo;s what our databases look like:
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/voemAen.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll be working with the same two tables: a <code>Users</code> table, and an <code>Orders</code> table. Each <code>User</code> instance has a <code>first_name</code> and a <code>last_name</code> (and realistically speaking, probably a bunch of other attributes&hellip;but let&rsquo;s keep it simple for now).</p>

<p>Each <code>Order</code> object <code>belongs_to</code> a <code>User</code>, which means it has a <code>user_id</code> column to store the foreign key from the <code>Users</code> table. Each <code>Order</code> also has a unique, randomly-generated <code>number</code> (think order confirmation number), and an order <code>total</code>, which is stored as a <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/02/10/money-makes-the-world-go-round-using-money-rails-and-bigdecimal/">Ruby BigDecimal object</a>.</p>

<h2>Inner Joins</h2>

<p>The most common and easiest join table syntax to understand is the <em>inner join</em>. Inner joins are our tool of choice if we&rsquo;re looking for a specific set of data that only matches the parameters we identify in our query.</p>

<p>For example, say we&rsquo;re looking for a subset of data that shows <em>only</em> <code>users</code> with <code>orders</code>. We&rsquo;re not interested in any <code>Users</code> that haven&rsquo;t placed an order; we only want the data of a <code>User</code> that actually <em>has</em> placed an order. This is a set of data that might be useful for something like an admin panel that we might want to build out in our next feature, so let&rsquo;s return just some basic information right now, like the <code>User</code>&rsquo;s <code>last_name</code> and their <code>user_id</code>.</p>

<p>So, what would that look like in a SQL query? Well, we know that we want to select only the <code>last_name</code> and the <code>id</code> of the <code>User</code> instance. But, we don&rsquo;t want ALL <code>Users</code> by their <code>ids</code>; we actually want only the <code>Users</code> that are associated with an <code>user_id</code> on an <code>Order</code>. So, that&rsquo;s what we&rsquo;ll select:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT users.last_name, orders.user_id
FROM users
</code></pre>

<p>Cool, we&rsquo;re halfway there. Now for the join. Let&rsquo;s think for a second&hellip;we want to <em>join</em> the data in our <code>Users</code> table with the data in our <code>Orders</code> table. And, we want to match the rows by <code>ids</code>. What does that mean, exactly? Well, it means that we only want to return an <code>User</code> row where that <code>User's</code> <code>id</code> exists in a row of the <code>Order</code> database, where it&rsquo;ll be under the <code>user_id</code> foreign key column. We&rsquo;ll also order our data by the <code>Order's</code> <code>id</code> for now, but we&rsquo;ll change that as we play around a bit more. So let&rsquo;s add all that to our query:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT users.last_name, orders.user_id
FROM users
INNER JOIN orders
ON users.id=orders.user_id
ORDER BY orders.id;
</code></pre>

<p>And if we run this query, what&rsquo;ll happen? We&rsquo;ll get this fabulousness:
<br><br>
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/sWlj3zx.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>Nice! So, we get five records returned to us, and it returns exactly what we asked for: the <code>User's</code> <code>last_name</code> and the <code>Order's</code> <code>user_id</code>. But there are some <code>User</code> instances that are there twice, and one of the <code>Users</code> (which is apparently T.S. Eliot) doesn&rsquo;t even show up in our records!</p>

<p>If we take a closer look at our <code>Orders</code> database table, that&rsquo;s exactly what we should <em>expect</em> to happen. The <code>User</code> with an <code>id</code> of <code>1</code> placed two <code>Orders</code>, so there are two records with his <code>last_name</code> and <code>id</code> that are returned to us. And Eliot, who hasn&rsquo;t placed any <code>Orders</code> yet, isn&rsquo;t returned to us at all! That makes sense though, since we&rsquo;re asking for a subset of information &ndash; only the rows that fit the requirements of our query &ndash; or, the inner information of our database, and nothing superfluous, meaning that all the outer, extra information is ignored.</p>

<h2>Left Outer Joins</h2>

<p>Now that we&rsquo;ve covered the relatively easier inner join, it&rsquo;s time to get to the slightly trickier stuff: outer joins! Outer joins come in two shapes and sizes: <strong>left outer joins</strong> and <strong>right outer joins</strong>. The concept behind the two is fundamentally the same, but they kind of work like opposites. Let&rsquo;s look at a left
outer join to start.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say that our admins actually want to see all the <code>Users</code> at once in the admin panel, regardless of whether they&rsquo;ve placed an order or not. This means that we want to widen our data query to ALL <code>Users</code>, and all the <code>Orders</code> associated with any of those <code>Users</code>. We&rsquo;ll begin our SQl query the same way as before, selecting the <code>User's</code> <code>last_name</code>.</p>

<p>But our admin&rsquo;s also want to see the <code>Order</code> <code>totals</code> for each <code>User</code> &ndash; if the <code>User</code> has placed an order, obviously. So, we&rsquo;ll add that to our select statement as well.</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT users.last_name, orders.total
FROM users
</code></pre>

<p>Now, we want to join our <code>Users</code> table with our <code>Orders</code> table again. Except this time, we don&rsquo;t want to do an inner join. Instead, we want all the data from our <code>Users</code> table, and any data that might correspond to all of our <code>Users</code> from the <code>Orders</code> database. We&rsquo;ll still do something similar to before and join our tables on the <code>id</code> columns, but we&rsquo;ll order by each <code>User's</code> <code>id</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT users.last_name, orders.total
FROM users
LEFT OUTER JOIN orders
ON users.id=orders.user_id
ORDER BY users.id;
</code></pre>

<p>If we look at our data, we&rsquo;ll remember that the <code>User</code> with an <code>id</code> of <code>4</code> never placed any orders! How might this affect what data is returned to us? Let&rsquo;s run our query and find out:</p>

<p><br><br>
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/STqLeW3.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>Whoa! Since our <code>User</code> T.S. Eliot never placed an order, he didn&rsquo;t have any row in the <code>Orders</code> database that corresponded to him. Because there was no <code>Order</code> <code>total</code> column that was attributed to his <code>id</code>, what got returned instead? <code>NULL</code>!</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s exactly what outer joins will do if they don&rsquo;t find anything! If there is no match on the right table that is being &ldquo;joined&rdquo; (in our case, the <code>Orders</code> database), the default return value will always be <code>NULL</code>. Now that we know that&hellip;how do you think that a right outer join might work?</p>

<h2>Right Outer Joins</h2>

<p>A <strong>right outer join</strong> is almost the same as a left outer join. The difference is that the table that you&rsquo;re joining is on the <em>right</em>. What does that mean for your return set of data?</p>

<p>Well, it means that all the data on the <em>right</em> table will be returned &ndash; even if it doesn&rsquo;t have a corresponding value. Our query might look something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT orders.number, orders.total
FROM users
RIGHT OUTER JOIN orders
ON users.id=orders.user_id
ORDER BY orders.id;
</code></pre>

<p>Here, we are ordering by the <code>Order's</code> <code>id</code>, and we&rsquo;re only looking at the <code>Order</code> <code>number</code> and <code>total</code>. When we run our query, this is what we&rsquo;ll get:</p>

<p><br><br>
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/LJoNd8I.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>In our case, our data doesn&rsquo;t look super different with a right outer join. In fact, it looks a lot like the inner join we started with! So why do right inner joins matter, then?</p>

<p>Well, what if our admins change their minds (again!) and instead want ONLY orders to be returned. And what if you have an order that doesn&rsquo;t have a <code>User</code>, because that user deleted their account? Well, in that case, our <code>Order</code> would still show up in the returned data, and if we selected the corresponding <code>User</code> <code>ids</code>, then the deleted <code>User</code> would have a <code>NULL</code> <code>id</code> value! Pretty cool, right?</p>

<p>See, databases can be pretty awesome once you understand a little bit about how they work! In fact, I love them so much that I give &lsquo;em two thumbs way, way up!</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/5fBH6zoy1szfjORd14s" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Join tables allow us to combine two different sets of data. You can make your data subset be as specific or broad as you want, depending on what you query for!</li>
<li>An inner join will only return values that exist in both tables.</li>
<li>A left outer join will return all the values from the left database, and any values that correspond from the right database. A right outer join will return all the values from the right database, and any values that correspond form the left. Any values that don&rsquo;t have a corresponding row will be returned as <code>NULL</code>.</li>
<li>Still curious about inner vs outer joins? Check out <a href="http://www.programmerinterview.com/index.php/database-sql/inner-vs-outer-joins/">this blog post</a>.</li>
<li>Want to know about ALL the different join tables out there? Here&rsquo;s a dope <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/equivalent/scrapbook2/master/assets/images/2014/sql-joins.png">graphic</a> that explains it well.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
