<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sql | Words and Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/categories/sql/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-14T09:06:30-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vaidehi Joshi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing Smart Migrations: References, Reversible, and Indexes]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/14/writing-smart-migrations-references-reversible-and-indexes/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-14T08:47:19-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/07/14/writing-smart-migrations-references-reversible-and-indexes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/SUtPZfyDenHoY" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>All it takes is a single feature to make you realize how well &ndash; or perhaps not so well &ndash; you&rsquo;ve written your application. Depending on if you&rsquo;ve done a good job of separating concerns, abstracting and encapsulating bits of functionality into cohesive code, and just generally not repeating yourself&hellip;well, you&rsquo;ll probably be way more enthusiastic about adding a huge new feature to an already massive application. But if you haven&rsquo;t done any of those things&hellip;well, you might find yourself doing a massive rewrite of your codebase just to implement a single feature.</p>

<p>Luckily, the application I started adding a feature to last week is pretty well-built, which makes it flexible enough to add new functionality relatively easily. Yet even the most well-thought-out applications need to be teased apart and glued back together during the course of their lives. Often times, a big part of building out a new feature is restructuring the architecture of your application. When you&rsquo;re working with larger code bases (legacy code in particular), that can be the most daunting task. But a lot of the intimidation of that begins to dissipate once you know how to go about restructuring a schema which already exists without breaking all the the things.</p>

<p>The first step in this process is writing migrations to change how the objects in your application and database relate to one another. Of course, knowing how to write the proper migration to suit your needs is just half the battle; the other half is writing a migration that makes object lookup in your database efficient and super fast. Even though I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/05/19/the-secret-life-of-your-database-part-1-migrations/">written about migrations</a> before, I&rsquo;m learning that there&rsquo;s always so much more to know. So, let&rsquo;s get learning!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Referencing Your References</h2>

<p>A really quick way to clean up our code is by changing the way that we create associations between objects from within our migrations. One feature we&rsquo;ll want to add is to have our <code>Book</code>s belong to a <code>Genre</code>. So far, we&rsquo;ve categorized our <code>Author</code>s by genre, but we&rsquo;ll want to be able to sort and organize our <code>Book</code> objects in a similar way.</p>

<p>We often use <code>belongs_to</code> and <code>has_many</code> inside of our migrations, which is totally valid. But in this case, it probably makes more sense to use something called <code>references</code>. According to the Rails <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/88aa2efd692619e87eee88dfc48d608bea9bcdb4/activerecord/lib/active_record/connection_adapters/abstract/schema_definitions.rb#L421">source code</a>, <code>references</code> is just an alias of <code>belongs_to</code>. But, a <code>Book</code> doesn&rsquo;t really &ldquo;belong to&rdquo; a <code>Genre</code>, it&rsquo;s more that it should be able to &ldquo;reference&rdquo; the genre that it&rsquo;s associated with. We can add a reference fairly easily just like this:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_reference :books, :genre
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This will create a <code>genre_id</code> column inside of our <code>Books</code> table. We could also have done this initially inside of a <code>change</code> method, and written something like <code>t.references(:genre)</code> inside of our migration method. We also have the option to add a <code>type</code>, and specify whether the reference is a <code>polymorphic</code> association or not, as explained by the <a href="http://apidock.com/rails/ActiveRecord/ConnectionAdapters/Table/references">Rails API</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p><code>references</code>: Adds a reference. Optionally adds a type column, if :polymorphic option is provided. The reference column will be an integer by default, the :type option can be used to specify a different type. A foreign key will be created if a foreign_key option is passed.</p></blockquote>

<p>Using <code>references</code> instead of a typical <code>has_many</code> and <code>belongs_to</code> gives us a bit more flexibility moving forward, especially if we know that we&rsquo;ll be adding different types of associations in the long run.</p>

<h2>Reverse, reverse!</h2>

<p>One big feature we want to add to our Bookstore app is giving our <code>Books</code> a rating. There&rsquo;ll be some slightly complicated logic on the backend for this feature to actually work, since we&rsquo;ll need to update a <code>Book</code>&rsquo;s rating every single time a <code>User</code> rates it. But, let&rsquo;s not worry too much about how that logic will be implemented just yet. Instead, it&rsquo;ll be more helpful to break down this larger problem into a few smaller, bite-sized pieces.</p>

<p>First things first: do what we know. And we know that we&rsquo;ll need to give every <code>Book</code> a <code>rating</code> attribute. We&rsquo;ll want this to use Ruby BigDecimal, so we&rsquo;ll specify that in our migration. This migration will start out pretty simple, since all we want to do is just give our <code>Book</code>s a new attribute:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddRatingColumnToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_column :books, :rating, :decimal
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>If we run <code>rake db:migrate</code>, and then open up our console, we can very quickly check that this added a column, just as we expected:</p>

<pre><code>♥ rails c
&gt; Book.all.pluck(:rating)
# =&gt; [nil, nil, nil, nil, nil, nil]
</code></pre>

<p>Uh oh, that&rsquo;s not so great. We really don&rsquo;t want all of the <code>Book</code>s that are <em>already</em> inside of our database to have <code>nil</code> values for their <code>rating</code>. Honestly, a more accurate representation of their <code>rating</code> would just be <code>0</code>, since none of our <code>User</code>s have actually given these products a rating yet.</p>

<p>What would be really nice is if we could do <em>two</em> things within this single migration: give our <code>Books</code> a <code>rating</code> column (done!), and set all of our pre-existing <code>Books</code> to have a <code>rating</code> of <code>0</code>. How can we do that? Well, by using <code>reversible</code>, of course!</p>

<p>We already know that we can use the <code>up</code> and <code>down</code> methods to migrate &ldquo;up&rdquo; and &ldquo;down&rdquo; the history or &ldquo;life&rdquo; of our database. But there&rsquo;s also another handy method that can help us out here, called <code>reversible</code>. Here&rsquo;s what the <a href="http://edgeguides.rubyonrails.org/active_record_migrations.html">Rails Guides</a> say about <code>reversible</code>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Complex migrations may require processing that Active Record doesn&rsquo;t know how to reverse. You can use <code>reversible</code> to specify what to do when running a migration and what else to do when reverting it. Using <code>reversible</code> will ensure that the instructions are executed in the right order too.</p></blockquote>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/11EAsNbNMMcO3u" width="480" height="148" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p><br></p>

<p>So how can we implement <code>reversible</code> here? Well, to start, we need a reversible block, which takes a direction. If you&rsquo;re thinking that the direction should be <code>up</code> or <code>down</code>, you&rsquo;d be right! Since we&rsquo;re only adding a column in this migration, we don&rsquo;t need to worry about a <code>down</code> method, since migrating down will automatically just drop the <code>rating</code> column that we&rsquo;re adding. What we do need to do is make sure that when we migrate <em>up</em>, we&rsquo;re also updating our current <code>Book</code> records. We can do that by specifying the <code>up</code> method on our direction, and then pass a block to <code>reversible</code> telling it what to do:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddRatingColumnToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_column :books, :rating, :decimal

    reversible do |direction|
      direction.up { Book.update_all(rating: 0.0) }
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Cool, this migration seems great. Now, we&rsquo;re not only adding a <code>rating</code> column to our <code>Books</code> table, but we&rsquo;re also updating all of our pre-existing <code>Book</code> objects so that they have some default value for their <code>rating</code>. Nothing about this should break ever, right?</p>

<p>Wrong! Why? Because we can rename anything we want at any time&hellip;and then forget to change all of our files. When we decide to start selling music or movies and go full-on Amazon in our application, we&rsquo;ll probably want to rename our <code>Books</code> table to something like <code>Product</code> or <code>Item</code>. We&rsquo;ll create a new migration to rename our table, change our model names, and everything will be fine. Except for one teeny, tiny little problem: when we decide to deploy to Heroku and try to run <code>rake db:migrate</code>, everything will explode. And why might that happen? Well, because we renamed our table, and now we&rsquo;re trying to run a migration on a <code>Books</code> table for a <code>Book</code> model, which, at this moment in time, <em>doesn&rsquo;t even exist</em>.</p>

<p>So, how can we fix this? Well, we can actually define a <code>Book</code> model inside of this very migration file. And, we can do it all in a single line:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddRatingColumnToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  class Book &lt; ActiveRecord::Base; end

  def change
    add_column :books, :rating, :decimal

    reversible do |direction|
      direction.up { Book.update_all(rating: 0.0) }
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Nice! Now, even if we forget to rename our old migrations, we can be sure that ActiveRecord won&rsquo;t complain if it can&rsquo;t find a <code>Book</code> model when this migration tries to run. In fact, it will <em>always</em> find a model no matter what we might rename our model or table to in the future because we&rsquo;ve defined an empty <code>Book</code> class inside of this migration file. We can be sure that this is the case because Ruby will first look for a class declaration inside of a file before searching anywhere else!</p>

<h2>Index All The Things</h2>

<p>Okay, time to get efficient. Let&rsquo;s look back at our first migration, where we were adding <code>Genre</code>s to <code>Book</code>s:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_reference :books, :genre
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>This is fine, but there&rsquo;s one slight problem here: what if we only have a few <code>Genre</code>s, but a ton of <code>Book</code>s? When we want to run a method like <code>where</code> or <code>sort_by</code>, how will our application handle this? Well, without even testing out our query, we know it&rsquo;s not going to go so well. And why not? Because, as it stands, our application will have to sort through <em>every single one</em> of our books to find the ones that match our query. And after a couple hundred or thousands of books, this is going to massively slow down our application.</p>

<p>But, we&rsquo;re smart enough to foresee that problem! We&rsquo;ll outsmart our application from the get-go, and just write a smart migration to begin with:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_reference :books, :genre, index: true
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>If we open up our <code>db/structure.sql</code>, we&rsquo;ll see this:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">CREATE TABLE books (
  rating numeric(10,2),
  genre_id integer
);

CREATE INDEX index_books_on_genre_id ON books USING btree (genre_id);
</code></pre>

<p>This created an <code>index</code> on our <code>Books</code> table, which is referenced to <code>Genre</code>. This is pretty amazing, because it means that our table will now use integers (not strings or any other data type) to look up an item on our table. Integer lookup is the cheapest and fastest way to look up an item in a database, which means that it&rsquo;s going to speed up our database like crazy!</p>

<p>We also could have just written a completely new migraiton for this as well, which would implement the <code>add_index</code> method:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class AddGenreIndexToBooks &lt; ActiveRecord::Migration
  def change
    add_index(:books, :genre)
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>and would add this line to our <code>db/structure.sql</code> file:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">CREATE INDEX suppliers_name_index ON suppliers(name)
</code></pre>

<p>We could also use the <code>add_index</code> method to create unique indexes, or named indexes, as highlighted in the <a href="http://apidock.com/rails/ActiveRecord/ConnectionAdapters/SchemaStatements/add_index">documentation</a>. Sometimes, it&rsquo;s actually <a href="http://makandracards.com/makandra/32353-psa-index-true-in-rails-migrations-does-not-work-as-you-d-expect">safer</a> to use the <code>add_index</code> method rather than <code>index: true</code>.</p>

<p>Now our migrations are not just clear and concise, but they&rsquo;re also helping our application run smoother and quicker in the process. Writing smart migrations can not only save us a lot of time down the road, but they make feature-writing a lot more fun! Not as fun as running wilding through the safari, but hey &ndash; it&rsquo;s a close second:</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/cyrx5VQ8PiWoE" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Using <code>references</code> in a migration is the same as <code>belongs_to</code>, but can make your code more clear. The <code>reversible</code> method is great for specifying how your migration should handle a reverse migration. Indexes are an easy way of adding an iteger column to speed up database queries.</li>
<li>Need to see another example of manipulating data from within a migraiton? This <a href="http://railsguides.net/change-data-in-migrations-like-a-boss/">blog post</a> walks through some great examples using the <code>up</code> and <code>down</code> methods.</li>
<li>Check out this great <a href="https://www.reinteractive.net/posts/178-reversible-migrations-with-active-record">post</a> on how to implement <code>reversible</code> in different situations!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Secret Life of Your Database, Part 2: Join Tables]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/05/26/the-secret-life-of-your-database-part-2-join-tables/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-26T08:02:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/05/26/the-secret-life-of-your-database-part-2-join-tables</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://daviddickball.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/sql-join.gif" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>When it comes to databases, there are generally two schools of thought. There are those people who love them, and there are those people who just hate them. While I wholeheartedly admit that I belong to the former camp of believers, I can understand why someone would subscribe to the latter group. Databases are hard! They&rsquo;re beautiful and super fun once you understand how to manipulate them, but until you get to that point, they&rsquo;re pretty much just hard.</p>

<p>I think that a large part of what makes databases hard to understand is the sheer amount of things you can do with the data it contains. Between database migrations, which we unpacked <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/05/19/the-secret-life-of-your-database-part-1-migrations/">last week</a>, and writing SQL queries that actually do what you want them to do, it&rsquo;s really easy to just throw your hands up in the air and give up completely. But, you shouldn&rsquo;t! And I hope that, after reading this post, you won&rsquo;t! Because <em>databases are beautiful</em> (that should be on a t-shirt somewhere), and you just have to get to know them a little bit.</p>

<p>So, what should we get to know about them? Well, the scariest part, of course: <strong>join tables</strong>. Join tables are used to combine two sets of data from two different tables. Depending on what you query the database for, different values can be returned. No matter the size of your application, you&rsquo;re probably going to have at least a few tables, and usually many more. Most of the time, the data in a single table by itself isn&rsquo;t super useful; when it&rsquo;s combined with another database&rsquo;s information, however, then things really get cooking. Join tables are how we get specific information from two different datasets (or two different database tables). There are seven different types of join tables, but there are three in particular that I&rsquo;ve encountered time and again. Let&rsquo;s explore the differences between inner joins, left outer joins, and right outer joins.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Know Thy Data</h2>

<p>Before we get too deep into join syntax, let&rsquo;s take a look at our data! We&rsquo;ll stick with the schema from our eCommerce bookstore application. Since we don&rsquo;t have any real users yet, we can just populate our database with some fake, super fun seed data.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer</em>: I may or may not have gotten carried away when making the seed data. Anyways, here&rsquo;s what our databases look like:
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/voemAen.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll be working with the same two tables: a <code>Users</code> table, and an <code>Orders</code> table. Each <code>User</code> instance has a <code>first_name</code> and a <code>last_name</code> (and realistically speaking, probably a bunch of other attributes&hellip;but let&rsquo;s keep it simple for now).</p>

<p>Each <code>Order</code> object <code>belongs_to</code> a <code>User</code>, which means it has a <code>user_id</code> column to store the foreign key from the <code>Users</code> table. Each <code>Order</code> also has a unique, randomly-generated <code>number</code> (think order confirmation number), and an order <code>total</code>, which is stored as a <a href="http://vaidehijoshi.github.io/blog/2015/02/10/money-makes-the-world-go-round-using-money-rails-and-bigdecimal/">Ruby BigDecimal object</a>.</p>

<h2>Inner Joins</h2>

<p>The most common and easiest join table syntax to understand is the <em>inner join</em>. Inner joins are our tool of choice if we&rsquo;re looking for a specific set of data that only matches the parameters we identify in our query.</p>

<p>For example, say we&rsquo;re looking for a subset of data that shows <em>only</em> <code>users</code> with <code>orders</code>. We&rsquo;re not interested in any <code>Users</code> that haven&rsquo;t placed an order; we only want the data of a <code>User</code> that actually <em>has</em> placed an order. This is a set of data that might be useful for something like an admin panel that we might want to build out in our next feature, so let&rsquo;s return just some basic information right now, like the <code>User</code>&rsquo;s <code>last_name</code> and their <code>user_id</code>.</p>

<p>So, what would that look like in a SQL query? Well, we know that we want to select only the <code>last_name</code> and the <code>id</code> of the <code>User</code> instance. But, we don&rsquo;t want ALL <code>Users</code> by their <code>ids</code>; we actually want only the <code>Users</code> that are associated with an <code>user_id</code> on an <code>Order</code>. So, that&rsquo;s what we&rsquo;ll select:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT users.last_name, orders.user_id
FROM users
</code></pre>

<p>Cool, we&rsquo;re halfway there. Now for the join. Let&rsquo;s think for a second&hellip;we want to <em>join</em> the data in our <code>Users</code> table with the data in our <code>Orders</code> table. And, we want to match the rows by <code>ids</code>. What does that mean, exactly? Well, it means that we only want to return an <code>User</code> row where that <code>User's</code> <code>id</code> exists in a row of the <code>Order</code> database, where it&rsquo;ll be under the <code>user_id</code> foreign key column. We&rsquo;ll also order our data by the <code>Order's</code> <code>id</code> for now, but we&rsquo;ll change that as we play around a bit more. So let&rsquo;s add all that to our query:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT users.last_name, orders.user_id
FROM users
INNER JOIN orders
ON users.id=orders.user_id
ORDER BY orders.id;
</code></pre>

<p>And if we run this query, what&rsquo;ll happen? We&rsquo;ll get this fabulousness:
<br><br>
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/sWlj3zx.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>Nice! So, we get five records returned to us, and it returns exactly what we asked for: the <code>User's</code> <code>last_name</code> and the <code>Order's</code> <code>user_id</code>. But there are some <code>User</code> instances that are there twice, and one of the <code>Users</code> (which is apparently T.S. Eliot) doesn&rsquo;t even show up in our records!</p>

<p>If we take a closer look at our <code>Orders</code> database table, that&rsquo;s exactly what we should <em>expect</em> to happen. The <code>User</code> with an <code>id</code> of <code>1</code> placed two <code>Orders</code>, so there are two records with his <code>last_name</code> and <code>id</code> that are returned to us. And Eliot, who hasn&rsquo;t placed any <code>Orders</code> yet, isn&rsquo;t returned to us at all! That makes sense though, since we&rsquo;re asking for a subset of information &ndash; only the rows that fit the requirements of our query &ndash; or, the inner information of our database, and nothing superfluous, meaning that all the outer, extra information is ignored.</p>

<h2>Left Outer Joins</h2>

<p>Now that we&rsquo;ve covered the relatively easier inner join, it&rsquo;s time to get to the slightly trickier stuff: outer joins! Outer joins come in two shapes and sizes: <strong>left outer joins</strong> and <strong>right outer joins</strong>. The concept behind the two is fundamentally the same, but they kind of work like opposites. Let&rsquo;s look at a left
outer join to start.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say that our admins actually want to see all the <code>Users</code> at once in the admin panel, regardless of whether they&rsquo;ve placed an order or not. This means that we want to widen our data query to ALL <code>Users</code>, and all the <code>Orders</code> associated with any of those <code>Users</code>. We&rsquo;ll begin our SQl query the same way as before, selecting the <code>User's</code> <code>last_name</code>.</p>

<p>But our admin&rsquo;s also want to see the <code>Order</code> <code>totals</code> for each <code>User</code> &ndash; if the <code>User</code> has placed an order, obviously. So, we&rsquo;ll add that to our select statement as well.</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT users.last_name, orders.total
FROM users
</code></pre>

<p>Now, we want to join our <code>Users</code> table with our <code>Orders</code> table again. Except this time, we don&rsquo;t want to do an inner join. Instead, we want all the data from our <code>Users</code> table, and any data that might correspond to all of our <code>Users</code> from the <code>Orders</code> database. We&rsquo;ll still do something similar to before and join our tables on the <code>id</code> columns, but we&rsquo;ll order by each <code>User's</code> <code>id</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT users.last_name, orders.total
FROM users
LEFT OUTER JOIN orders
ON users.id=orders.user_id
ORDER BY users.id;
</code></pre>

<p>If we look at our data, we&rsquo;ll remember that the <code>User</code> with an <code>id</code> of <code>4</code> never placed any orders! How might this affect what data is returned to us? Let&rsquo;s run our query and find out:</p>

<p><br><br>
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/STqLeW3.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>Whoa! Since our <code>User</code> T.S. Eliot never placed an order, he didn&rsquo;t have any row in the <code>Orders</code> database that corresponded to him. Because there was no <code>Order</code> <code>total</code> column that was attributed to his <code>id</code>, what got returned instead? <code>NULL</code>!</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s exactly what outer joins will do if they don&rsquo;t find anything! If there is no match on the right table that is being &ldquo;joined&rdquo; (in our case, the <code>Orders</code> database), the default return value will always be <code>NULL</code>. Now that we know that&hellip;how do you think that a right outer join might work?</p>

<h2>Right Outer Joins</h2>

<p>A <strong>right outer join</strong> is almost the same as a left outer join. The difference is that the table that you&rsquo;re joining is on the <em>right</em>. What does that mean for your return set of data?</p>

<p>Well, it means that all the data on the <em>right</em> table will be returned &ndash; even if it doesn&rsquo;t have a corresponding value. Our query might look something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="sql">SELECT orders.number, orders.total
FROM users
RIGHT OUTER JOIN orders
ON users.id=orders.user_id
ORDER BY orders.id;
</code></pre>

<p>Here, we are ordering by the <code>Order's</code> <code>id</code>, and we&rsquo;re only looking at the <code>Order</code> <code>number</code> and <code>total</code>. When we run our query, this is what we&rsquo;ll get:</p>

<p><br><br>
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/LJoNd8I.png" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>

<p>In our case, our data doesn&rsquo;t look super different with a right outer join. In fact, it looks a lot like the inner join we started with! So why do right inner joins matter, then?</p>

<p>Well, what if our admins change their minds (again!) and instead want ONLY orders to be returned. And what if you have an order that doesn&rsquo;t have a <code>User</code>, because that user deleted their account? Well, in that case, our <code>Order</code> would still show up in the returned data, and if we selected the corresponding <code>User</code> <code>ids</code>, then the deleted <code>User</code> would have a <code>NULL</code> <code>id</code> value! Pretty cool, right?</p>

<p>See, databases can be pretty awesome once you understand a little bit about how they work! In fact, I love them so much that I give &lsquo;em two thumbs way, way up!</p>

<iframe src="//giphy.com/embed/5fBH6zoy1szfjORd14s" width="480" height="270" frameBorder="0" style="max-width: 100%" class="giphy-embed" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h2>tl;dr?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Join tables allow us to combine two different sets of data. You can make your data subset be as specific or broad as you want, depending on what you query for!</li>
<li>An inner join will only return values that exist in both tables.</li>
<li>A left outer join will return all the values from the left database, and any values that correspond from the right database. A right outer join will return all the values from the right database, and any values that correspond form the left. Any values that don&rsquo;t have a corresponding row will be returned as <code>NULL</code>.</li>
<li>Still curious about inner vs outer joins? Check out <a href="http://www.programmerinterview.com/index.php/database-sql/inner-vs-outer-joins/">this blog post</a>.</li>
<li>Want to know about ALL the different join tables out there? Here&rsquo;s a dope <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/equivalent/scrapbook2/master/assets/images/2014/sql-joins.png">graphic</a> that explains it well.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
